<chapter id="Preparing-for-Observations">
  <info>
    <title>Preparing for Observations</title>
    <date>$Date: 2017-06-01 17:33:47 +1000 (Thu, 01 Jun 2017) $</date>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.5</revnumber>
	<date>2017 June 1</date>
	<authorinitials>jbs</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Added information about how to use the rapid response mode</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.4</revnumber>
	<date>2016 May 9</date>
	<authorinitials>jbs</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Updated information about the new high-frequency 1934-638 flux density model</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.3</revnumber>
	<date>2015 Oct 21</date>
	<authorinitials>jbs</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Updated information about remote observing procedures</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
	<date>2014 Oct 15</date>
	<authorinitials>jbs</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Fix a couple of typos regarding 1934-638 flux density models</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
	<date>2014 May 28</date>
	<authorinitials>jbs</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Rewrite chapter in FAQ format</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>2014 Mar 20</date>
	<authorinitials>jbs</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial Docbook revision</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </info>

  <para>
    <indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>preparing</secondary></indexterm>
    This chapter deals with how to prepare for observations on the
    <acronym>ATCA</acronym> after having been granted observing time.
    It is presented as an FAQ, so that new observers can get all the information
    they need, and experienced observers can quickly find the information
    they need.
  </para>

  <para>
    <indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>considerations</secondary></indexterm>
    Broadly speaking you will need to address at least the following considerations
    when planning an observation with the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  How much integration time is required on source to reach
	  the necessary sensitivity?
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  What calibration is required to ensure the observations succeed, and how
	  much observing time will it require?
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  How can observational overheads be minimised?
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  How will weather and <acronym>RFI</acronym> affect the observations?
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>
    After reading this chapter you should be able to optimally plan an observation,
    and know how to make the schedule that carries it out.
  </para>

  <section id="observations-sensitivity">
    <info>
      <title>Observational Sensitivity</title>
    </info>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>How long is my source up per day?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATCA</primary><secondary>declination coverage</secondary></indexterm>
	The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> antennas have a hard elevation limit of
	12&#x00B0;, and for observations in the millimetre bands it is
	recommended that you stay above an elevation of 30&#x00B0; in order to
	avoid the thickest parts of the atmosphere.
      </para>

      <para>
	A quick estimate of how long a particular source will be observable on
	a single day with the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> can be made using
	<xref linkend="DeclinationTimes"></xref>. It shows, for a source at a particular declination,
	the LST range before/past transit it is above elevations of 12&#x00B0; 
	and 30&#x00B0;.
      </para>

      <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis> The source 0823-500
	(coordinates RA=08:25:26.869, Dec=-50:10:38.4) will rise above the
	12&#x00B0; elevation limit at an LST of 01:05 (take 07:20 from 08:25),
	and it will fall below 30&#x00B0; at an LST of 13:42 (add 05:17 to 08:25).
	It will be above the 12&#x00B0; elevation limit for 
	approximately 14 h 40 m each day.
      </para>

      <para>
	<table frame="all" id="DeclinationTimes" shortentry="1" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	  <title>
	    For sources at particular declinations, this table displays the amount
	    of time the source would take to get from rise to transit, or from
	    transit to set at the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>. The LST ranges are shown
	    for both the hard 12&#x00B0; and the recommended millimetre 30&#x00B0; elevation
	    limits.
	  </title>
	  <titleabbrev>Observational availability with Declination</titleabbrev>
	  <tgroup cols="3" align="center">
	    <colspec colname="declination"/>
	    <colspec colname="lstrange12"/>
	    <colspec colname="lstrange30"/>
	    <thead>
	      <row>
		<entry morerows="1">Declination</entry>
		<entry namest="lstrange12" nameend="lstrange30">LST range</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>12&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>30&#x00B0;</entry>
	      </row>
	    </thead>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry>-80&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>always above horizon</entry>
		<entry>06:09</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>-70&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>10:35</entry>
		<entry>05:47</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>-60&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>08:14</entry>
		<entry>05:32</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>-50&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>07:20</entry>
		<entry>05:17</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>-40&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>06:44</entry>
		<entry>05:02</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>-30&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>06:17</entry>
		<entry>04:46</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>-20&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>05:53</entry>
		<entry>04:28</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>-10&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>05:31</entry>
		<entry>04:07</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>+0&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>05:07</entry>
		<entry>03:42</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>+10&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>04:42</entry>
		<entry>03:09</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>+20&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>04:12</entry>
		<entry>02:20</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>+30&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>03:32</entry>
		<entry>00:21</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>+40&#x00B0;</entry>
		<entry>02:31</entry>
		<entry>never above horizon</entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</table>
      </para>
      
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observability plotter</primary></indexterm>
	To calculate precisely how long your source is observable each day with the
	<acronym>ATCA</acronym> you can use the
	<ulink url="https://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/web_observability_plotter/">
	Interactive Observability Chart Plotter</ulink>.
	<!-- <command>coord</command> program,
	available from the
	<ulink url="http://www.parkes.atnf.csiro.au/cgi-bin/utilities/coord.cgi">Parkes website.</ulink>
	When using <command>coord</command> from the website you must remember to
	change both the site to &#x201C;Australia Telescope Compact Array&#x201D;,
	and the elevation limit to the value you require. -->
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>Is it possible to tune my observing frequencies to obtain optimal
	sensitivity?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>sensitivity</primary><secondary>optimising</secondary></indexterm>
	<acronym>CABB</acronym> makes available two 2048 MHz wide bands, and the centre
	frequency of one <acronym>IF</acronym> must be within 6 GHz of the centre frequency of the other.
	Generally speaking however, the closer the two centre frequencies are to each other,
	the more sensitive the observations will be.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>local oscillator</primary><secondary>optimising</secondary></indexterm>
	This is due to the design of the <acronym>CABB</acronym> system. All frequency bands
	observable by the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> are first mixed to fit into the primary
	<acronym>CABB</acronym> frequency window of 4 to 12 GHz (except for the 4cm band, which
	doesn't require any mixing). By default, closely-spaced <acronym>IF</acronym> pairs
	are mixed so that they lie at the top of this frequency window because the lower frequency
	end can suffer from poor image rejection. If two widely-spaced <acronym>IF</acronym>s
	are selected however, the observational sensitivity for one of the
	<acronym>IF</acronym>s may suffer because of this.
      </para>

      <para>
	It is important to note that the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> sensitivity calculator does
	<emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> account for this effect.
      </para>

      <para>
	To counter this problem, you may wish instead to use frequency switching techniques;
	you can read about how to do this in <xref linkend="strategy-frequency-switching"></xref>.
      </para>

      <para>
	For normal continuum observations we recommend that you use our recommended frequencies, shown
	in <xref linkend="recommended-continuum-frequencies"></xref>.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>continuum observing</primary><secondary>recommended frequencies</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>frequency</primary><secondary>recommended</secondary></indexterm>
      </para>

      <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="recommended-continuum-frequencies">
	<title>Recommended <acronym>CABB</acronym> continuum centre frequencies.</title>
	<tgroup align="center" cols="3">
	  <colspec colname="bandname"/>
	  <colspec colname="if1"/>
	  <colspec colname="if2"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Band</entry>
	      <entry><acronym>IF</acronym>1 (MHz)</entry>
	      <entry><acronym>IF</acronym>2 (MHz)</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>16cm</entry>
	      <entry>2100</entry>
	      <entry>2100</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>4cm</entry>
	      <entry>5500</entry>
	      <entry>9000</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>15mm</entry>
	      <entry>17000</entry>
	      <entry>19000</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>15mm (to avoid satellite <acronym>RFI</acronym>, in dry weather)</entry>
	      <entry>16700</entry>
	      <entry>21200</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>7mm (<acronym>LSB</acronym>)</entry>
	      <entry>33000</entry>
	      <entry>35000</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>7mm (<acronym>USB</acronym>)</entry>
	      <entry>43000</entry>
	      <entry>45000</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>3mm</entry>
	      <entry>93000</entry>
	      <entry>95000</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>
	If you are using the 3mm system, the choice of simultaneous frequencies can affect
	the observational sensitivity in another way, due to restrictions on the
	<acronym>LO</acronym> frequencies:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If the highest central frequency
	      is &gt; 100.6 GHz and the lowest central frequency is &gt; 97.8 GHz,
	      then the band will be <acronym>USB</acronym>, and sensitivity will be optimised.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If the lowest central
	      frequency is &lt; 97.8 GHz and the highest central frequency is
	      &gt; 100.6 GHz, then the band will be <acronym>LSB</acronym>, but the 
	      <acronym>LO</acronym> will
	      be driven past its rated limit, reducing the sensitivity.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If the lowest central frequency is &lt; 97.8 GHz, and the highest
	      central frequency is &lt; 100.6 GHz, then the band will be <acronym>LSB</acronym>, and
	      sensitivity will be optimised.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If the highest central frequency is &lt; 100.6 GHz, and the lowest
	      central frequency is &gt; 97.8 GHz, then the band may either be 
	      <acronym>LSB</acronym> or <acronym>USB</acronym>,
	      and will be automatically configured by <command>caobs</command> to optimise sideband
	      rejection (but this may still result in less than optimal sensitivity).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <info>
	<title>How can I avoid <acronym>RFI</acronym>?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary><secondary>avoiding</secondary></indexterm>
	<acronym>RFI</acronym> at the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> falls into two groups:
	external, and self-generated. External <acronym>RFI</acronym> is worst at lower frequencies,
	and can significantly reduce the bandwith usable in the centimetre bands. Self-generated
	<acronym>RFI</acronym> is less destructive, but also mostly unavoidable, and can be present
	regardless of which band you're observing in.
      </para>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>What external transmitters are located near the observatory?</title>
	</info>

	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary><secondary>nearby transmitters</secondary></indexterm>
	  The observatory keeps track (as much as possible) of the licensed transmitters in the
	  surrounding area. A searchable database of these transmitters is 
	  <ulink url="https://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/rfi/rfi_gmap.html">made available
	  </ulink> for
	  users of the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> (who already have an <acronym>ATNF</acronym>
	  UNIX account). You can search for transmitters based on their frequencies and distance
	  from their observatory, and learn about where they are, their transmission power, and
	  pointing direction.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>How much continuum sensitivity will I lose due to <acronym>RFI</acronym>?</title>
	</info>

	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary><secondary>effect of</secondary></indexterm>
	  The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> sensitivity calculator also has information about frequency
	  ranges that are commonly flagged due to <acronym>RFI</acronym>, and so can take into
	  account the bandwidth losses when doing its calculations. This functionality is recommended
	  for all continuum observers.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Continuum observers should expect to lose approximately 270 MHz of bandwidth in the
	  16cm band (13% of the 2048 MHz total bandwidth) and approximately 200 MHz of bandwidth in the 4cm band
	  (5% of the 4096 MHz total bandwidth) due to <acronym>RFI</acronym> that is almost always
	  present. There are other sources of <acronym>RFI</acronym> that will be present for only some
	  of the time that will cost even more bandwidth, but most of these have fairly short durations
	  and will not generally significantly affect the continuum sensitivity.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>What is &#x201C;mid-week&#x201D; <acronym>RFI</acronym>?</title>
	</info>

	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary><secondary>mid-week</secondary></indexterm>
	  In the 16cm band there is a transmitter that produces what is commonly referred to as
	  &#x201C;mid-week&#x201D; <acronym>RFI</acronym>, since it usually appears on weekdays during
	  business hours (it can however appear at other times). This transmitter is so powerful that it
	  can send the 16cm receivers into saturation, or at the very least cause intermodulation products
	  to contaminate the entire 2 GHz band; during either of those scenarios, no sensible
	  astronomical data is produced by the system. The observatory will sometimes receive advanced
	  warning about this <acronym>RFI</acronym>, and observers will be notified before they start in
	  that case, but this is not guaranteed to happen. If warning is given sufficiently in advance,
	  the operations staff may be able to assist you in organising a swap with a project that can
	  observe in a band other than 16cm; again, no guarantee is made that this will occur.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="observations-calibration">
    <info>
      <title>Calibration</title>
    </info>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>What type of calibration do I need to do?</title>
      </info>
    
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibration</primary><secondary>required</secondary></indexterm>
	During a normal observing run you will have to do calibration before you can
	start your observations, and then you will need to schedule time on one
	or more calibration sources.
      </para>

      <para>
	At the beginning of your observing run you may find that while observing a strong
	point source, the phases will not be constant as a function of frequency across the
	band; this indicates that the array requires delay calibration. To successfully perform
	delay calibration will require a point source of at least moderate flux density
	(<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{S} \gtrsim 1\mathrm{\,Jy}</textobject></inlineequation>).
	This is so the correlator can accurately determine the phase slope with frequency;
	the accuracy improves with the signal-to-noise ratio.
      </para>

      <para>
	The response of each antenna to the incoming radiation must also be determined, and
	this is comprised of bandpass and flux density calibration. This calibration can be
	done with only one source if the flux density of that source is known, it is a point
	source, and has sufficient flux density. Otherwise a point source with a high flux density can be observed
	as the bandpass calibrator (the source used for the delay calibration can usually be
	used for this purpose), and a source with a known flux density, or a
	planet can be used for flux density calibration.
      </para>

      <para>
	Over the duration of the experiment, several factors that affect the antenna
	response will change. These include atmospheric phase, opacity, elevation-dependent
	dish surface distortions and focus changes, aperture illumination and spillover.
	To monitor these changes you will need to observe a point source nearby to your
	science target. This point source will need to have a relatively high flux density,
	although averaging over a short period of time (~1 minute) if this is not possible.
      </para>

      <para>
	If you need to measure the polarisation of your science target, you will want
	to determine the leakage parameters: the fraction of linearly-polarised photons
	that are detected by the receptor that should not have been.
      </para>

      <para>
	If you are observing at high frequency, where the primary beam of the antenna
	is small, it is important that the maximum response of the beam is directed
	toward the source you're observing. To ensure this is the case, you should do
	periodic pointing-correction scans on a nearby point source with reasonable
	flux density (&gt;300 mJy).
      </para>

      <para>
	Finally, if you're observing in the 3mm band, you will need to use the
	receiver's absorber paddle to keep track of how the system temperature varies
	over time. This is done periodically on-line using &#x201C;paddle&#x201D;
	scans.
      </para>

      <para>
	A summary of what type of calibration you will require for each observing band is
	given in <xref linkend="RequiredCalibration"></xref>.
      </para>

      <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="RequiredCalibration">
	<title>Calibration required by observing band.</title>
	<tgroup align="center" cols="6">
	  <colspec colname="type"/>
	  <colspec colname="cm16"/>
	  <colspec colname="cm4"/>
	  <colspec colname="mm15"/>
	  <colspec colname="mm7"/>
	  <colspec colname="mm3"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Calibration</entry>
	      <entry>16cm</entry>
	      <entry>4cm</entry>
	      <entry>15mm</entry>
	      <entry>7mm</entry>
	      <entry>3mm</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Delay calibration</entry>
	      <entry namest="cm16" nameend="mm3">Required</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Bandpass calibration</entry>
	      <entry namest="cm16" nameend="mm3">Required</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Flux density calibration</entry>
	      <entry namest="cm16" nameend="mm7">Required, on 1934-638</entry>
	      <entry>Required, on Uranus</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Gain calibration</entry>
	      <entry namest="cm16" nameend="mm3">Required</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Polarisation calibration</entry>
	      <entry namest="cm16" nameend="mm3">Required</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Pointing calibration</entry>
	      <entry namest="cm16" nameend="cm4">Not required</entry>
	      <entry namest="mm15" nameend="mm3">Required</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Paddle calibration</entry>
	      <entry namest="cm16" nameend="mm7">Not possible</entry>
	      <entry>Required</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>
	For more detail on each of these types of calibration, read the sections
	below. It is important to note that you must repeat all the calibration for
	every frequency configuration that you observe, as it is not generally possible to
	interpolate or extrapolate the calibration parameters determined from one frequency
	configuration to another.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id="calibration-delays">
      <info>
	<title>What sources can be used for delay calibration?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>delay</secondary></indexterm>
	The calibrator you use to calibrate the delays is largely dependent on the
	band you are observing in, and the <acronym>LST</acronym> when you are setting up.
      </para>

      <para>
	For the centimetre bands (16cm and 4cm), delay calibration is best done with one of
	two sources. When the LST is between 11:00 and 04:18, you should use PKS 1934-638 to calibrate
	the delays, because it is has a large flux density and you'll need to observe it anyway for flux
	density calibration purposes. At all other times you should use 0823-500.
      </para>

      <para>
	For the higher frequency bands, you will need to use one of the many available
	sources with a large flux density in the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> calibrator database, such as:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>0003-066</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>0420-014</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>0537-441</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>0727-115</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>1034-293</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>1253-055</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>1424-418</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>1613-586</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>1921-293</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>2155-152</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	You should choose whichever is at the highest elevation at the time, or nearest to your targets.
	There are many more
	sources that have large flux densities in the millimetre bands, and you can search for those
	calibrators using the
	<ulink url="https://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/calibrators/">
	  <acronym>ATCA</acronym> calibrator database search interface.</ulink>
      </para>
      
    </section>

    <section id="calibration-bandpass">
      <info>
	<title>How do I calibrate the bandpass response of the antennas?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibration</primary><secondary>bandpass</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>bandpass</secondary></indexterm>
	The bandpass calibration is best done with a source with a large flux density, since you're trying to
	precisely determine how each frequency channel responds to a known amount of flux density.
      </para>

      <para>
	To do this ideally, the response should be dominated by the signal rather than the
	thermal noise in each channel. Since this is also a very useful property for a
	delay calibrator to have, the same calibrators that can be used for delay calibration
	(<xref linkend="calibration-delays"></xref>) are ideal for bandpass calibration as
	well. If the bandpass calibrators is used as the delay calibrator, then the bandpass 
	calibration observation can be made immediately following
	the completion of the setup without further slewing overhead.
	If the observations are at 3mm, a paddle measurement should be
	made immediately before the bandpass observation.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	As the receiver response does not change greatly as a function of time, for a
	continuum observation it is
	usually sufficient to make an observation of a bandpass calibrator at the very start of
	the allocated time. The amount of time spent
	integrating on the bandpass calibrator depends on its flux density, but generally 5-10 minutes
	is sufficient at all frequencies. 
      </para>

      <para>
	For spectral line observations though, it has been noted that the <acronym>CABB</acronym> 
	bandpass is not perfectly stable over the
	course of a normal 12 hour observation, and for this reason it is advisable
	to observe a bandpass calibrator more than once per observation. Visiting it
	three times (once at the start, once at the end, and once sometime near the
	middle) during a 12 hour observation should be sufficient to obtain a reliable
	bandpass solution. Alternatively, provided the gain calibrator has a large flux density,
	the periodic visits to it may provide accurate enough information to
	determine how the bandpass solution changes over time.
      </para>

      <para>
	The integration time spent on the bandpass calibrator will have an effect on
	the accuracy of the flux density that is measured after reduction. It is necessary to
	obtain each correlator channel's response to the same precision as required for the
	flux density calibrator, ie. obtain a signal-to-noise ratio of 100 <emphasis>per channel</emphasis>
	if the required flux density precision is 1%. Since any point source can be a bandpass calibrator,
	the sensitivity calculator should be used
	to find out the RMS noise per channel for your observations, and then a calibrator
	found from the calibrator database that provides enough flux density to meet the signal-to-noise
	ratio requirements. For example, a typical <acronym>CABB</acronym> observation has 2048 channels,
	and at 50 GHz, the RMS noise per channel is about 35 mJy for a 5 minute observation.
	For a signal-to-noise ratio of 100, a calibrator with flux density greater than 3.5 Jy is
	required, and a search through the calibrator database identifies 19 such sources.
	Of course, if a flux density calibrator is strong enough to be a bandpass calibrator
	as well, then observing time can be conserved by not having a separate bandpass
	calibrator.
      </para>

    </section>
    
    <section id="calibration-flux-density">
      <info>
	<title>How do I calibrate the flux density of my observations?</title>
      </info>
      
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibration</primary><secondary>flux density</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>flux density</secondary></indexterm>
	Flux density calibration is required to translate the arbitrary gain scaling that is produced by
	an observation to an absolute flux density scale. The most effective way of doing this is by
	observing a calibrator that has a known flux density (on the absolute flux density scale) and comparing
	it to the sources that you are observing that have unknown flux densities.
      </para>

      <para>
	For the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>, there are currently only four flux density calibrators, and of those only two
	are regularly used.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibration</primary><secondary>flux density scale</secondary></indexterm>
	For frequencies between 1 GHz and 50 GHz, the preferred flux density calibrator is PKS 1934-638.
	It has a known, stable flux density, and conveniently has no linear or circular polarisation, at least
	at low frequencies.
	The flux density model for 1934-638 that is installed in <application>Miriad</application> are 
	based on the models described in the memo
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">A Revised Flux Scale for the AT Compact Array</emphasis>
	    (<ulink url="https://www.atnf.csiro.au/observers/memos/d96783~1.pdf"><emphasis>J Reynolds, 1994</emphasis></ulink>),
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	and the paper
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Absolute calibration of the radio astronomy flux density scale at
	    22 to 43 GHz using <emphasis>Planck</emphasis></emphasis>
	    (<ulink url="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/0004-637X/821/1/61/meta"><emphasis>Partridge et. al, 2016</emphasis></ulink>)
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	The model is separated into two frequency ranges. Below 11 GHz, the Reynolds model is used, which is:
	<equation>
	  <title>Flux density model for 1934-638 from Reynolds 1994</title>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \log\mathrm{S} = -30.7667 + 26.4908\log\nu - 7.0977(\log\nu)^{2} + 0.605334(\log\nu)^{3},
	  </textobject>
	</equation>
	where <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{S}</textobject></inlineequation> is the flux density
	in Jy and <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\nu</textobject></inlineequation> is the frequency in
	MHz. For frequencies above 11 GHz<application>Miriad</application> uses the model from the Planck study:
	<equation>
	  <title>Flux density model for 1934-638 for frequencies above 11 GHz</title>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \log\mathrm{S} = 5.8870 - 1.3763\log\nu
	  </textobject>
	</equation>
	The high-frequency model has been shown by Partridge et al. (2016) to match quite well with the
	<acronym>VLA</acronym>, but unfortunately the low-frequency model does not.
      </para>

      <para>
	For frequencies higher than 50 GHz you can use 1934-638 as the flux density calibrator, but the planet Uranus
	is brighter. Its flux density is known to vary with time, but it does so in a way that is understood and can
	be modelled. The planets Mars and Neptune can also be used, but Uranus is preferred
	because its angular size is smaller than Mars (making it easier to observe with typical
	Compact Array baselines), and it is brighter than Neptune (which would require a longer
	scan to provide the same signal-to-noise level).
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>flux density calibrator</secondary></indexterm>
	To be as effective as possible, the flux density calibrator should be observed when it is at the
	same elevation as the target source, and at as high an elevation as possible. Doing this
	means that any gain-elevation dependence
	is reduced, and the effect of airmass is also reduced. At low frequencies (below 7 GHz),
	these requirements are not as important as they are for higher frequencies, where the
	atmospheric effects become a significant factor. Indeed, many (if not most) centimetre observers
	simply make a scan on 1934-638 at the beginning of their observations, and this is usually
	good enough to get a flux density uncertainty of only a few percent.
      </para>

      <para>
	Because 1934-638 is a point source (at least at the resolution of the Compact Array), it
	can be observed the same way as any other calibrator. That is, a scan on 1934-638 should
	be included in the schedule, and should be preceded by a pointing scan when it is observed
	with the 15mm or 7mm receivers.
      </para>

      <para>
	Observing the planets is a little more complicated. Because they are not point sources on
	even the most compact of <acronym>ATCA</acronym> baselines, they cannot be used as a pointing reference. A
	nearby source must therefore be used to determine the pointing offsets before observing
	the planet. Also, because the planets will substantially fill the primary beam of the
	<acronym>ATCA</acronym> antenna, the apparent system temperature of the antenna will be increased while
	a planet is being observed. Because of this, if a paddle scan is made while observing a
	planet, the system temperature will not be correctly determined, and the flux scaling will
	be in error. When observing with the 3mm system therefore, the paddle scan should be made
	while observing the same nearby pointing reference calibrator.
      </para>

      <para>
	To make a good observation of Uranus, follow the procedure:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Determine a suitable nearby calibrator that can be used for pointing/paddle
	    measurements. First, check the ephemeris of Uranus with the <command>planet</command>
	    task in <application>Miriad</application>. After the position of Uranus on the date of the observation has been
	    determined, use the <ulink url="https://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/calibrators/">calibrator database</ulink>
	    or the &#x201C;Search Cal&#x201D; button in the Web Scheduler to find the closest suitable
	    calibrator.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If observing at 3mm, make a paddle measurement while tracking the calibrator.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Determine the pointing offsets using the calibrator.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Observe the calibrator for 2 minutes.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Observe Uranus for a sufficient amount of time (10-15 minutes is usually more
	    than enough).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Observe the calibrator again for 2 minutes.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	The procedure is similar for the other planets. Note that because the phases of the nearby
	calibrator are not used by the <application>Miriad</application> flux calibration task 
	<command>mfboot</command>, it is not
	absolutely necessary to bracket the planet with a calibrator observation. It can however
	be useful to have that data to diagnose potential problems, should they arise.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>Miriad</primary><secondary>tasks</secondary><tertiary>mfboot</tertiary></indexterm>
      </para>

      <para>
	The integration time spent on the flux density calibrator is largely governed by the 
	precision required for the observations to be successful, and the strength of the primary flux 
	density calibrator at the observing frequency. If a flux density precision of 1% is required, then the aim
	should be to make an observation with a signal-to-noise ratio of 100. For a
	observation with 2 GHz bandwidth, this is relatively easy, as even
	a 5 minute observation of 1934-638 at 50 GHz gives a signal-to-noise ratio in
	excess of 1000.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The sensitivity calculator should be used to estimate the observing time required to achieve the desired
	flux density precision. However, it is never a bad idea to pad the required time out a little
	to ensure that enough good data will remain after flagging.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id="calibration-gains">
      <info>
	<title>How do I best calibrate the time-varying gains?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>gain</primary><secondary>time variable</secondary></indexterm>
	The gain parameters that vary significantly over time include:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>atmospheric phase</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>atmospheric opacity</para></listitem>	  
	  <listitem><para>forward gain due to structural deformation</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>aperture illumination</para></listitem>	  
	</itemizedlist>
	As these factors vary, the path lengths between the antennas will vary
	(which varies the phase), and the system temperatures may change, thus
	changing the sensitivity. To accurately correct for these changes, they must
	be regularly monitored.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>gain</primary><secondary>calibration</secondary><see>calibration</see></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibration</primary><secondary>gain</secondary></indexterm>
	The best way to monitor these changing parameters is to observe a
	simple source (a point source in an otherwise empty field is the ideal case)
	every time the observing configuration (elevation, weather, etc.) changes
	significantly. The definition of &#x201C;significant&#x201D; change
	depends on the observing frequency and the observing conditions (such as
	array configuration, atmospheric seeing, temperature, precipitation etc.).
	More precisely,
	by observing a source that looks the same irrespective of time or (u,v)
	coordinates, changes in gain can be determined directly. Therefore, gain calibrators
	should be unresolved, with a stable flux density over the observation timescale.
      </para>

      <para>
	The
	<acronym>ATCA</acronym> provides
	<ulink url="https://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/calibrators/calcycle.html">a calculator</ulink>
	to advise observers on how often to visit their phase calibrator.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>gain</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>phase</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>decorrelation</primary></indexterm>
	For this calculator:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Input the central observing frequency and the maximum baseline
	      of interest (ie. don't include the 6km antenna if its data will be discarded).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      For the seeing monitor RMS phase, give a nominal value of 300 microns if the
	      observations will be performed in winter, and 700 microns if they will be in
	      daytime during summer; for other times, choose a value between those two extremes.
	      You can adjust using the actual values on the day if you want, but these
	      values will generally prevent you from not calibrating frequently enough.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      For the phase screen speed, choose 5 m/s.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      For the Kolmogorov exponent, leave the
	      default 0.83 unless the 6km antenna will be required, in which case enter 0.33
	      instead.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	For example, for an observation at 19 GHz, with a seeing RMS of 300 microns, in a
	750m array, the calculator determines that if the gain calibrator was visited every
	2 minutes, the observations would have an RMS phase of 15&#x00B0;, be decorrelated
	by 3%, and have a maximum dynamic range of just 282. However it also determines that
	this is as bad as it gets, so that a 10 minute visit interval would give the same results.
	Since 2 minutes is a very frequent visit schedule, it would seem that self-calibration
	would be preferable for high dynamic range observations.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	Dropping the seeing RMS to 100 microns (which would be a good winter day)
	improves matters significantly, allowing a dynamic range of 874 with no decorrelation and a
	5&#x00B0; RMS phase for any visit interval greater than 2 minutes.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	It is important however not to extend the interval too far, as then the atmosphere
	being sampled by the gain calibrator will be different to that the source has sampled
	during that time. For cm observations, one might need only visit the gain calibrator
	once or twice per hour in good conditions, while for mm observations, it is unwise
	to visit the calibrator less frequently than once every 15 minutes.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>database</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>searching for</secondary></indexterm>
	The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> has a large list of gain calibrators, spread over the viewable sky. This list
	can be queried using a 
	<ulink url="https://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/calibrators/">web interface</ulink>.
	  This interface queries the database in one of three ways:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Quick-find calibrator</emphasis>: finds a calibrator with a specified name.
	    The quick-find box will show all sources that match the string you enter into it.
	    For example, there
	    are five sources in the database which match with &#x201C;0537&#x201D;: 0537-441, 0537-158, 0537-286,
	    J0537-3357 and 0537+531. When this list of sources is displayed, you can click on the one you want
	    to get a small list of that calibrator's most recent flux densities and its position.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Cone search</emphasis>: finds calibrators within a specified angular distance from
	    a given sky position. Can optionally be restricted to sources brighter than a given
	    flux in a specified wavelength band. You can also enter a resolvable name into the position box instead
	    of an RA and Dec.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Patch search</emphasis>: finds all calibrators within a specified RA and Dec range.
	    Can optionally be restricted to sources brighter than a given flux in a specified wavelength
	    band.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	Selection of an appropriate gain calibrator can also be done while you are preparing
	the schedule in the <acronym>CABB</acronym> web scheduler (see
	<xref linkend="Continuum-Schedule-Example"></xref> for an example of how this works).
	Ideally, choose the nearest possible point source calibrator to your target.
	Sometimes that calibrator may not have a high flux density though, and you may wish to
	choose a calibrator that is further away in order to lessen your
	overhead: a calibrator with a higher flux density can give a good measurement of the gain in a
	shorter time. For continuum observations this is largely
	irrelevant since the large <acronym>CABB</acronym> bandwidths allow for a very
	accurate measure of gain in just a few cycles. For spectral line observations though,
	the more flux density the source has the better.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>What do I need to do for polarisation calibration?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibration</primary><secondary>polarisation</secondary></indexterm>
	The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> uses dual linear orthogonal feeds to measure the incident radiation.
	Ideally, these two feeds would be independent: in reality
	this is not the case, and a fraction of the radiation measured by one feed is also
	received by the other; this effect is called &#x201C;leakage&#x201D;. Polarisation calibration is primarily concerned
	with measuring the leakage fraction and the possibly non-zero signal phase (the so-called
	XY-phase) between the two feeds.
      </para>

      <para>
	A paper by Sault and Cornwell (1999, in &#x201C;Synthesis Imaging in Radio Astronomy II&#x201D;,
	ASP Conf. 180, p657) showed that for an observation where a calibrator with apriori unknown
	polarisation properties can be observed with at least three different parallactic angles (what they
	call the &#x201C;parallactic angle rotation trick&#x201D;), polarisation calibration is required
	to determine the absolute alignment of linear polarisation angle and the term which causes leakage
	between Stokes I and V.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibration</primary><secondary>noise diode</secondary></indexterm>
	The absolute alignment of linear polarisations is achieved by injecting a linearly
	polarised signal at 45&#x00B0; to the linear orthogonal feeds several times per second: this
	is known as the &#x201C;noise diode&#x201D;. This signal is measured by the correlator on each
	antenna, and the XY-phase is used later in data reduction to determine the absolute linear polarisation
	angle. All the receivers except for the 3mm system have a noise diode on each antenna. For 3mm
	observations, CA02 has got the Mopra spare receiver installed, which has a noise diode, while all
	other antennas do not. Should Mopra require the spare at any point however, this capability may
	be removed from the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>; in this case you would need to use a different
	observational strategy to recover the absolute alignment information.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>polarisation</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary><secondary>linear</secondary></indexterm>
	This means that to complete the linear polaristion calibration, any of the point source calibrators in the
	<acronym>ATCA</acronym> calibrator database can be observed at least a few times over the course of an
	Earth-rotation synthesis observation. Since this is likely being done for normal gain calibration,
	most observations will contain enough information to calibrate the linear polarisation.
      </para>

      <para>
	If you can't play the parallactic angle rotation trick (if for instance you are observing for only
	a short time), then you will need to know the polarisation parameters for the calibrators you are
	observing. At low frequencies (in the 16cm band), it is known that PKS B1934-638 has zero linear
	polarisation. For short observations then, you can use the flux density calibration observations
	to calibrate linear polarisation as well.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary><secondary>circular</secondary></indexterm>
	Dave Rayner's <ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/observers/memos/circpolguide.pdf">&#x201C;Circular Polarization User's Guide&#x201D;</ulink>
	is a useful guide on how to accurately measure circular polarisation with the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>When is pointing calibration required?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>pointing</primary><secondary>accuracy</secondary></indexterm>
	The global pointing model for the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> antennas is usually good to a few
	arcseconds under ideal conditions, and the tracking accuracy is better than an arcsecond.
	But changes in temperature can make the pointing model incorrect by a few 10s of arcseconds,
	and this would mean that for the millimetre bands the pointing may be incorrect by a
	significant fraction of the primary beam size (see <xref linkend="table_sensitivity"></xref>).
	This would adversely affect the sensitivity of the observations of your targets.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>pointing</primary><secondary>correction</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibration</primary><secondary>reference pointing</secondary></indexterm>
	While observing, you can correct the pointing model to ensure that the peak response of the
	primary beam is pointing directly at your target. A pointing correction scan is made by
	observing a point source directly and at the half-power point of the
	primary beam in each of the azimuth and elevation axes, and comparing the amplitude seen at
	each of these points.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>reference pointing</secondary></indexterm>
	With 2 GHz of bandwidth, almost any point source in the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> calibrator
	database has enough flux density to allow determination of the pointing corrections, however
	the pointing corrections only really improve the global pointing model within 20&#x00B0; of
	the azimuth/elevation at
	which the corrections were determined. The natural choice of calibrator for this purpose
	is therefore the same as for the gain calibration, and in general you should use your
	gain calibrator for pointing calibration.
      </para>

      <para>
	Because the pointing corrections are only valid with 20&#x00B0;, a pointing correction scan
	will be required approximately every hour while you're observing if you're tracking the same
	source as it crosses the sky, or more frequently if you're observing multiple sources across
	the sky.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>When is paddle calibration required?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibration</primary><secondary>paddle</secondary></indexterm>	
	The &#x201C;paddle&#x201D; is a mechanical arm that holds an absorbing material large
	enough to cover the 3mm feed horn. By observing the paddle, the temperature of which is assumed
	to be the ambient temperature in the antenna vertex room (which is monitored), and comparing it
	to the assumed temperature of the mostly empty sky, you get a system temperature that includes
	the effect of the atmosphere. This is sometimes referred to as the &#x201C;above-the-atmosphere&#x201D;
	system temperature, because in this case the system includes the atmosphere.
      </para>

      <para>
	Because changes to the system temperature affect the response of the system to an otherwise
	equivalent amount of radiation, it is important to keep track of these changes as your observations
	progress. With the other receivers, the injected noise signal (the temperature of which is assumed to
	stay constant) is monitored constantly, and no overhead is incurred for sytem temperature monitoring.
	For observations with the 3mm receiver however, you will need to observe the paddle reasonably
	frequently and incur a couple of minutes overhead each time you do.
      </para>

      <para>
	How often the paddle is used depends on the conditions. Since in principle you are using the paddle
	scans to interpolate the actual system temperature at any particular point in time during your observations,
	you will need to observe the paddle frequently enough to catch any departures from a linear change
	to the system temperature. If you are observing in good and stable weather, you can go 20 minutes between paddle
	scans. If the atmosphere is very turbulent though you may have to use the paddle more often.
      </para>

      <para>
	It is important to remember that the system temperature calculation depends on the assumption that
	it will be looking at mostly empty sky after it looks at the paddle. For most point source calibrators
	this assumption will be valid, but if you are pointing at a planet, the system response will include
	its temperature, and this will affect the system temperature calculations.
      </para>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="observations-scheduling">
    <info>
      <title>Scheduling your observations</title>
    </info>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>What is meant by &#x201C;schedule&#x201D;?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	Observations on the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> normally consist of a sequence of
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>scan</primary><see>schedule</see></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>schedule</primary><secondary>scan</secondary></indexterm>
	<firstterm>scans</firstterm>: a scan is a period of observing where the telescope configuration
	stays the same. A complete observation is made up of a
	number of scans.  Observations typically alternate between scans on the
	scientifically interesting sources and scans on one or more calibrators. 
	The configuration of the scans and their order are kept in a
	<wordasword>schedule file</wordasword>.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>caobs</primary></indexterm>
	The main observing task, <command>caobs</command>, reads the schedule file to
	determine what sources are to be observed, for how long, and in what
	order. The schedule file also defines the frequencies and
	correlator setup for each scan and can also be used to make the system automatically
	execute commands.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>schedule</primary><secondary>file</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>schedule</primary><secondary>web scheduler</secondary></indexterm>
	The 
	<ulink url="https://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/sched/cabb/"> <acronym>ATCA</acronym> web scheduler</ulink>
	is the tool to use to create <acronym>ATCA</acronym> schedule files in the <acronym>CABB</acronym> era.
	Schedules made with the old <command>sched</command> program are no longer understood by
	the <acronym>CABB</acronym> version of <command>caobs</command> and thus cannot be used. However, it is
	possible for the web scheduler to read in old schedules and save them
	for use with the new system. Please also note that an active <acronym>ATNF</acronym> username
	and password is required to gain access to the web scheduler page.
      </para>

      <para>
	Generally, users will want to prepare <emphasis role="bold">at least</emphasis> two schedule files:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A schedule file for setting up (delay calibration etc.) and flux density calibration.
	    It should include the appropriate flux density calibrator (<xref linkend="calibration-flux-density"></xref>),
	    and if the flux density calibrator cannot be used as a bandpass calibrator, another calibrator
	    with higher flux density that can be used for array setup and bandpass calibration.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A schedule file containing the science program source(s) and gain calibrator(s)
	    (<xref linkend="calibration-gains"></xref>).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	You may also want to prepare contingency schedule files in case your preferred frequency is seriously
	affected by interference, or the selected calibrator proves to be resolved.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="scheduling-snapshots">
      <info>
	<title>How do I best observe if I want to image compact sources?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>snapshot</secondary></indexterm>
	If your goal is to make a high-quality image of a source that has an angular extent much smaller than the
	size of the primary beam of the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> antennas, then you should observe your source
	in &#x201C;snapshots&#x201D;. The same strategy can be applied if you want to image a small number of
	sources that are separated in the sky.
      </para>

      <para>
	Snapshot observations will allow you to obtain a wide range of uv coverage without having to spend all
	your observing time on source. This is necessary because you will need to obtain calibration data
	within your time allocation. Generally, a snapshot consists of one or more calibration scans,
	followed by some integration time on the science target, followed by a gain calibration scan. These
	snapshots are repeated until your observations are complete.
      </para>

      <para>
	Snapshot observing is best illustrated with examples.
      </para>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>Example 1: Imaging a single source in the 16cm band</title>
	</info>

	<para>
	  This is essentially the simplest form of snapshot observing. All you need to do is integrate on the
	  target, and occasionally visit a gain calibrator to ensure that you keep track of any phase changes.
	  A single snapshot might therefore be:
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem><para>2 minutes integration on a gain calibrator.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>40 minutes integration on the target.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>2 minutes integration on a gain calibrator.</para></listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	  This set of scans can be repeated as many times as possible within the allocated time. 
	</para>

	<para>
	  These scans will give you enough data to properly calibrate the gains during your observing, and
	  the polarisation as well, provided you get more than three snapshots in your allocated time.
	  However you will need to spend some time observing the flux density calibrator (which also works
	  as a bandpass calibrator) at some time during your allocated time.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>Example 2: Imaging several sources in the 4cm band</title>
	</info>
	
	<para>
	  Imaging several sources is basically the same as imaging a single source, except you have
	  multiple snapshot sets to get through. For each source that you have, you will have an
	  associated nearby gain calibrator. Then, you will have multiple sets that look like:
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem><para>2 minutes integration on gain calibrator for source 1.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>20 minutes integration on the target source 1.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>2 minutes integration on gain calibrator for source 1.</para></listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	</para>

	<para>
	  During the allocated observing time, each set of scans will be observed multiple times, but
	  it is best to interleave them to ensure you get the widest possible coverage of azimuths and
	  elevations for each set. And once again, you must remember to get some time on the flux
	  density calibrator.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>Example 3: Imaging several sources in the 7mm band</title>
	</info>
	  
	<para>
	  Changing to the higher frequency 7mm band means that you must start doing online
	  pointing correction scans. The basic set of scans is still the same, as in example
	  2, but now you have to occasionally add in a pointing scan. For example, if your
	  normal scan set takes 20 minutes (e.g. 16 minutes on source, 4 minutes on the
	  gain calibrator), then you could observe this set three times between pointing
	  scans, as it is recommended that you don't use a pointing solution for more than
	  an hour.
	</para>

	<para>
	  If your sources are all within 20&#x00B0; of each other, you may be able to
	  find a single source that can be used as the pointing correction calibrator, and
	  you will only need to do this once per hour.
	</para>

	<para>
	  If your sources are spread around the sky you will need to do a pointing correction
	  for each source. If you are only visiting your sources once per hour, then the
	  pointing correction scan can simply be built into your snapshot set. However if you
	  are looking at each source multiple times per hour, but you want to observe the sources
	  interleaved with each other, you will need to be careful.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Usually, when you do a pointing correction scan, the corrections that are determined
	  are applied immediately and all subsequent scans (well, those that have 
	  <literal>Pointing</literal> set to &#x201C;Offset&#x201D;) will use those corrections.
	  This would be a problem if you are observing a source that is more than 20&#x00B0;
	  away from the location of the most recent pointing scan, even if it was within 20&#x00B0; of the
	  location of a pointing scan that was done less than an hour ago; such a scan would
	  use the wrong pointing corrections!
	</para>

	<para>
	  The solution to this is to set <literal>Pointing</literal> to &#x201C;Offpnt&#x201D;
	  for the scan. In this case, <command>caobs</command> will find the most recent
	  pointing corrections that are close to the location of the current scan, and use those
	  corrections for that scan.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>Example 4: Imaging a single source in the 3mm band</title>
	</info>

	<para>
	  In the 3mm band, not only do you need to do pointing corrections every hour, you
	  need to do frequent observations of the paddle. The frequency of your paddle
	  observations is determined by the conditions during your allocated time, and is
	  related somewhat to the required frequency of your gain calibrator observations.
	  That is, if the atmosphere is turbulent, then you may only be able to spend
	  a few minutes away from a gain calibrator. And in such a case, the system temperature
	  may be changing on a similar timescale. It is therefore usually a good idea to
	  include a paddle scan in every snapshot set. Such a set might look like this:
	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem><para>Measurement of the paddle.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>2 minutes integration on the gain calibrator.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>8 minutes integration on the target source.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>Measurement of the paddle.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>2 minutes integration on the gain calibrator.</para></listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	</para>

	<para>
	  Since the apparent flux density of the sources you are observing will depend
	  on the system temperature measured by the paddle scan, it is very important to
	  ensure that you do the paddle measurement <emphasis role="bold">before</emphasis>
	  you observe the sources. It is however not really necessary to ensure the
	  measured amplitudes are accurate before doing a pointing scan.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>How do I best image a source with a large angular extent, or a wide field
	region?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>mosaic</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>mosaicking</secondary></indexterm>
	If the source you will image is bigger than a small fraction of the
	<acronym>ATCA</acronym> primary beam, or the region you want an image for is
	considerably larger than the primary beam, you will need to use the
	<acronym>ATCA</acronym>'s mosaicking functionality.
      </para>

      <para>
	In interferometry adjacent pointings are not independent and so
	we can get fundamentally better images by processing the
	different pointings together. Necessary information about the
	pointing grid pattern to use for proper Nyquist sampling and
	the time to be spent on each position to optimise tangential
	uv coverage can be found in 
	<ulink url="https://www.atnf.csiro.au/computing/software/miriad/userguide/node175.html">Chapter 21</ulink>
	of the <application>Miriad</application> Users Guide.
      </para>

      <para>
	For close-packed mosaicking (pointing centres every
	half-beamwidth), drive times are determined by the
	acceleration limit of 800&#x00B0;/min&#x00B2;. Half the drive
	time is spent accelerating and half decelerating. For drive
	times much further than 108&#x2032; in azimuth or 27&#x2032;
	in elevation, the drive times are dominated by the slew rate
	limits of 38&#x00B0;/min in elevation and 19&#x00B0;/min in
	azimuth. For example, a 16&#x2032; drive for a 16cm mosaic
	will take, depending on the elevation and azimuth of the
	source, approximately 2.2 seconds. Data taken during the
	off-source period is blanked in the correlator using a
	predicted drive time. As drive times can be a significant
	overhead, care should be taken to not slew the antennas more than
	necessary.
      </para>

      <para>
	Mosaicking is less useful if frequency switching is desired, as
	no frequency changes can occur during the mosaic scan. Since
	slew times are often much greater than the time it takes for
	the correlator to switch frequencies, the overheads involved
	in repeating a mosaic scan for each separate frequency might
	quickly negate the normal benefits of mosaicking.
      </para>

      <para>
	Mosaicking mode can also be useful when a large
	number of nearby sources are to be observed, as observing
	overheads are reduced. Other applications include holography
	and source surveys using one dimensional cuts. 
      </para>

      <para>
	When scheduling a mosaic observation, the &#x201C;snapshot&#x201D; strategy
	should be used in order to get calibration data. That is, a point source
	calibrator should be observed periodically between observations of the
	mosaic pointings.
      </para>

      <para>
	If you are mapping a very large, regularly-shaped region at
	low frequency, where the slew time between each pointing centre
	is dominated by the maximum speed of the antenna rather than
	the acceleration/deceleration rate, then you may get a significant
	reduction in overhead by using <firstterm>on-the-fly mosaicking</firstterm>.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>mosaic</primary><secondary>on-the-fly</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>on-the-fly mosaicking</secondary></indexterm>
	On-the-fly (<acronym>OTF</acronym>) mosaicking has a couple of important differences to
	traditional mosaicking. Most importantly, although the
	mosaic pattern should be broadly the same &#x2013; the hexagonal pattern is still
	the optimal sampling &#x2013; the order of observations should be such that the
	telescope scans in a straight line for as long a distance as possible.
      </para>

      <para>
	During an <acronym>OTF</acronym> mosaic, the phase center follows the mosaic points as specified,
	and the pointing center moves continuously across the pointings. In effect the
	primary beam of the antennas becomes elongated (to 1.5 beams) in the scanning
	direction.
      </para>

      <para>
	To satisfy proper sampling of the sky, the antennas should not move by more than
	half a beam per integration cycle, so the spacing of pointings in the mosaic file
	should be the same as before. Because <command>caobs</command> assumes
	you are scanning in rows or columns, the direction of scanning is inferred from
	the next point. At the last point of a row or column the previous direction is
	maintained to complete the scan. One extra point, marked with the name 
	&#x201C;<literal>TURN</literal>&#x201D;, needs
	to be specified at the start of the next row/column, to allow the antennas
	to change direction and scan at the correct speed again.
      </para>

      <para>
	The primary advantage of <acronym>OTF</acronym> mosaicking over regular mosaicking is its speed in
	covering a large area of sky, making it possible to get good uv coverage
	of a large field in a single observing run. It will not usually provide any better
	sensitivity than a carefully-crafted regular mosaic.
      </para>

      <para>
	Although <acronym>OTF</acronym> mosaicking is most useful at low frequencies where the slew time
	between mosaicking points is a significant fraction of the total integration
	time, this mode could also be used for mm observations by using bin mode and
	moving the antennas by e.g., 16 beams in a single integration with 32 time bins.
	The <application>Miriad</application> program atlod will need some work to properly record the
	phase center and pointing center in this case (ie. such a mode is not currently supported,
	but may be if demand for it is high).
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="scheduling-mosaics">
      <info>
	<title>How do I schedule a mosaic observation?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>mosaic</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>mosaic</primary><secondary>file</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>schedule</primary><secondary>mosaic</secondary></indexterm>
	Mosaic observations use a standard schedule file and an additional file,
	called the <firstterm>mosaic file</firstterm>, 
        which lists the positions of the mosaic field centres. 
        Up to 2048 fields can be specified in a single file.
	This mosaic file must consist of one line per pointing centre in the
	mosaic pattern. Lines beginning with the &#x201C;<literal>#</literal>&#x201D; character
	are ignored and can be used for comments.
      </para>

      <para>
	The general mosaic file format is:
      </para>
      <para>
	<screen>
	  # Comments  .... ignored by the software
	  #
	  d(RA)  d(DEC)  INT  $FIELD_1
	  d(RA)  d(DEC)  INT  $FIELD_2
	  d(RA)  d(DEC)  INT  $FIELD_3
	  d(RA)  d(DEC)  INT  $FIELD_4
	</screen>
      </para>

      <para>
	The items in each line are:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    &#x201C;<literal>d(RA)</literal>&#x201D;
	    the offset Right Ascension of the pointing centre,
	    in &#x201C;degrees of polar rotation&#x201D;, from the reference position.
	    For example, <literal>d(RA) = +15.00</literal> will move +1 hr in RA at
	    all declinations.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    &#x201C;<literal>d(DEC)</literal>&#x201D;
	    the offset declination of the pointing centre,
	    in degrees, from the  reference position.
	    e.g. <literal>d(DEC) = +1.000</literal> will move the pointing centre one degree
	    north.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    &#x201C;<literal>INT</literal>&#x201D;
	    the integral number of integration cycles to spend on each
	    pointing centre.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    &#x201C;<literal>$FIELD_n</literal>&#x201D;
	    the name of the field.
	    The &#x201C;<literal>$</literal>&#x201D; symbol is a prefix to the field name, and indicates that
	    scans will follow in the order as they are listed in the mosaic file.
	    The field name must be different for each pointing centre and must
	    have 9 or fewer characters (naturally, &#x201C;<literal>$</literal>&#x201D; can not be used as the
	    first character of the field name).
	    <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis>
	    If you wish to use the &#x201C;<literal>mosaic</literal>&#x201D; option in the 
	    <application>Miriad</application> task
	    <command>uvsplit</command> (to keep the mosaic pointings together in one uv data
	    file), the field name strings should differ by only the
	    &#x201C;<literal>_n</literal>&#x201D; part of the name, where 
	    &#x201C;<literal>n</literal>&#x201D; is an integer.
	    The field name given within the mosaic file does not need to match
	    the source name given in the schedule file.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	This file should be named &#x201C;<literal>mosnam.mos</literal>&#x201D;.  The
	&#x201C;<literal>.mos</literal>&#x201D; suffix is required, or
	<command>caobs</command> will not find the file.  The
	&#x201C;<literal>mosnam</literal>&#x201D; part of the name
	<emphasis>must</emphasis> match the source name given in the
	schedule file.
      </para>

      <para>
	To include a mosaic in a schedule file, insert a scan and set:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    &#x201C;<literal>Source</literal>&#x201D;
	    to the name of the mosaic file, excluding the &#x201C;<literal>.mos</literal>&#x201D; extension,
	    i.e. &#x201C;<literal>mosnam</literal>&#x201D;.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    &#x201C;<literal>ScanType</literal>&#x201D;
	    to &#x201C;<literal>Mosaic</literal>&#x201D;
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    &#x201C;<literal>RA</literal>&#x201D; and &#x201C;<literal>Dec</literal>&#x201D;
	    to the reference position for the mosaic, i.e. the position that all
	    the mosaic field centres are offset from. Check this carefully.
	    Then check it again. Although the reference position is usually
	    included as a comment in the mosaic file, <command>caobs</command> reads only
	    the coordinate offsets from the mosaic file. Therefore, if the reference position
	    is set incorrectly in the schedule file, <command>caobs</command> will not warn you,
	    and your observations will fail.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	All other scan settings have their usual effect, including the
	&#x201C;<literal>Pointing</literal>&#x201D; mode, and the observing
	frequencies.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>mosaic</primary><secondary>filename</secondary></indexterm>
	The mosaic file must be placed
	in the <literal>/atca/mosaic</literal> directory on <hardware>xbones</hardware> so
	that <command>caobs</command> can locate it during the
	observations.  The mosaic file name must be completely in
	lowercase letters, even if the corresponding source name in
	the schedule has uppercase letters;
	<command>caobs</command> will report that the mosaic file
	could not be found unless it has an all-lowercase file name.
	The &#x201C;<literal>.mos</literal>&#x201D; suffix is required, or
	<command>caobs</command> will not find the file.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>mosaic</primary><secondary>file</secondary><tertiary>uploading</tertiary></indexterm>
	The file can be copied into position manually, but there is also a
	<ulink url="https://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/sched/mosaic/">web interface</ulink>
	that will ensure your mosaic files are put in the correct location.
      </para>

      <para>
	The time specified in the &#x201C;<literal>ScanLength</literal>&#x201D; field
	in the schedule file will determine how many times the mosaic
	is looped through in a single scan. <command>caobs</command>
	calculates this by dividing the &#x201C;<literal>ScanLength</literal>&#x201D;
	time by the total length of the mosaic and rounding this to
	the nearest integer; this will be the number of times the
	mosaic is repeated during this scan. The mosaic is always observed at least
	once, regardless of the &#x201C;<literal>ScanLength</literal>&#x201D;.
      </para>

      <para>
	It should be noted, in particular for mosaic files containing sources
	spread over a range of RAs, that if <command>caobs</command> encounters a source in
	that has set (or not risen), it will skip to the
	next scan in the schedule file, not to the next source in the
	mosaic file.
      </para>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>Can I see an example mosaic file?</title>
	</info>

	<para>
	  The following example shows a mosaic file specifying a four pointing
	  centre pattern on a 0.25&#x00B0; grid. Note that the RA offsets
	  are coordinate increments not sky distances.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>mosaic</primary><secondary>example</secondary></indexterm>
	</para>
	<informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
	  <tgroup cols="5">
	    <colspec colwidth="25*" colname="left"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="20*" colname="dRA"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="20*" colname="dDec"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="10*" colname="int"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="10*" colname="field"/>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry morerows="6">Mosaic file: <literal>mymap.mos</literal></entry>
		<entry namest="dRA" nameend="field">
		  <literal># mymap.mos by P. Smith</literal>
		</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry namest="dRA" nameend="field">
		  <literal># A four pointing centre mosaic</literal>
		</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry namest="dRA" nameend="field">
		  <literal># Ref. Position = 05:21:33, -65:56:41</literal>
		</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><literal>0.0000</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>0.000</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>2</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>$mymap_1</literal></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><literal>0.6133</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>0.000</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>2</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>$mymap_2</literal></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><literal>0.6133</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>-0.250</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>2</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>$mymap_3</literal></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><literal>0.0000</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>-0.250</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>2</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>$mymap_4</literal></entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</informaltable>

	<para>
	  The scan in the corresponding schedule file might have the
	  parameters:
	</para>
	<informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
	  <tgroup cols="7">
	    <colspec colwidth="15*"></colspec>
	    <colspec colwidth="15*"></colspec>
	    <colspec colwidth="15*"></colspec>
	    <colspec colwidth="15*"></colspec>
	    <colspec colwidth="15*"></colspec>
	    <colspec colwidth="15*"></colspec>
	    <colspec colwidth="10*"></colspec>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry morerows="6"><emphasis role="bold">Scheduler fields:</emphasis></entry>
		<entry><literal>Source:</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>mymap</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>Observer:</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>Smith</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>Project:</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>C555</literal></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><literal>RA:</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>05:21:33</literal></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><literal>Dec:</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>-65:56:41</literal></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><literal>Epoch:</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>J2000</literal></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><literal>ScanLength:</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>00:30:00</literal></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><literal>ScanType:</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>Mosaic</literal></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry><literal>Pointing:</literal></entry>
		<entry><literal>Global</literal></entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</informaltable>

	<para>
	  With these settings, and with the default integration time of 10
	  seconds, the four pointing centres will be observed every 80 seconds.
	  Since the &#x201C;<literal>ScanLength</literal>&#x201D; is 30 minutes, the mosaic will be repeated
	  23 times (22.5 is rounded up), but if the &#x201C;<literal>ScanLength</literal>&#x201D; was 29.5
	  minutes, the mosaic would only be repeated 22 times (22.125 is rounded
	  down).
	</para>

      </section>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>Can I see an example on-the-fly mosaic file?</title>
	</info>

	<para>
	  Here is a 3x3 pointing grid around a source; we use 1934-638, but the same offsets
	  could be used for any source.
	</para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>mosaic</primary><secondary>on-the-fly</secondary><tertiary>example</tertiary></indexterm>
	<screen>
	  0.0000    0.00    2  $@1934-on C
	  -0.1812  -0.16    1  $TURN-10
	  -0.1812  -0.08    1  $1934-11
	  -0.1812   0.00    1  $1934-12
	  -0.1812   0.08    1  $1934-13
	  0.0000    0.16    1  $TURN-24
	  0.0000    0.08    1  $1934-23
	  0.0000    0.00    1  $1934-22
	  0.0000   -0.08    1  $1934-21
	  0.1812   -0.16    1  $TURN-30
	  0.1812   -0.08    1  $1934-31
	  0.1812    0.00    1  $1934-32
	  0.1812    0.08    1  $1934-33
	</screen>
      </para>

      <para>
	Note that you can specify a non-scanning position in an <acronym>OTF</acronym> mosaic file by starting
	the field name with a &#x201C;@&#x201D;, like the 2 cycle calibration on 
	&#x201C;<literal>1934-on</literal>&#x201D; above. Also
	note the fields marked with &#x201C;<literal>TURN</literal>&#x201D; - these are the extra 
	points required at the
	start of each scanning row/column to give the antennas time to get to the correct position
	and scanning speed. They should be discarded when processing the data.
      </para>

      <para>
	Note also that all other pointing centres in the <acronym>OTF</acronym> mosaic file
	are only observed for 1 cycle. This cannot be changed, since the antenna will be
	moving while it observes each pointing.
      </para>

      <para>
	To use
	the <acronym>OTF</acronym> mosaic mode, specify a scantype of 
	&#x201C;<literal>OTFMos</literal>&#x201D; in the web scheduler and
	put a mosaic file like the one above in &#x201C;<literal>/atca/mosaic</literal>&#x201D; on 
	<hardware>xbones</hardware>.
      </para>

      </section>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>Is there an easy way to make a mosaic file?</title>
	</info>

	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>mosaic</primary><secondary>generating</secondary></indexterm>
	  The <application>Miriad</application> tasks 
	  <ulink url="https://www.atnf.csiro.au/computing/software/miriad/doc/mosgen.html">
	    <command>mosgen</command></ulink> and
	    <ulink url="https://www.atnf.csiro.au/computing/software/miriad/doc/atmos.html">
	      <command>atmos</command></ulink> may be useful when you are preparing your mosaic file.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>mosaic</primary><secondary>mosgen</secondary></indexterm>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Miriad</primary><secondary>tasks</secondary><tertiary>mosgen</tertiary></indexterm>
	  If you need to map a region of known size around a known sky location,
	  you will want to use <command>mosgen</command>. It will overlap each pointing
	  correctly with hexagonal tiling, and will ensure that the pointings are
	  observed with minimal overhead.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>mosaic</primary><secondary>atmos</secondary></indexterm>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Miriad</primary><secondary>tasks</secondary><tertiary>atmos</tertiary></indexterm>
	  If you have a number of specific locations you want to observe, you will
	  want to use <command>atmos</command>, as it will ensure that the offsets are correct
	  and that the route between the pointings is optimised (the &#x201C;travelling
	  salesman&#x201D; problem).
	</para>

	<para>
	  <emphasis role="bold">We do not recommend that you manually calculate the offset positions
	  for your mosaic.</emphasis> An error in calculating the offsets will likely ruin your
	  observations. Such an error is easily avoidable by using the <application>Miriad</application>
	  tasks.
	</para>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>How do I best map regions of spectral line emission?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>spectral line</secondary></indexterm>
	How large the mapping region is will determine whether you can image using
	standard snapshot observations, or if you will need to use mosaicking. In either
	case, the imaging strategy is no different to that of a continuum observation,
	but you may need more frequent calibration to ensure you get a sufficient signal
	to noise ratio for your lines; <acronym>CABB</acronym>'s extra bandwidth doesn't
	help you observe a single line at known redshift!
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>CABB</primary><secondary>bad channels</secondary></indexterm>
	If you're looking for your spectral line in one of the <acronym>CABB</acronym> continuum
	<acronym>IF</acronym>s, one of the most important things to consider is where the line
	to be observed will fall within the bandpass, ie. which channel(s) it will
	appear in. There are several channels in the <acronym>CABB</acronym> continuum
	<acronym>IF</acronym>s that are always flagged, and
	several more that are often contaminated with self-generated interference, and
	these should be avoided when observing spectral lines.
      </para>

      <para>
	The <acronym>CABB</acronym> correlator always flags the centre continuum channel and each of the
	quarter-band channels. If you select a <acronym>CABB</acronym> mode that provides 1 MHz continuum
	channels, the flagged channels will be 513, 1025 and 1537. For <acronym>CABB</acronym> modes that
	provide 64 MHz continuum channels, the flagged channels will be 9, 17 and 25.
	You should avoid making the central <acronym>CABB</acronym>
	continuum frequency the same as the expected frequency of the line.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>CABB</primary><secondary>birdies</secondary></indexterm>
	Self-generated interference will likely be present in the 1 MHz continuum channels 129, 157, 257,
	641, 769, 1153, 1177, 1281, 1409, 1793 and 1921. All these channels can be
	easily flagged with the online correlator software (and they routinely are) and the interference does
	not leak into the adjacent channels.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary><secondary>self-generated</secondary></indexterm>
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>CABB</primary><secondary>zoom bands</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>zooms</secondary></indexterm>
	If you are using the <acronym>CABB</acronym> zoom bands to detect your spectral line, you should
	again avoid using one of the continuum channels listed above, especially the quarter- and half-band
	channels. The zoom bands derived from those channels will usually have a very large spike at the
	centre of the zoom, and this spike may leak into adjacent channels since the zoom channels are
	not perfectly square. However, since the zooms come from the interleaved channels, the zoom channel
	number is derived from the continuum channel number by multiplying by 2 and subtracting 1. For example,
	channel 17 in the 64 MHz continuum band is actually zoom channel
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">17\times 2 - 1 = 33</textobject></inlineequation>.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>Doppler tracking</primary></indexterm>
	It is important to note that <acronym>ATCA</acronym> is not able to Doppler track. You will need
	to ask for enough frequency coverage to ensure that your line will not drift out of the band due
	to observatory velocity changes.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	Calibration of spectral-line observations is done with the same
	&#x201C;snapshot&#x201D; strategy that was described in
	<xref linkend="scheduling-snapshots"></xref>. It is important to note however that
	the calibration itself is slightly different. Because accurate measurements of
	a spectral line requires good bandpass characterisation, but in general you are dealing
	with much smaller bandwidths than for continuum observations, you will need to observe
	calibrators with higher flux densities, observe the calibrators for longer, or observe the calibrators
	more often in order to get a sufficient signal-to-noise ratio.
      </para>
    </section>
      
    <section id="strategy-frequency-switching">
      <info>
	<title>Are there limits to the frequencies I can observe?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>frequencies</secondary>
	<tertiary>allowed</tertiary></indexterm>
	There are many restrictions on the frequencies that can be observed with the
	<acronym>CABB</acronym> system. The most basic restriction is that only two
	2048 MHz <acronym>IF</acronym>s can be observed simultaneously. All of the additional
	zoom bands must lie within these <acronym>IF</acronym>s, so they do not count as
	&#x201C;extra&#x201D; bandwidth. You can only specify the central continuum
	frequencies to MHz precision.
      </para>

      <para>
	If you want to use the entire array for a single band, then there are
	band-specific restrictions on the frequencies that can be observed.
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      In the 16cm band, the central frequency of each continuum <acronym>IF</acronym>
	      must obey
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\nu_{\mathrm{C}} \geq 1728</textobject>
	      </inlineequation>
	      MHz.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      In the 4cm band, the central frequency of each continuum <acronym>IF</acronym> must obey
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">4928 \leq \nu_{\mathrm{C}} \leq 10928</textobject>
	      </inlineequation> MHz.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      In each of the mm bands, the centre frequencies of the two continuum
	      <acronym>IF</acronym>s cannot be separated by more than 6000 MHz, ie.
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">|\nu_{\mathrm{C}1} - \nu_{\mathrm{C}2}| \leq 6000
	      </textobject></inlineequation> MHz.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      In the 15mm band, the central frequency of each continuum <acronym>IF</acronym> must obey
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">16001 \leq \nu_{\mathrm{C}} \leq 25472
	      </textobject></inlineequation> MHz.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      In the 7mm band, the central frequency of each continuum <acronym>IF</acronym> must obey
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">30001 \leq \nu_{\mathrm{C}} \leq 49999
	      </textobject></inlineequation> MHz.
	    </para>
	    
	    <para>
	      In addition, the <acronym>IF</acronym> centre frequencies must both be below 40673 MHz, 
	      or both be above 41227 MHz.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      In the 3mm band, the central frequency of each continuum <acronym>IF</acronym>
	      must obey
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">82501 \leq \nu_{\mathrm{C}} \leq 117699
	      </textobject></inlineequation> MHz.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>split band</secondary></indexterm>
	If you don't need all the baselines in the same band, it is possible to split the array up
	so you can observe in two bands simultaneously. For each of the two <acronym>CABB</acronym>
	continuum <acronym>IF</acronym>s you can select a set of antennas to use with the
	<command>caobs</command> command &#x201C;<literal>set band1_antennas</literal>&#x201D;.
	In this way you can specify a frequency in <acronym>IF</acronym>1 that is in a different band
	to the frequency specified in <acronym>IF</acronym>2. The antennas specified in the
	&#x201C;<literal>band1_antennas</literal>&#x201D; would use the <acronym>IF</acronym>1
	band, while the rest of the array would use the <acronym>IF</acronym>2 band.
      </para>

      <para>
	The primary restriction in this mode is the central site oscillator. Since there is only one
	central site oscillator that feeds the entire array's L86 modules, if you want to observe in more
	than one mm band simultaneously, both the frequencies must be observable with the same
	central site frequency.
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      You cannot observe in both the 15mm and 3mm bands simultaneously.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Observing in the 15mm and 7mm bands simultaneously is possible if the 15mm central
	      continuum frequency obeys
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">16092 \leq \nu_{\mathrm{C}15\mathrm{mm}} \leq 25472</textobject>
	      </inlineequation> MHz, and the 7mm central frequency obeys either
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">30001 \leq \nu_{\mathrm{C}7\mathrm{mm}} \leq 40673</textobject>
	      </inlineequation> MHz, or
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">45458 \leq \nu_{\mathrm{C}7\mathrm{mm}} \leq 49999</textobject>
	      </inlineequation> MHz.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Observing in the 7mm and 3mm bands simultaneously is possible if the 7mm central
	      continuum frequency obeys either
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">30001 \leq \nu_{\mathrm{C}7\mathrm{mm}} \leq 35152</textobject>
	      </inlineequation> MHz, or
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">41708 \leq \nu_{\mathrm{C}7\mathrm{mm}} \leq 49999</textobject>
	      </inlineequation> MHz, and the 3mm central frequency obeys either
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">87152 \leq \nu_{\mathrm{C}3\mathrm{mm}} \leq 101952</textobject>
	      </inlineequation> MHz, or
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">103008 \leq \nu_{\mathrm{C}3\mathrm{mm}} \leq 117699</textobject>
	      </inlineequation> MHz.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	Since neither the 16cm or 4cm bands need the central site synthesiser, there are no special
	frequency restrictions when one of the simultaneous bands is 16cm or 4cm.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>Can I change between frequencies during my observations?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>frequency</primary><secondary>switching</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>frequency switching</secondary></indexterm>
	It isn't possible with <acronym>CABB</acronym> to observe more than 4096 MHz of bandwidth
	simultaneously, but it is possible to quickly switch between frequencies within
	a single band, and also to swap between different bands with only a moderate
	loss of simultaneity.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>overheads</primary><secondary>frequency switching</secondary></indexterm>
	If you want to change frequencies, you will need to start a new scan in the schedule. This
	restriction makes it impossible to change frequencies within a mosaic. Whenever you change
	scans you will experience two integration cycles of overhead, and if you are changing frequencies within
	a band, this is the only applicable overhead. For example, if you changed your central
	continuum frequencies from 5500 &amp; 7500 MHz to 6500 &amp; 8500 MHz, you will only need
	to incur two cycles of overhead as the scan is changed.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>overheads</primary><secondary>zoom switching</secondary></indexterm>
	There is also no extra overhead when changing the zoom band configuration, which is simply
	viewed as a change of frequency within the same band.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>turret</primary><secondary>rotation</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>receiver</primary><secondary>translator</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>overheads</primary><secondary>turret rotation</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>overheads</primary><secondary>receiver translation</secondary></indexterm>
	If you are changing bands, you will likely incur more overhead. In this case, the turret
	on the antennas will need to rotate to put the new receiver at the right position, and if
	you are changing to or from the 7mm band the mm receiver package will need to be
	moved using the translator as well. Turret rotations will usually add only a few cycles of
	overhead at most, since the turret can be rotating during the normal two cycle overhead
	that occurs at every change of cycle. Translating the receiver to go to or from the 7mm
	band takes much longer: between 2 and 3 minutes.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>subreflector</primary><secondary>focus</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>overheads</primary><secondary>focusing</secondary></indexterm>
	When you change bands you may also have to refocus the antenna by moving the subreflector.
	When going to or from the 4cm band, all antennas need to be refocused, and this
	takes approximately 90 seconds. When going to or from the 3mm band, antenna CA01 needs to
	be refocused, and will take approximately 40 seconds.
      </para>

      <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">WARNING:</emphasis> Movement of the turret does produce wear on the
	bearing, and it would be extremely difficult to replace it should it fail. We therefore ask
	that observers not change bands more than once every 15 minutes.
      </para>
      
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>How do I observe a planet in our Solar System?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>planets</secondary></indexterm>
	To schedule an observation of a major planetary object, simply put
	its name in the &#x201C;<literal>Source</literal>&#x201D; field of a scan. During the observations,
	<command>caobs</command> will interpret this name and calculate where the planet, Sun
	or Moon is and point the array towards it.
      </para>

      <para>
	The scheduler will not automatically calculate where the planet will be during
	the scheduling process, unless you enter the appropriate date and LST or UTC and then
	click on the &#x201C;<literal>Listing</literal>&#x201D; tab. At this point, the
	scheduler will determine the planet's position and fill the &#x201C;<literal>RA</literal>&#x201D; and
	&#x201C;<literal>Dec</literal>&#x201D; fields. Alternatively, you could use 
	the <application>Miriad</application> task <command>planets</command>.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>Miriad</primary><secondary>tasks</secondary><tertiary>planets</tertiary></indexterm>
      </para>

      <para>
	It is useful to note again that the &#x201C;<literal>RA</literal>&#x201D; and
	&#x201C;<literal>Dec</literal>&#x201D; fields are ignored by <command>caobs</command>
	when the source name is recognised as a planet, the Sun or the Moon, as
	<command>caobs</command> will compute the appropriate position for the body in
	real time. There is no reason therefore to prefer absolute time scheduling when
	observing planets.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>How do I observe a minor object in our Solar System?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>Solar System</secondary></indexterm>
	Solar system objects differ from most astronomical sources in that the
	proper motions are large enough that the object position may change in the
	course of an observation. <command>caobs</command> has the ability to phase track
	an object with a non-sidereal rate, and command the antennas to correctly track it as well.
	If the object moves across the sky too quickly however, the antenna speed limits may
	prevent you from tracking the object.
      </para>

      <para>
	For minor bodies, <command>caobs</command> cannot compute a position, so the correct
	position must be provided by the user. The scheduler
	treats source names beginning with the @ symbol (eg. a source name of
	<literal>@hbopp</literal>) as pointing to an external ephemeris file (eg. a file
	<literal>$ATCA_EPHEM:hbopp.eph</literal>).
      </para>

      <para>
	Ephemerides for minor solar system bodies can be computed before scheduling
	using
	<ulink url="https://ssd.jpl.nasa.gov/?horizons">JPL's Horizons on-line system</ulink>.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>ephemerides</primary><secondary>Solar system</secondary></indexterm>
	Only the <command>telnet</command> (terminal-based) access method is described here, but there
	is also a web-interface method available from the
	<ulink url="https://ssd.jpl.nasa.gov/horizons/app.html#/">web page</ulink>
	that is self-explanatory.
      </para>

      <para>
	Horizons asks the user a series of questions. To generate an ephemeris file
	for <acronym>ATCA</acronym> observations:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <programlisting>telnet horizons.jpl.nasa.gov 6775</programlisting>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    First select an object by giving the source name (followed by a
	    semi-colon for minor bodies) or by source number.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    In response to prompts, select &#x201C;<literal>Ephemeris</literal>&#x201D;, then
	    &#x201C;<literal>Observe</literal>&#x201D;, then 
	    &#x201C;<literal>Geo</literal>&#x201D; to select geocentric RA/Dec ephemerides.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Give the start time of interest, in UTC, in the format
	    suggested by the prompt. At the next prompt give the end time, and then the
	    time increment; typically 1 minute (&#x201C;<literal>1m</literal>&#x201D;)
	    will give you the best chance to accurately track the object. The scheduler
	    uses simple linear interpolation of the ephemeris values. The ephemeris
	    supplied to the scheduler must start at least two time increments before
	    the scheduled start time, and must extend beyond its end time.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Accept &#x201C;<literal>default output</literal>&#x201D;, and at the
	    &#x201C;<literal>Select table quantities</literal>&#x201D; prompt, enter 
	    &#x201C;<literal>1,20</literal>&#x201D; to get RA, Dec,
	    distance and velocity of the object.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Horizons will then display the ephemeris in the terminal. To get it
	    to email the ephemeris, press &#x201C;<literal>q</literal>&#x201D; and the main menu will be displayed
	    again. Then select &#x201C;<literal>[M]ail</literal>&#x201D; and enter the email address to send the
	    ephemeris to.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    To log out of Horizons, press &#x201C;<literal>Ctrl-D</literal>&#x201D; (the terminal hangup signal).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	The ephemeris file produced by Horizons needs to be massaged into the format
	that the scheduler requires. This is best achieved with the <command>ephformat</command>
	command available on <hardware>xbones</hardware>.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    First, copy the ephemeris from the email sent by Horizons into a plain
	    text file on <hardware>xbones</hardware>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Run the command <command>ephformat</command> with no arguments.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    At the first prompt, give the name of the text file with the Horizons
	    ephemeris (including file extension). At the second prompt, give a short
	    descriptive name for the output ephemeris file (excluding any file extension).
	    <command>ephformat</command> will then write out the appropriate ephemeris file to
	    &#x201C;<literal>$ATCA_EPHEM:file.eph</literal>&#x201D; where 
	    &#x201C;<literal>file</literal>&#x201D; is the name entered at the
	    second prompt.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	To use the ephemeris you just created in the schedule, enter the name of the
	ephemeris (the &#x201C;<literal>file</literal>&#x201D; name described in the last
	dot point above), preceded by the &#x201C;<literal>@</literal>&#x201D; symbol, into
	the &#x201C;<literal>Source</literal>&#x201D; field of the web scheduler.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id="scheduling-antenna-wraps">
      <info>
	<title>What are the antenna &#x201C;wraps&#x201D;?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>antenna</primary><secondary>wrap limits</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>wrap</primary><secondary>limits</secondary></indexterm>
	There is a limit to how far the antennas can slew in azimuth.
	The limit arises because of all the cabling inside the antenna which
	passes up the centre of the structure to the receiving and cryogenic
	equipment in the vertex room.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>vertex room</primary></indexterm>
	There is a limit to how far these cables can wrap around in either direction
	(similar to the head of an owl).
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The wrap limits for the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> antennas are CCW=152.5&#x00B0; and
	CW=327.5&#x00B0; as shown in <xref linkend="wraplimits"></xref>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	<figure id="wraplimits">
	  <title>Wrap limits for the Compact Array and Mopra antennas.</title>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/wrap.jpg" format="JPG">
	      </imagedata>
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>
      </para>
      
      <para>
	It is a good idea to check what wrap the telescope is in at the
	start of your observations, as &#x201C;unwrapping&#x201D; can take up to 10 minutes.
	To determine the wrap you are in, consult <application>MoniCA</application> or <command>atdrivemon</command>.
	<application>MoniCA</application> shows the wrap explicitly, on the 
	&#x201C;<acronym>ATCA</acronym> Summary&#x201D; page.
	<command>atdrivemon</command> shows the azimuth using the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> convention &#x2014;
	while in the South wrap azimuths are expressed as positive angles,
	and negative angles in the North wrap.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>How do I prepare a schedule file?</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>schedule</primary><secondary>file</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>schedule</primary><secondary>file</secondary><tertiary>preparation</tertiary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>schedule</primary><secondary>web scheduler</secondary></indexterm>
	The <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/sched/cabb/">
	<acronym>CABB</acronym> web scheduler</ulink>
	is used to prepare schedule files. The web scheduler
	checks the schedule for completeness and, where
	possible, checks choices such as observing frequency for hardware
	compatibility. Drive times, and source azimuths and elevations can also
	be computed to enable you to estimate overheads and observability.
      </para>

      <para>
	Three steps are involved in using the web scheduler:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A new scan is added to the schedule.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The details of the scan are changed as desired.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    When all the scans have been defined, the entire schedule is written to file.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	When constructing a schedule, consider:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Is the sequence of sources sensible, and how much time is
	    expended on slewing?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Does the schedule contain all the sources, and at the
	    appropriate frequencies and bandwidths?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	The web scheduler can produce a listing to help answer these questions.
	It is a good idea to study these listings very
	carefully before observing commences. The scheduler considers drive times:
	all coordinate entries are automatically followed by a calculation of the
	azimuth and elevation of the source, as well as the drive time from
	the previous source, using the entered value for LST. When making
	a schedule file, the integration times are specified
	for each source (and calibrator source). Note that,
	except in the case of mosaic schedules and <literal>Dwell</literal> scan types,
	these integration times
	include drive times, so the specified time must be somewhat longer
	than the amount of integration on source required. This is
	particularly important for gain calibrators, when the drive time
	(up to a minute or so) may be comparable to the integration time
	(one to three minutes). Alternatively, the <literal>ScanType</literal> field can
	be set to <literal>Dwell</literal> to ensure a source or calibrator
	is tracked for the specified scan duration.
      </para>

      <para>
	The schedule file submitted to <command>caobs</command> (the online Compact Array control
	task) need have no specific start time. Rather, the schedule file asks
	<command>caobs</command> to start the first scan as soon as possible. The sequence of
	scans will be exactly as specified in the schedule file. However, when
	using the web scheduler, the calculation of azimuths, elevations and drive times
	is possible only if the starting sidereal time is known (at least
	approximately). The sidereal time for the first scan in the schedule
	can be set in the web scheduler by giving the time in the <literal>Time</literal> field,
	and setting <literal>TimeCode</literal> to <literal>LST</literal>. Alternatively, the starting UT
	may be specified by setting <literal>TimeCode</literal> to <literal>UT</literal>, and by setting
	the <literal>Date</literal> to the appropriate start date by clicking on it and using
	the calendar that appears. Note that when viewing any scan other than the
	first in the schedule, the fields <literal>Time</literal>, <literal>TimeCode</literal> and
	<literal>Date</literal> all become read-only.
      </para>

      <para>
	The environment flag can be used to instruct the online software to
	remember certain settings, such as attenuators, and to recall them whenever
	a scan with the same environment flag is encountered. However, this is
	generally not required, as the online software will remember user settings,
	and recall them when the same conditions are encountered again. There are
	at least 128 slots for user settings, so for a normal schedule, the
	environment flag will probably not need to be used.
      </para>

      <para>
	See <xref linkend="Web-Scheduler"></xref> for a complete guide to all the functionality
	available in the web scheduler.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Continuum-Schedule-Example">
      <info>
	<title>Could I see an example continuum schedule file?</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	Yes! In this section a simple continuum schedule file is constructed. It will contain
	three sources: a program source and two calibration sources. The
	following observing sequence will be specified:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Setup calibrator (0537-441, a catalogued source) for 5 minutes,
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Program source (R.A. 05:21:35.5, Dec. -21:24:27.1 (J2000)) for 30 mins,
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A gain calibrator for 5 minutes.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	These sources will be observed at the standard 4cm band frequencies of
	5500/9000 MHz.
	To create this schedule file, perform the following steps (instructions are given in
	bold, and the results of the instruction, or important caveats, and described below it):
      </para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Navigate to the <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/sched/cabb/">
	    <acronym>CABB</acronym> web scheduler</ulink> in a web browser.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The first screen is displayed.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Change the <literal>Source</literal> field to <literal>test</literal>,
	    the <literal>RA</literal> field to <literal>05:21:35.5</literal> 
	    and the <literal>Dec</literal> field to <literal>-21:24:27.1</literal>.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The delimiter for coordinates must
	      be a colon, and the default <literal>Epoch</literal> of <literal>J2000</literal> should only be
	      changed if necessary.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Change <literal>ScanLength</literal> to 00:30:00
	    and change the <literal>ScanType</literal> to <literal>Dwell</literal>.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This ensures that	30 minutes are spent on source, regardless of slewing times.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Ensure <literal>Pointing</literal> is set to <literal>Global</literal>.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Offset pointing is not required for low-frequency observations.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Change the <literal>Observer</literal> field to <literal>Wild</literal>,
	    the <literal>Project</literal> code to <literal>C123</literal>.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      These fields should be set in the first source - they will propagate to
	      the other sources as they are added.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Change the <literal>Time</literal> field to <literal>02:00:00</literal>,
	    and the <literal>TimeCode</literal> field to <literal>LST</literal>.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This indicates that the schedule will be started at an approximate LST of 2h.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click the <literal>Freq1 Setup</literal> bar.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This brings up the frequency selection fields.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Enter <literal>5500</literal> in the <literal>Continuum</literal> frequency box, 
	    and keep the <literal>Chn. BW</literal> selection box to <literal>1</literal> MHz.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The velocity resolution should be calculated to be 55 km/s, and the
	      velocity range will be 111632 km/s.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click the <literal>Freq2 Setup</literal> bar.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This brings up the frequency selection fields.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Enter <literal>9000</literal> in the <literal>Continuum</literal> frequency 
	    box, and keep the <literal>Chn. BW</literal> selection box to <literal>1</literal> MHz.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The velocity resolution should be calculated to be 33 km/s, and the
	      velocity range will be 68219 km/s.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click the <literal>Scan Parameters</literal> bar.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This brings up the scan details.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click the <literal>Search Cal</literal> button.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This presents a list of
	      nearby calibrators to the right of the scan details, sorted by distance
	      to the source. The closest source to the program source with a moderate flux density
	      (&gt; 1 Jy) is shown to be 0454-234, at a distance of 6.02&#x00B0;.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click on the <literal>0454-234</literal> button.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The details for this source are displayed from the calibrator database
	      below the source list. This source is a suitable gain calibrator
	      as it has a decent flux density, has a defect less than 0.1% and a closure phase less than
	      0.3%.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click on the <literal>0454-234</literal> button again.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Clicking on the button twice (without clicking another source button
	      between clicks) inserts this source into the schedule above the currently
	      selected source.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select source 1, and change the <literal>ScanLength</literal>
	    field to 00:05:00.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">To copy this source to the end of the schedule, click on the 
	    <literal>Edit</literal> menu and select <literal>Copy</literal>, then select the 
	    <literal>test</literal> source, click on <literal>Edit</literal> and select 
	    <literal>Paste</literal>.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The schedule should now have three sources (in order): 0454-234, test,
	      0454-234. The first source needs to be changed to 0537-441.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select source 1</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Change the <literal>Source</literal> field to 0537-441 and press 
	    <literal>TAB</literal>.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The scheduler will automatically put the source coordinates for
	      this known calibrator in the <literal>RA</literal> and <literal>Dec</literal> fields.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click on the <literal>File</literal> menu and select <literal>Save As</literal>.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The <literal>Schedule file selector</literal> window will appear.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">The schedule will be called c123_test.sch, so enter this into the 
	    <literal>Filter</literal> box to ensure that there is not already a schedule with this name.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If there is another schedule with the
	      desired name, consider changing it.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Enter <literal>c123_test.sch</literal> into the <literal>Schedule</literal> 
	    box and press the <literal>Save</literal> button.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The file selection window will
	      disappear, and the name of the schedule should now appear at the top
	      of the window.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>
	To produce a listing of the schedule, in order to check that the
	schedule proceeds as expected, click on the <literal>Listing</literal> tab.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Zoom-Mode-Schedule-Example">
      <info>
	<title>Could I see an example spectral-line schedule file?</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	Yes! This example adds to the example from the previous section; ensure that the
	schedule created in the previous section is in the scheduler before continuing.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	Now the aim is to observe 1 zoom band in each <acronym>IF</acronym>, each covering at least
	70 km/s. The galaxy
	&#x201C;test&#x201D; is actually at an LSR recessional velocity of 25000 km/s,
	and these observations will look for CH<subscript>3</subscript>OH methanol and 
	HC<subscript>3</subscript>N cyanoacetylene lines.
      </para>

      <para>
	To create a schedule that can perform suitable observations for this situation,
	follow the steps:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select the first scan in the schedule.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This should be 0537-441.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select the <literal>Global change</literal> menu item from 
	    the <literal>Tools</literal> menu before
	    changing the <literal>Date</literal> of this scan to 30/11/2014.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The date that the observation will be performed is required to ensure that
	      the observatory velocity is computed correctly.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Hit the <literal>Global Apply</literal> button.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The date will now change for all the sources in the schedule.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select the <literal>Advanced view</literal> menu item from
	    the <literal>Tools</literal> menu.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      You should now see many more input fields.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select the &#x201C;<literal>test</literal>&#x201D; source in the schedule,
	    then enter &#x201C;<literal>25000</literal>&#x201D; into the <literal>CatVel</literal> field, and
	    press TAB.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The entry in the <literal>CatVel</literal> field should now read
	      &#x201C;<literal>25000 lsr radio</literal>&#x201D; as the default frame is LSR, in the
	      radio convention.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click the <literal>Freq1 5500MHz</literal> bar.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This brings up the IF1 frequency selection fields.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click the topmost <literal>Velo</literal> button.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This brings up the velocity calculator.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select the <literal>CH3OH</literal> line from the <literal>Spectral Line</literal> 
	    dropdown box.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The rest frequency of this line (6668.518) appears in the <literal>Rest Frequency</literal>
	      box below.
	      The <literal>Sky Frequency</literal> will be updated to 6112.092 MHz, and the zoom band
	      frequency will be calculated as the nearest half-MHz, in this case as <literal>6112</literal> MHz.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click the <literal>Apply</literal> button in the velocity calculator.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The velocity calculator will disappear and information will be inserted into the
	      first zoom band. In this case, the <literal>6112</literal> MHz frequency translates into
	      the channel <literal>3273</literal>. The velocity resolution is given as 0.024 km/s, and the
	      velocity range is listed as 49 km/s.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select the zoom band width to be <literal>2</literal> from the width drop box.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The velocity range now increases to 73.6 km/s.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click the <literal>Freq2 9000MHz</literal> bar.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This brings up the IF2 frequency selection fields.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click the topmost <literal>Velo</literal> button.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This brings up the velocity calculator as before.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select the <literal>HC3N</literal> line from the <literal>Spectral Line</literal> 
	    dropdown box.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The rest frequency of this line (9098.332) appears in the <literal>Rest Frequency</literal>
	      box below, and the <literal>Sky Frequency</literal> will be updated to 8339.161 MHz. The
	      zoom band frequency will be calculated to be <literal>8339</literal> MHz.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click the <literal>Apply</literal> button in the velocity calculator.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The velocity calculator will disappear and information will be inserted into the
	      first zoom band. In this case, the <literal>8339</literal> MHz frequency translates into
	      the channel <literal>727</literal>. The velocity resolution is given as 0.018 km/s, and the
	      velocity range is listed as 36 km/s.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select the zoom band width to be <literal>3</literal> from the width drop box.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The velocity range now increases to 71.9 km/s, comparable to the width provided
	      for the IF1 zoom band.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Click the <literal>Scan Parameters</literal> bar.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This brings up the scan details.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select the <literal>Master1</literal> option from the <literal>FreqConfig</literal>
	    dropdown box.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This signifies that the frequency configuration, including the zoom modes, from
	      this scan, should be defined as the master configuration.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select the <literal>0537-441</literal> source from the schedule,
	    then elect the <literal>Slave-1</literal> option from the 
	    <literal>FreqConfig</literal> dropdown box.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Now this scan will exactly mirror the frequency and zoom mode configuration from
	      the <literal>test</literal> scan, even if the configuration of the <literal>test</literal> scan is
	      changed. When a scan is set as a slave scan, the <literal>Freq</literal> panels will display
	      a message describing which frequency and scan it is slaved to.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <emphasis role="bold">Select the <literal>0454-234</literal> source from the schedule,
	    then select the <literal>Slave-1</literal> option from the <literal>FreqConfig</literal> dropdown box.</emphasis>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Now this scan will exactly mirror the frequency and zoom mode configuration from
	      the <literal>test</literal> scan.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>
	At this point, the schedule would correctly describe a zoom mode observation.
      </para>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="observations-execution">
    <info>
      <title>Running a schedule</title>
    </info>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>How can I calculate how much data will be produced?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>data</primary><secondary>rate</secondary><tertiary>calculating</tertiary></indexterm>
	The data rate during <acronym>CABB</acronym> observations can be calculated with the
	formula:
	<equation id="equation_dataratecycle">
	  <title><acronym>CABB</acronym> data rate per cycle</title>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}} = \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{corr}} \times \left(\sum_{i=1}^{N_{\mathrm{IFs}}} N_{\mathrm{channels}}(i) \times \sum_{j=1}^{N_{\mathrm{Stokes}}(i)}\sum_{k=1}^{N_{\mathrm{products}}(i)} N_{\mathrm{bins}}(i,j,k)\right),
	  </textobject>
	</equation>
	where 
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}</textobject></inlineequation>
	      is the number of bytes produced per integration cycle,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{corr}}</textobject></inlineequation>
	      is the number of bytes per correlation product, and 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{IFs}}</textobject></inlineequation>
	      is the number of IFs,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{channels}}(i)</textobject></inlineequation>
	      is the number of channels in IF
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">i</textobject></inlineequation>,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{Stokes}}(i)</textobject></inlineequation>
	      is the number of Stokes quantities in IF
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">i</textobject></inlineequation>,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{products}}(i)</textobject></inlineequation>
	      is the number of correlation products in IF
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">i</textobject></inlineequation>,
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{bins}}(i,j,k)</textobject></inlineequation>
	      is the number of bins in IF
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">i</textobject></inlineequation>,
	      Stokes parameter
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">j</textobject></inlineequation> and
	      correlation product
	      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">k</textobject></inlineequation>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	The data-rate per second is thus:
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \frac{\mathrm{b}}{1 \mathrm{\,second}} = \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}\frac{t_{\mathrm{cycle}}}{1 \mathrm{\,second}},
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
	where <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">t_{\mathrm{cycle}}</textobject></inlineequation>
	the cycle time of the correlator.
      </para>

      <para>
	A few example calculations are given below. In all cases it is assumed that
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{corr}}=8</textobject></inlineequation>
	bytes (in all modes, 4 bytes are recorded for each of the complex visibilities, and 4
	bytes are recorded for the weight component), and
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">t_{\mathrm{cycle}}=10</textobject></inlineequation>
	seconds.
      </para>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>How much data is produced for a typical continuum observation?</title>
	</info>
	
	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>data</primary><secondary>rate</secondary>
	  <tertiary>continuum observing</tertiary></indexterm>
	  For a typical continuum observation, we have:
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		2 IFs
		(<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{IFs}}=2</textobject></inlineequation>),
		each with
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      2049 channels
		      (<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{channels}}(1-2)=2049</textobject></inlineequation>),
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      4 Stokes parameters (XX, YY, XY, YX;
		      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{Stokes}}(1-2)=4</textobject></inlineequation>),
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      21 correlator products
		      (6 auto-correlation and 15 cross-correlation spectra;
		      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{products}}(1-2)=21</textobject></inlineequation>).
		      <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			  <para>
			    Each auto-correlation same-polarisation (XX, YY) spectrum has 2 bins (noise diode on and
			    noise diode off;
			    <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{bins}}(1-2,1-2,1-6)=2</textobject></inlineequation>).
			  </para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			  <para>
			    Each auto-correlation cross-polarisation (XY, YX) spectrum has 1 bin 
			    <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{bins}}(1-2,3-4,1-6)=1</textobject></inlineequation>).
			  </para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			  <para>
			    Each cross-correlation spectrum has 1 bin
			    (<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{bins}}(1-2,1-4,7-21)=1</textobject></inlineequation>).
			  </para>
			</listitem>
		      </itemizedlist>
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  Putting this in <xref linkend="equation_dataratecycle"></xref> we get
	  <informalequation>
	    <textobject role="tex">
	      \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}} = 8 \times \left(2\times 2049 \times \left(2 \times 6 \times 2 + 2 \times 6 \times 1 + 4 \times 15 \times 1\right)\right) = 3,147,264.
	    </textobject>
	  </informalequation>
	</para>

	<para>
	  This works out to be a data rate of 0.300 MiB per second, or roughly 1.055 GiB per hour.
	  <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> we use the binary prefixes MiB and GiB (the mebibyte and
	  gibibyte) for data sizes. See <ulink url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gibibyte">Wikipedia</ulink>
	  for a good explanation.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Since <acronym>CABB</acronym> data files will automatically close when they reach
	  4.0 GiB in size, it would take approximately 3 h 47 m to fill one file (not accounting
	  for the overhead consumed by the header information).
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>How much data is produced for an observation with all zooms individually recorded?</title>
	</info>
	
	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>data</primary><secondary>rate</secondary>
	  <tertiary>spectral line observing</tertiary></indexterm>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>data</primary><secondary>rate</secondary>
	  <tertiary>maximum</tertiary></indexterm>
	  For an observation where each of the 16 zooms in each IF is recorded, and no zooms
	  are consolidated, we have:
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		34 IFs
		(<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{IFs}}=34</textobject></inlineequation>).
		Two of these are the continuum IFs, each having
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      2049 channels
		      (<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{channels}}(1-2)=2049</textobject></inlineequation>),
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      4 Stokes parameters (XX, YY, XY, YX;
		      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{Stokes}}(1-2)=4</textobject></inlineequation>),
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      21 correlator products
		      (6 auto-correlation and 15 cross-correlation spectra;
		      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{products}}(1-2)=21</textobject></inlineequation>).
		      <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			  <para>
			    Each auto-correlation same-polarisation (XX, YY) spectrum has 2 bins (noise diode on and
			    noise diode off;
			    <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{bins}}(1-2,1-2,1-6)=2</textobject></inlineequation>).
			  </para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			  <para>
			    Each auto-correlation cross-polarisation (XY, YX) spectrum has 1 bin 
			    <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{bins}}(1-2,3-4,1-6)=1</textobject></inlineequation>).
			  </para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			  <para>
			    Each cross-correlation spectrum has 1 bin
			    (<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{bins}}(1-2,1-4,7-21)=1</textobject></inlineequation>).
			  </para>
			</listitem>
		      </itemizedlist>
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The other 32 IFs are the zoom bands, each having
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      2049 channels
		      (<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{channels}}(3-34)=2049</textobject></inlineequation>),
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      4 Stokes parameters (XX, YY, XY, YX;
		      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{Stokes}}(3-34)=4</textobject></inlineequation>),
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      21 correlator products
		      (6 auto-correlation and 15 cross-correlation spectra;
		      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{products}}(3-34)=21</textobject></inlineequation>).
		      <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			  <para>
			    Each spectrum has 1 bin
			    (<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{bins}}(3-34,1-4,1-21)=1</textobject></inlineequation>).
			  </para>
			</listitem>
		      </itemizedlist>
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  Putting this in <xref linkend="equation_dataratecycle"></xref> we get
	  <informalequation>
	    <textobject role="tex">
	      \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}} = 8 \times \left(2\times 2049 \times \left(2 \times 6 \times 2 + 2 \times 6 \times 1 + 4 \times 15 \times 1\right) + 32 \times 2049 \times 4 \times 21 \times 1\right) = 4.5635344 \times 10^{7}.
	    </textobject>
	  </informalequation>
	</para>

	<para>
	  This works out to be a data rate of 4.352 MiB per second, or roughly 15.3 GiB per hour.
	  Since <acronym>CABB</acronym> data files will automatically close when they reach
	  4.0 GiB in size, it would take approximately 15 m to fill one file (not accounting
	  for the overhead consumed by the header information).
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>How much data is produced for a pulsar-binning observation?</title>
	</info>
	
	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>data</primary><secondary>rate</secondary>
	  <tertiary>pulsar binning</tertiary></indexterm>
	  For an observation using <acronym>CABB</acronym>'s pulsar-binning mode, we have:
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		4 IFs
		(<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{IFs}}=4</textobject></inlineequation>).
		Two of these are the normal continuum IFs, each having
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      2049 channels
		      (<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{channels}}(1-2)=2049</textobject></inlineequation>),
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      4 Stokes parameters (XX, YY, XY, YX;
		      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{Stokes}}(1-2)=4</textobject></inlineequation>),
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      21 correlator products
		      (6 auto-correlation and 15 cross-correlation spectra;
		      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{products}}(1-2)=21</textobject></inlineequation>).
		      <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			  <para>
			    Each auto-correlation same-polarisation (XX, YY) spectrum has 2 bins (noise diode on and
			    noise diode off;
			    <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{bins}}(1-2,1-2,1-6)=2</textobject></inlineequation>).
			  </para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			  <para>
			    Each auto-correlation cross-polarisation (XY, YX) spectrum has 1 bin 
			    <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{bins}}(1-2,3-4,1-6)=1</textobject></inlineequation>).
			  </para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			  <para>
			    Each cross-correlation spectrum has 1 bin
			    (<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{bins}}(1-2,1-4,7-21)=1</textobject></inlineequation>).
			  </para>
			</listitem>
		      </itemizedlist>
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		The other two IFs are the pulsar-binned continuum bands, each having
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      513 channels (each of them being the average of 4 of the normal continuum channels)
		      (<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{channels}}(3-4)=513</textobject></inlineequation>),
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      4 Stokes parameters (XX, YY, XY, YX;
		      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{Stokes}}(3-4)=4</textobject></inlineequation>),
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      15 correlator products
		      (15 cross-correlation spectra;
		      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{products}}(3-4)=15</textobject></inlineequation>).
		      <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			  <para>
			    Each cross-correlation spectrum has 32 bins across the pulse period
			    (<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">N_{\mathrm{bins}}(3-4,1-4,1-15)=32</textobject></inlineequation>).
			  </para>
			</listitem>
		      </itemizedlist>
		    </para>
		  </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  Putting this in <xref linkend="equation_dataratecycle"></xref> we get
	  <informalequation>
	    <textobject role="tex">
	      \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}} = 8 \times \left(2\times 2049 \times \left(2 \times 6 \times 2 + 2 \times 6 \times 1 + 4 \times 15 \times 1\right) + 2 \times 513 \times 4 \times 15 \times 32\right) = 1.8906624 \times 10^{7}.
	    </textobject>
	  </informalequation>
	</para>

	<para>
	  This works out to be a data rate of 1.803 MiB per second, or roughly 6.339 GiB per hour.
	  Since <acronym>CABB</acronym> data files will automatically close when they reach
	  4.0 GiB in size, it would take approximately 37 m to fill one file (not accounting
	  for the overhead consumed by the header information).
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>How can I quickly determine how much data will be produced?</title>
      </info>
	
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>data</primary><secondary>rate</secondary>
	<tertiary>calculating quickly</tertiary></indexterm>
	Since all modes give you the continuum IFs, you start off with one of two base
	data rates, per cycle. For the 1 MHz modes, the base data rate is:
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}(1\mathrm{\,MHz}) = 1.573632 \times 10^{6}
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
	bytes per IF. For the 64 MHz modes, the base data rate is:
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}(64\mathrm{\,MHz}) = 2.5344 \times 10^{4}
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
	bytes per IF.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	For each pulsar-binned IF you have (only available in 1 MHz mode) you add:
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}(\mathrm{pulsar\, binning}) = 7.87968 \times 10^{6}.
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
      </para>
      
      <para>
	For each single zoom you have (i.e. zooms with a width of 1) you add:
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}(\mathrm{zoom}) = 1.376928 \times 10^{6}.
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
      </para>
      
      <para>
	For each consolidated zoom you have (i.e. zooms with a width of 2 or more) you 
	begin by adding:
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}(\mathrm{base\,czoom}) = 6.888 \times 10^{5}.
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
	Then, for each zoom band in the consolidated zoom, you add:
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}(\mathrm{extra\,czoom}) = 6.88128 \times 10^{5}.
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
	For example, if you had a consolidated zoom with a width of 5, it would produce
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}(\mathrm{czoom\,of\,width\,5}) = 6.888 \times 10^{5} + 5 \times 6.88128 \times 10^{5} = 4.12944 \times 10^{6}
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
	bytes per cycle.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	<emphasis role="bold">Example:</emphasis> If you were using the 1 MHz/64 MHz
	hybrid <acronym>CABB</acronym> configuration, and had one zoom of width 1 and
	one consolidated zoom of width 12 in the 64 MHz IF your total data usage would
	be:
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}} = \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}(1\mathrm{\,MHz}) + \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}(64\mathrm{\,MHz}) + \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}(\mathrm{zoom}) + \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}(\mathrm{base\,czoom}) + 12 \times \mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}}(\mathrm{extra\,czoom}).
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
	Doing the sum gives
	<inlineequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">\mathrm{b}_{\mathrm{cycle}} = 1.192224\times10^{7}</textobject>
	</inlineequation>
	bytes per cycle. Assuming a 10 second cycle time, this would generate 3.997 GiB per hour,
	which would give you roughly one new <acronym>CABB</acronym> data file every hour.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <info>
	<title>Do I have to do the observations myself?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>performing</secondary></indexterm>
	Users of the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> are expected to organise the execution of the observations.
	Any member of the team that proposed the experiment is eligible to observe from the Marsfield
	<acronym>SOC</acronym>, or any other researcher that the primary investigator might like to nominate.
	If the researcher has
	not previously observed with the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> and <acronym>CABB</acronym>, or has not
	observed within the past 12 months, they will have to travel to the <acronym>SOC</acronym> to be trained.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>SOC</primary><secondary>visiting</secondary></indexterm>
      </para>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>Do I need to be trained to use the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>?</title>
	</info>
	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>training</secondary></indexterm>
	  Yes. It is recommended that observers unfamiliar with the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> arrive at
	  the <acronym>SOC</acronym> at least two full weekdays before their observations, in order for them to
	  become familiar with how to use the array and who to talk to if things go wrong.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>What if we can't make it to the <acronym>SOC</acronym>?</title>
	</info>
	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>remote</secondary></indexterm>
	  If it is not possible for any of your team members to come to the <acronym>SOC</acronym> for your allocated
	  observing time, but you have visited <acronym>SOC</acronym> sometime in the 12 months prior to your
	  observations, you may be granted permission to
	  do your observations remotely (<xref linkend="running-remotely"></xref>).
	</para>

      </section>

      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>Can't someone do the observations for me?</title>
	</info>

	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>collaboration</secondary></indexterm>
	  We expect that observers are members of the team that proposed the experiment. Said another way,
	  if you require someone to do your observations, we fully expect that that person would become
	  a collaborator, and would be included on any publications derived from those observations. If this
	  is what you require, you will need to alert <acronym>ATNF</acronym> staff well ahead of your
	  scheduled time (4 weeks at least).
	</para>
      </section>
	
      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>I was planning to come, but I've just had an emergency. What can I do?</title>
	</info>
	<para>
	  We understand that plans can change on short timescales and without warning. We recommend
	  first trying to recruit another member of your team to do the observations, but should that not
	  be possible, please alert <acronym>ATNF</acronym> staff.
	</para>

	<para>
	  It may be possible to do a short-notice scheduling swap with another project, leaving you to
	  do your observations at a later date. If this is not possible, we may be able to find a
	  replacement observer, with the understanding that whomever does the observing will become
	  a collaborator on the experiment, and will receive due credit on any publications derived from
	  the observations.
	</para>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section id="running-remotely">
      <info>
	<title>Can I do my observations from my home institution?</title>
      </info>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>remote</secondary></indexterm>
	Remote observing is available for experienced <acronym>ATCA</acronym> observers. We will consider
	granting a request for remote observations if the observer:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Has observed from the <acronym>SOC</acronym> at least once in the 12 months prior
	      to the date of the proposed remote observations, or
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Usually observes more than 3 times per semester, or on at least 10 days per semester,
	      and has observed from the <acronym>SOC</acronym> at least once in the 18 months prior
	      to the date of the proposed remote observations.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
	Applications to do a remote observation must be made <emphasis role="bold">at least 2 weeks before the
	observations</emphasis>. This is so observatory staff can check for possible network
	disruptions during your observations, and advise you if remote observing will not be possible.
	The later you leave your remote observing application, the less time you will have
	to change your plans should your request for remote observations be refused.
      </para>

      <para>
	Permission to do your observations remotely is given at the discretion of science operations staff,
	and you should not presume that permission will be forthcoming. Should permission be refused and
	you are not able to come to the observatory, you may need to find a local collaborator to do the
	observations for you. <!-- Your observing &#x201C;friend&#x201D;
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>friend</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>friend</secondary></indexterm>
	will not generally be available to do your observations. -->
	The duty astronomer is under no obligation to observe for your project if you are unable to.
      </para>

      <para>
	To apply to make an observation remotely, use the &#x201C;Booking&#x201D; tab on the
	<ulink url="https://ca-ops.atnf.csiro.au/jPORTAL/"><acronym>ATCA</acronym> observing PORTAL</ulink>,
	which will look something like <xref linkend="portal-booking-tab"></xref>.
	First, fill out the &#x201C;Booking details&#x201D; form (which is revealed by clicking on that
	button), and hit the &#x201C;Book&#x201D; button in the &#x201C;Status&#x201D; column.
      </para>

      <para>
	<figure id="portal-booking-tab">
	  <title>The &#x201C;Booking&#x201D; tab on the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> observing PORTAL.</title>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/new-portal-booking-tab.png" format="PNG">
	      </imagedata>
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>
      </para>

      <para>
	  Remote observers must
	  have their own <acronym>ATNF</acronym> UNIX account and remember their password for this account.
	  The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> website has pages describing
	  <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/remote_conditions.html">current remote observing conditions</ulink>
	  and
	  <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/rem_obs.html">instructions for observing remotely</ulink>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>remote</secondary>
	<tertiary>requirements</tertiary></indexterm>
	To be sure of a successful remote observing session, all observers are required to test their
	remote observing setup at least a week before their observations.
      </para>

      <para>
	At a minimum, you will require the following for remote observing:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A computer with SSH software, capable of running a VNC viewer, on a high bandwidth connection,
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A telephone near to the computer, that can make calls to, and accept calls from the observatory.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	Remote observations will be easier if you also have:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Two or more monitors attached to their computer,
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A computer with X-Windows software,
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A hands-free speakerphone or headset.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>remote</secondary>
	<tertiary>testing</tertiary></indexterm>
	To test your setup, you should contact the duty astronomer and ask to be allowed
	to login and perform the test. If the test will not disturb current observations, you  should follow
	the instructions on remote observing found in Chapter 3
	to ensure that you can monitor and control all the required VNC sessions. If problems
	are encountered here, and the duty astronomer can't help you resolve them,
	contact the observatory staff with a description of the problems and ask for advice.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="rapid-response-mode">
    <info>
      <title>Rapid Response Mode</title>
    </info>
    <para>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>rapid response</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>NAPA</primary><secondary>rapid response</secondary><see>rapid response</see></indexterm>
      For the 2017APR semester, a rapid response mode was introduced. This is designed to allow the
      <acronym>ATCA</acronym> to respond almost instantly to a request for a <acronym>NAPA</acronym> over-ride.
      This section describes how to use this mode.
    </para>
    <section>
      <info>
	<title>Who can use the rapid response mode?</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> rapid response mode is only available to proposers who have submitted a
	<acronym>NAPA</acronym> proposal for the current semester. If you are interested in being granted
	permission to use the rapid response mode for your <acronym>NAPA</acronym> proposal, please talk
	to Jamie Stevens (<email>Jamie.Stevens@csiro.au</email>).
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
	<title>How does the rapid response mode work?</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	The rapid response mode is designed to take a user-made schedule, and get it onto the telescope
	as soon as possible after the request has been made. Getting the telescope to stop one schedule
	and start another is very easy; determining when "as soon as possible" actually starts is the
	tricky part. The rest of this section describes the process which takes place to perform an
	over-ride observation.
      </para>
      <para>
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      You submit a <acronym>NAPA</acronym> science case to the <acronym>ATNF</acronym>
	      <acronym>TAC</acronym>, which gives you a ranking grade for the semester.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      You ask for, and are supplied with an authorisation token which will allow you to
	      request an over-ride through the rapid response service.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      At some point during the semester, you decide to trigger your <acronym>NAPA</acronym> proposal.
	      You (or more likely your software) creates a <acronym>CABB</acronym> schedule that
	      observes both the target of interest and a nearby phase calibrator.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      You submit this schedule to the ATCA rapid response web service.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The service checks that you are an authorised user, and rejects the request if not.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The minimum amount of time that you have requested is still available to be
		    scheduled for your project, considering the amount of time you requested from
		    the TAC, and the amount of time you have used before this request. If you do
		    not have sufficient time, the request is rejected.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    A start time is determined where
		    <itemizedlist>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  the source is above the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> lower elevation limit,
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  the project that must be over-ridden has a lower grade than the
			  <acronym>NAPA</acronym>,
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  and that the schedule can be executed for at least the minimum required
			  amount of time while still meeting the above conditions.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		    The search for this suitable start time is limited to either 100 hours after the
		    request submission, or to a user-specified duration, if it is less than 100 hours.
		    The 100 hour limit is designed to allow for an automated response even for long
		    weekends where the proposers may not be available for a manual over-ride, while
		    the user-specified duration can indicate that an observation that can't be made
		    within some time frame would no longer be scientifically interesting.
		  </para>
		  <para>
		    If a suitable start time cannot be found, the request is rejected.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    An estimate is made of when the flux-density and bandpass calibrators should
		    be observed, given the start time. The schedule is altered to insert those scans.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    If the request has not been rejected by this point, the request is approved.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      At the start time determined in the previous step, several additional checks
	      are made.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    All scheduled scans will be above the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> lower elevation
		    limit at their expected start time, for at least the minimum required time.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The project currently being observed has a grade that is lower than the grade
		    of the <acronym>NAPA</acronym>.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The array is not stowed due to weather conditions.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    <acronym>CABB</acronym> is configured in either 1 MHz continuum mode, or
		    1 MHz zooms mode.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </orderedlist>
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      If any of these conditions is not met, then the start time of the project is delayed
	      from between 5 seconds and 10 minutes, at which point each of the checks are made again.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      When all checks from the previous step are satisfied, a final set of schedule alterations
	      are made.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The schedule is shortened if necessary, to fit in the time available at this start
		    time. The amount of time scheduled will always at least the minimum required.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    If the user has requested to use the same frequency configuration as the project
		    being over-ridden, and
		    <orderedlist>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  the band currently being observed (or that was last observed) is not 7mm
			  or 3mm,
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  the array is not currently split between two bands,
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  and the project that is currently being observed (or that was last observed)
			  is not C999,
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </orderedlist>
		    then the over-ride schedule is altered to use the same frequency configuration
		    as is currently listed. Otherwise, the frequency configuration is left as specified
		    in the request.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    If the slew from the current position to the first scan of the schedule is less
		    than 20 seconds, and the delays need to be reset because the user-specified
		    frequencies are being used instead of the currently configured frequencies,
		    an additional &#x201C;Normal&#x201D; scan of 40 seconds is inserted at the
		    beginning of the schedule. This scan is named &#x201C;setup&#x201D; so it can
		    easily be identified and discarded during later data reduction.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    The first scan in the schedule is altered, in the following ways.
		    <itemizedlist>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  The command <literal>focus default</literal> is added, to ensure the focus
			  is set correctly.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  If the scheduled frequencies are not the same as those that were observed
			  before the over-ride, the command <literal>corr reset delays</literal> is
			  added, and the tv-channels are set to be 1020 to 1022 in each
			  <acronym>IF</acronym>.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The altered schedule is copied into the right place, <command>caobs</command> detects
	      this new schedule file and immediately begins executing it. Over-ride schedules are
	      started at scan 1, and continue through until the last scan, and will not loop.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      While the schedule is being executed, an automatic monitoring system will watch that
	      the schedule is progressing, and will attempt to automatically restart the schedule
	      in the event that it gets stopped.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
	<title>Can I over-ride any scheduled block?</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	All scheduled slots that have a project code starting with &#x201C;C&#x201D; can be over-ridden
	by the rapid response mode, provided that your <acronym>TAC</acronym> score is sufficiently
	high and <acronym>CABB</acronym> is in the correct mode.
      </para>
      <para>
	Blocks of time scheduled for reconfigures, maintenance and VLBI cannot be over-ridden.
      </para>
      <para>
	In the 2017APR semester, it is not possible to over-ride time scheduled for legacy projects,
	but this will change in the 2017OCT semester, so that any over-ride project that has a score
	higher than or equal to the lowest score given to a scheduled project may over-ride successfully.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
	<title>How can I make a schedule file automatically?</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	As part of the project to develop this rapid response mode, a library for creating and
	manipulating <acronym>CABB</acronym> schedules was developed. It can be found
	<ulink url="https://github.com/ste616/cabb-schedule-api">on GitHub</ulink>, and is
	free for use.
      </para>
      <para>
	Because many of the existing libraries that astronomers use to deal with transient
	event streams are written in Python, the choice was made to focus first on providing
	a Python library for schedule manipulation. This library is targetted toward Python
	2.7.
      </para>
      <para>
	Documentation on how to use the library in your own code is part of the GitHub repository.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
	<title>What is this authorisation token that I need?</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	To ensure that only those projects that have been pre-approved can perform over-rides on
	the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>, any request for over-ride time needs to be accompanied by
	a valid authorisation token. This can only be obtained by emailing
	<email>Jamie.Stevens@csiro.au</email>.
      </para>
      <para>
	There are two types of authorisation token available. The first is a test token, which
	allows you to submit a request, and go through the entire process of the over-ride, but
	not actually get time on the telescope. This is designed to be used while you are trying
	to develop and perfect your automated trigger routines. You may issue as many requests
	as you like with a test token.
      </para>
      <para>
	The second token will allow your request to allocate time on the telescope. This type of
	token will not be issued until you have demonstrated that your code can properly submit
	a test request. You will need to work with Jamie Stevens during this process.
      </para>
      <para>
	Authorisation tokens are valid only for a specific project and semester, and will be
	rejected if used outside those bounds.
      </para>
      <para>
	The authorisation token itself is a
	<ulink url="https://jwt.io/introduction"><acronym>JSON</acronym> Web Token</ulink>.
	You will be supplied with a normal <acronym>ASCII</acronym> file that will need to be
	passed back to the service whenever you make a request.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
	<title>But how do I make a request?</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	All requests to trigger an over-ride observation are submitted through a web service.
	The exact format of the request won't be documented here, and we suggest that you use
	the Python code we provide when you are building your trigger response software.
      </para>
      <para>
	The library which makes it easy to submit over-ride requests can be found
	<ulink url="https://github.com/ste616/atca-rapid-response-api">on GitHub</ulink>, along
	with documentation and examples.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <info>
	<title>How can I find out what the service is doing?</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	If your request is unable to be scheduled given the bounds you provided, you will receive
	your rejection in the response from the web service.
      </para>
      <para>
	If the web service doesn't reject your request, your schedule will enter the queue to be
	executed. At this point, two emails will be sent to this effect. As with all emails sent by
	the rapid response service, they will be from Jamie.Stevens@csiro.au and will go to all
	the members of the NAPA team (as specified on its OPAL coversheet), along with all the
	members of each project that will need to be displaced.
      </para>
      <para>
	The first email will have the subject &#x201C;ATCA rapid response mode triggered for Cxxxx
	&#x201D;, where of course the real NAPA project code will be specified instead of &#x201C;
	Cxxxx&#x201D;. The second email will have the subject &#x201C;Your ATCA rapid response
	over-ride request has been queued for execution.&#x201D;.
      </para>
      <para>
	The first email will look something like this.
	<blockquote>
	  <para>
	    The ATCA rapid response mode was requested by the NAPA project C008 at UTC 2017-03-31 04:14:14.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This over-ride has been scheduled to begin at UTC 2017-03-31 04:14:14 and end at approximately UTC 2017-03-31 04:27:06.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This over-ride has been assigned the ID xaap6yuacy10ltg9lc3g.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    This will displace time from the project C007.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    The observations will be automatically started without any user intervention. While the observations are running, please do not intervene unless advised to by observatory staff.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    You will receive another email when the observations have started, and another when the over-ride observations have ended. Messages to the same effect will also appear in the ATCA Portal chat.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Please send any feedback about this system by replying to this email.
	  </para>
	</blockquote>
      </para>
      <para>
	As you can see, the time of the request, and the expected start and end times are all listed, along
	with the unique ID assigned to the over-ride, and a list of all the projects that will be displaced.
      </para>
      <para>
	The next email will look similar to the following.
	<blockquote>
	  <para>
	    This email is from the ATCA rapid response system.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    What follows is a log of the progress of your requested over-ride experiment.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Project code: C008
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Over-ride ID: xaap6yuacy10ltg9lc3g
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    2017-03-31_04:14:14: Your experiment has been placed in the queue, and should start at 2017/3/31 04:14:14. You will receive another email at that time.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    If you have any concerns about this experiment, please reply to this email.
	  </para>
	</blockquote>
      </para>
      <para>
	This second email introduces the time-stamped log of the progress of the over-ride. All subsequent
	email communication will contain this log, as it was when the email was sent. The log will have
	entries for all the important actions made by the rapid response service, and entries that will be
	useful for later data reduction.
      </para>
      <para>
	At the start time, the service will either start or delay the schedule, and in either case an email
	will be sent. If the schedule is started, the email will have the subject &#x201C;An ATCA rapid
	response over-ride is now being observed&#x201D;, while if the schedule is delayed the subject will
	be &#x201C;Your ATCA rapid response over-ride request has been delayed&#x201D;; the reasons for the
	delay will be included in the log. If the schedule is started, the name of the schedule will be given
	in the email, and you may load it in the CABB web scheduler to see how the service has altered it.
      </para>
      <para>
	No emails will be sent while the schedule is running, except if the service encounters a problem.
	In that case, you will get an email with the subject &#x201C;There has been a problem while
	executing your ATCA rapid response over-ride&#x201D;.
      </para>
      <para>
	When the schedule finishes, the service will send out one final email, with the subject
	&#x201C;ATCA rapid response over-ride is now complete&#x201D;. This email contains the full
	log, which will include the name of the RPFITS files that contain the data.
      </para>
      <para>
	If for some reason the service is unable to perform the scheduled over-ride (for example, if the
	antennas are weather stowed for an extended period of time), then the schedule might expire and
	be removed from the queue. If this happens you will get an email with the subject
	&#x201C;Your ATCA rapid response over-ride request has expired&#x201D;.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="OverrideScheduleStrategy">
      <info>
	<title>What is the recommended strategy for a rapid response schedule?</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	The schedule you make depends on what type of observation you are trying to perform. What follows
	are some general recommendations for rapid response schedules.
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis role="bold">Select the frequencies that will give you the best science, rather
	      than ask for the frequency configuration that is being used when the telescope is over-ridden.
	      </emphasis>
	      There is no actual need to have a perfectly calibrated array when doing an observation with
	      the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>. As long as the delays can be measured while observing a strong
	      calibrator, you will be able to correct for those delays in <application>Miriad</application>.
	      If you specify the frequencies you want, the service will ensure that the delays are set back
	      to their defaults at the start of your observation, which will always produce a dataset that
	      can be successfully calibrated.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      To ensure that the observations can be monitored effectively with default delays, the
	      tvchannel range is limited to 1020 - 1022 in each <acronym>IF</acronym>. This 3 MHz of
	      bandwidth near the band centre is sufficient to measure the system temperature and to show
	      the calibrator's flux density in <application>vis</application>. You will not need to
	      specify this when creating the schedule, as the service will automatically do this for you.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis role="bold">If measuring very early prompt emission is important to your
	      science, ensure that you visit the target source first, before your first scan on the
	      gain calibrator.</emphasis>
	      Observing your target for a few minutes before going to the gain calibrator should not
	      be a problem, as the gains can be reliably extrapolated at cm wavelengths. Also, if you are
	      observing in the 16cm band, there is a very good chance you will have a source in your field
	      that is bright enough to allow for self-calibration.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis role="bold">Keep your scans short so the service can easily cut it to fit the
	      earliest available slot.</emphasis>
	      If authorised to do so, the service can automatically shorten the schedule you provide in
	      order to fit it into the earliest possible available slot; how it does this is described in
	      <xref linkend="ScheduleShortening"></xref>. If you keep your scans short (ie. don't have
	      hour long scans between visits to your calibrator) then the shortener will act much more
	      reliably.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      <emphasis role="bold">Do not include a flux density calibrator in your schedule.</emphasis>
	      The service will automatically add the appropriate flux density calibrator to your schedule,
	      depending on frequency and sidereal time.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="ScheduleShortening">
      <info>
	<title>How does the service shorten my schedule?</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	The service shortens a schedule in four stages.
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The hard end time of the available slot is determined. This may be because the source has
	      set, or a project has started with a score higher than that of your project. All scans that
	      end after that hard end time are immediately deleted from the schedule, except if it is the
	      flux density calibrator scan that the service added.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      As mentioned in <xref linkend="OverrideScheduleStrategy"></xref>, this step can cause problems
	      if your scans are too long. Consider a scenario where the scan that ends after the hard end time
	      is scheduled to run for 1 hour. Even if the hard end time is only 10 minutes from the scheduled
	      end of this scan, the entire scan is cut, and you have lost a potential 50 minutes of observing
	      time.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If the schedule is still too long at this point, all scans on the nominated calibration source
	      may be shortened to have a dwell length of 1 minute. This is done from the first scan and
	      continues until all the calibrator scans have been shortened, or the schedule now finishes before
	      the hard end time.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If the schedule is still too long at this point, then the scan on the flux density calibrator
	      is shortened by 1 minute.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If the schedule is still too long at this point, then the source scans are shortened.
	      The service calculates the amount of time that needs to be cut for the schedule to fit in
	      the slot, and then subtracts as much time as possible from the last remaining source scan.
	      If the last remaining source scan is longer than the cut time, then the scan survives,
	      otherwise it, and the following calibrator scan, are removed entirely. This process repeats
	      until the schedule finishes before the hard end time.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
	If at the end of this process, the schedule length falls below the specified minimum useful
	time required, the start time will be delayed and the schedule restored to its original
	specification.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <info>
      <title>Pre-observation Checklist</title>
    </info>
    <para>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>checklist</primary><secondary>pre-observation</secondary></indexterm>
      Ready to observe? Check that all the following tasks have been done:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Determined sources to use for:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Delay calibrator
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Flux density calibrator
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Bandpass calibrator
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Gain calibrator(s)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Pointing calibrator(s) (only if doing reference pointing)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Polarisation calibrator(s) (only if doing polarisation studies)
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Checked that all sources are visible during allocated time.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Contacted your observing friend if assistance is required to prepare your schedules.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Prepared a schedule file using the <acronym>CABB</acronym> web scheduler for:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Array setup
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Calibration
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Science observations
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Used the sensitivity calculator to make sure that integration time on
	  calibrators is sufficient.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Ensured that turret movements are limited to once every 15 minutes or
	  longer.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Generated a mosaic pointing file (only if doing mosaic observations),
	  and copied it to the appropriate place on <hardware>xbones</hardware>.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Generated an ephemeris for the solar system object (only if doing
	  solar system observations), and copied it to the appropriate place on
	  <hardware>xbones</hardware>.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Calculated how much data the observations will generate, and obtained
	  enough disk space to accommodate this.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Checked for possible problems, and made contingency plans for:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Antenna shadowing
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Wrong time range for flux density calibrator observations
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Bad weather forecast during observations
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Checked
	  <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/CurrentIssues.html">current issues page</ulink>
	  for issues that may cause problems with the observations.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Checked that remote observations are permitted (only if remotely observing).
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Contacted observatory staff and duty astronomer if assistance will be
	  required during observations.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

</chapter>
