<chapter id="The-Australia-Telescope-Compact-Array">
  <info>
    <title>The Australia Telescope Compact Array</title>
    <date>$Date: 2018-03-15 14:22:18 +1100 (Thu, 15 Mar 2018) $</date>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.5</revnumber>
	<date>2018 Mar 15</date>
	<authorinitials>jbs</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Clarified the rules and procedures around NAPA and ToO requests, and how time
	is allocated to them.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.4</revnumber>
	<date>2016 Sep 14</date>
	<authorinitials>jbs</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Added discussion of the 4cm and 15mm RFI we now know about, and change the 15mm
	recommended continuum frequencies. Update the upcoming configurations table.</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.3</revnumber>
	<date>2015 Nov 20</date>
	<authorinitials>jbs</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Added discussion of the 16cm RFI environment, RFI monitor and mid-week RFI</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.2</revnumber>
	<date>2015 Oct 20</date>
	<authorinitials>jbs</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Updated information about observing at the SOC</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
	<date>2014 May 30</date>
	<authorinitials>jbs</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Revised out-of-date tables and figures</revremark>
      </revision>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
	<date>2014 Mar 20</date>
	<authorinitials>jbs</authorinitials>
	<revremark>Initial Docbook revision</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </info>
  <para>
    This chapter gives an overview of the <firstterm>Australia Telescope Compact Array</firstterm>
    (<acronym>ATCA</acronym>)
    <indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATCA</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Compact Array</primary><secondary>Australia Telescope</secondary>
    <see>ATCA</see></indexterm>
    and provides the information needed to prepare an observing proposal.
    As such, this chapter supercedes the <firstterm>Guide to Observations</firstterm> that was
    provided in the past (and which contained a lot of overlap with the previous
    <firstterm>Users Guide</firstterm>). The old <firstterm>Users Guide</firstterm> is still available and is
    recommended for those reducing
    pre-<acronym>CABB</acronym> data (i.e., observations before April 2009).
    <indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>guide to</secondary></indexterm>
    </para>
    <para>
    The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> consists of six 22-m radio antennas which can be configured
    with antenna spacings of up to 6km, located
    at the Paul Wild Observatory near Narrabri,
    <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Narrabri</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Wild, Paul</primary></indexterm>
    some 550 km northwest of Sydney.  It is one of the telescopes operated
    by the Australia Telescope National Facility (<acronym>ATNF</acronym>).
  </para>
  
  <section id="The-Australia-Telescope-National-Facility">
    <info>
      <title>The Australia Telescope National Facility</title>
    </info>
    <para>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>National Facility</primary><secondary>Australia Telescope</secondary><see>ATNF</see></indexterm>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATNF</primary></indexterm>
      The <acronym>ATNF</acronym> is managed as a National Facility by the Commonwealth
      Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (<acronym>CSIRO</acronym>). Formerly part
      of the <acronym>CSIRO</acronym> Division of Radiophysics, it became a separate division in
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Radiophysics</primary><secondary>Division of</secondary><see>ATNF</see></indexterm>
      January 1989.  The <acronym>ATNF</acronym> became a National Facility in April 1990.
      In December 2009,
      <acronym>ATNF</acronym> became part of a new Division, <acronym>CSIRO</acronym> Astronomy and Space Science (CASS),
      together with NASA Operations
      (including the Canberra Deep Space Communication Complex),
      and <acronym>CSIRO</acronym> Space Sciences and Technology.
      The Australia Telescope continues as a National Facility, providing world-class
      observing facilities for astronomers at Australian and overseas
      institutions.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <acronym>ATNF</acronym> employs about 185 staff, including about 40 astronomers, with
      the majority of staff located at its headquarters in Marsfield, a suburb
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Marsfield</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Epping</primary><see>Marsfield</see></indexterm>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATNF</primary><secondary>headquarters</secondary></indexterm>
      of Sydney (although Marsfield is sometimes referred to as Epping, a
      larger neighbouring suburb).  The site was shared with the AAO 
      (the Australian Astronomical Observatory, or before 2010, 
      the Anglo-Australian Observatory) until 2012, when the AAO relocated
      to the nearby suburb of North Ryde.
    </para>
    <para>Besides the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>, the <acronym>ATNF</acronym> operates the 64-m radio telescope at
      the Parkes Observatory
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Parkes</primary></indexterm>
      (300 km west of Sydney) and a 22-m antenna at Mopra,
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Mopra</primary></indexterm>
      120 km south of the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>.  In addition, the <acronym>ATNF</acronym> negotiates time with the
      <acronym>CSIRO</acronym>-administered 70-m and 34-m antennas at the Tidbinbilla Deep Space
      Tracking station outside Canberra.  The <acronym>ATNF</acronym> telescopes are used
      together, in conjunction with the University of Tasmania telescopes at
      Hobart and Ceduna, as part of the Long Baseline Array for Very Long
      Baseline Interferometry (<acronym>VLBI</acronym>) observations.
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Tidbinbilla</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Long Baseline Array</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>VLBI</primary></indexterm>
      The <acronym>ATNF</acronym> is
      currently structured into four themes: Operations, Astrophysics,
      Technologies, and <acronym>ASKAP</acronym>.
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>ASKAP</primary></indexterm>
      <acronym>ASKAP</acronym> (the Australian SKA Pathfinder), is a telescope being
      constructed by <acronym>ATNF</acronym> in
      Western Australia, and will be an array of thirty-six wide-field 12m antennas
      operating in the 0.7&#x2013;1.8 GHz range. Commissioning of the first antennas is currently underway.  More details are available at
      <ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/projects/askap/">the <acronym>ASKAP</acronym> project website.</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
      A biannual newsletter is produced by the
      <acronym>ATNF</acronym> which includes recent news items, scientific articles and time
      assignment information. All the newsletters are 
      <ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/news/newsletter/">archived on the web</ulink>, as are the
      <ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/the_atnf/annual_reports/"><firstterm>ATNF Annual Reports</firstterm></ulink>.
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATNF</primary><secondary>annual report</secondary></indexterm>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="Overview-of-the-ATCA">
    <info>
      <title>Overview of the <acronym>ATCA</acronym></title>
    </info>
    <para>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATCA</primary><secondary>overview</secondary></indexterm>
      The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> is an array of six 22m diameter antennas located
      237m above sea level at latitude
      -30&#x00B0; 18&#x2032; 46.385&#x2033; south, longitude
      149&#x00B0; 33&#x2032; 00.500&#x2033; east.
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATCA</primary><secondary>longitude &amp; latitude</secondary></indexterm>
      The array has a 3km east-west track with a 214m northern
      spur.  Five antennas can be moved along these tracks, with the sixth
      antenna at a fixed position 3km to the west of the east-west track.  The
      longest possible baseline is, therefore, 6km.
      The array can be used for observations in five wavelength bands
      between 27cm and (with five antennas only) 3mm,
      between frequencies of approximately 1.1GHz and 105GHz.
    </para>
    
    <section id="Array-configurations">
      <info>
	<title>Array configurations</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>array</primary><secondary>configurations</secondary></indexterm>
	The location of six
	antennas at six stations is called an
	<firstterm>array configuration</firstterm>, or often, simply a <firstterm>configuration</firstterm>.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATCA</primary><secondary>configurations</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>configurations</primary></indexterm>
	The westernmost antenna, CA06, is fixed in position.
	The other five antennas can be positioned at any of 44 fixed stations.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>station</primary><secondary>posts</secondary></indexterm>
	The station posts provide mains power to the antennas and network connections
	that allow commands from the control building to be sent to the antenna, and monitor data
	to be received from the antenna. The posts also have high-speed
	optical links that allow data from the antenna
	to be transferred to the control building. The smallest baseline
	increment available is 15.306m, and the shortest physical baseline is
	30.612m.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>baselines</primary><see>ATCA</see></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATCA</primary><secondary>baselines</secondary></indexterm>
	Five of the six <acronym>ATCA</acronym> antennas are shown in <xref linkend="atcatrack"></xref>.
      </para>

      <para>
	A standard set of 17 configurations has been defined, and a subset of these
	is offered for each semester. These configurations have been designed to give
	optimum, minimum-redundancy coverage after a 12 hour observing period.
	Four configuration sets for the principal arrays (750m, 1.5km and
	6km) are offered over several semesters (see <xref linkend="ATCA-Array-Configurations"></xref>
	for details of these sets).
	Your choice of configuration depends on the
	extent, brightness and complexity of your source (see below).
      </para>

      <para>
	The Australia Telescope Compact Array is an earth-rotation aperture synthesis
	radio interferometer. Earth-rotation aperture synthesis
	was first used in the 1950s for radio observations of the sun.
	The technique is comprehensively explained, with a historical perspective, in
	<wordasword>Interferometry and Synthesis in Radio Astronomy</wordasword> by
	Thompson, Moran &amp; Swenson (Wiley, 1st edition 1986, 2nd edition 2001).
	Essentially, the array of antennas is comprised of a number of two-element
	interferometers.
	The visibility (i.e., the fraction of the signal common to both
	antennas of a pair) is derived by multiplying the (suitably delayed)
	signals together. By combining the correlated signals obtained over a long
	period of time and with a large range of spacings between antennas, the
	Compact Array measures the spatial coherence function:
      </para>

      <para>
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{V} = \int \mathrm{I}_{\nu}(\mathbf{s}) e^{2\pi i \mathbf{s}\cdot(\mathbf{r_{1}} - \mathbf{r_{2})}} d\Omega
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
	where <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{I}_{\nu}(\mathbf{s})</textobject></inlineequation>
	is the two dimensional intensity
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>coherence function</primary><secondary>spatial</secondary></indexterm>
	distribution on the sky,
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathbf{s}</textobject></inlineequation>
	is the unit vector in the direction
	of the celestial source,
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">(\mathbf{r_{1}} - \mathbf{r_{2}})</textobject></inlineequation>
	is the separation vector between antennas 1 and 2 and
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">d\Omega</textobject></inlineequation>
	indicates integration over the sphere (or, in practice, solid angle of the antenna beam).
      </para>

      <para>
	The van Cittert&#x2013;Zernike theorem states that the Fourier
	transformation of the spatial coherence function yields the source
	brightness distribution, i.e., the Fourier Transform of the
	visibilities produces an image of a radio source. The image is formed
	with the same angular resolution 
	as for observations with a single antenna with a diameter equal to the
	largest spacing, however it will be less sensitive due to the interferometer's
	smaller collecting area.
      </para>

      <para>
	By plotting the tracks that the baseline vectors trace out (from the source's perspective)
	as the Earth rotates, astronomers can gauge how good the telescope will be at
	imaging the source and resolving components in the field of view.
	This plot is referred to as the
	(u,v)-coverage as, by convention, the two orthogonal axes of the
	plot are u and v.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>uv-coverage</primary></indexterm>
	These variables have units of the observing wavelength.
	The (u,v)-coverage shows where on the Fourier plane the image has been
	sampled.
      </para>

      <para>
	To obtain the fullest (u,v) coverage with the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> would require
	observations with multiple different configurations, and for twelve hours with
	each configuration. However, almost any program can be successfully carried out
	with less than complete (u,v) coverage, and the individual configurations
	are chosen so as to optimise single configuration imaging
	characteristics. Sophisticated off-line image processing techniques
	minimise the effect of missing (u,v) coverage and allow reasonable
	images to be made with one configuration. For most programs, one to
	four configurations provide the best compromise between dynamic range,
	(u,v) coverage and time.
      </para>

      <para>
	The smallest synthesized beamwidths in Right Ascension for each observing
	wavelength are shown in <xref linkend="table_sensitivity"></xref>, but bear
	in mind that, for east-west arrays, the beamwidth in Declination is greater by
	a factor cosec(Dec). At high angular resolution, the telescope is only
	useful for observing southern objects.  North of Declination
	-24&#x00B0;, full (u,v)-coverage is unobtainable;
	near Declination zero the beam is highly elongated north-south; and
	north of Declination +48&#x00B0; sources are below the
	telescope's +12&#x00B0; elevation limit and are inaccessible.
	For lower angular resolution,
	the north-south and hybrid arrays improve the (u,v)-coverage
	for equatorial sources, but only up to a maximum north-south baseline
	of 214m.
      </para>
      <figure id="atcatrack">
        <title>Five of the six <acronym>ATCA</acronym> antennas in the H75 array.</title>
        <mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="figures/hybridarray.jpg" format="JPG" scalefit="1">
	    </imagedata>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
	The rest of this chapter outlines the structure and operation of the
	<acronym>ATCA</acronym>. The path of the radio signal is traced through the system from
	the dish to the final data recording. This section is designed to
	help you understand how the Compact Array operates and provide all the
	information required to design an appropriate experiment. Detailed
	technical information about the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> can be found in the <wordasword>Journal of
	  Electrical and Electronics Engineering, Australia</wordasword>, Special Issue, Vol.
	12, No. 2, June 1992, a copy of which is available in the control room
	at the Narrabri Observatory.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Design-and-Operation-of-the-ATCA">
      <info>
	<title>Design and Operation of the <acronym>ATCA</acronym></title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>signal</primary><secondary>path</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>antenna</primary><secondary>optics</secondary></indexterm>
	The antennas have a Cassegrain design, i.e., the receivers are located
	in a turret that protrudes through the main reflector
	surface &#x2014; see <xref linkend="atcatrack"></xref>.  The antennas have an altitude-azimuth
	mount with wrap limits as shown in the figure.  The shaped (i.e.,
	non-parabolic) dish and subreflector surfaces are designed to maximise
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>antenna</primary><secondary>surface</secondary></indexterm>
	the gain to antenna noise ratio.  The reflecting surface of antennas
	1&#x2013;5 are solid panels that allow observations up to 116 GHz. This is
	also true of the inner 15.3m of antenna 6. The outer reflecting
	surface of antenna 6 is made of perforated panels which 
permit observations at frequencies up to 50 GHz.
      </para>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>subreflector</primary></indexterm>
	The subreflector mounted near the prime focus has a specially designed
	shape, differing slightly from the hyperbolic secondary of standard
	Cassegrain optics.  The feedhorns are mounted on
	the optic axis &#x2014; this allows polarisation measurements to
	be made, with very low (
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\sim 1\%</textobject></inlineequation>)
	instrumental polarisation. Subreflector focus is presently chosen to best suit 3mm
	observations and is adjusted for some antennas for the 7mm and 4cm bands.
	This means that the subreflectors positions may be slightly less than
	ideal for longer wavelengths. If you need better focus settings,
	discuss your requirements with local staff.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>antenna</primary><secondary>focus</secondary></indexterm>
	A major feature of the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> is its wide bandwidth operation. The
	feedhorns and front-end electronics operate over a very large range of
	frequencies, thus allowing (u,v) coverage to be increased by
	multi-frequency synthesis and dual frequency observations. The
	feedhorns are compact, with a corrugated interior
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>feedhorns</primary></indexterm>
	surface and are designed for maximum frequency coverage, low noise,
	low spillover, low reflection and low cross-polarisation sidelobe
	levels. The feedhorns allow two simultaneous orthogonal linear
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary><secondary>orthogonal</secondary></indexterm>
	polarisations to be measured (at frequencies almost an octave apart),
	and have a main lobe with near-constant, symmetrical beamwidth
	(James, G.L., 1984, <wordasword>IEEE Trans. Antennas Propagat.</wordasword>
	<emphasis role="bold">AP&#x2013;22</emphasis>,
	pp 1134&#x2013;1138;
	Thomas, B.M., James, G.L., Greene, K.J., 1986, <wordasword>IEEE Trans.
	  Antennas Propagat.</wordasword> <emphasis role="bold">AP-34</emphasis>, pp 750&#x2013;757).
      </para>
      <para>
	The frequencies at which the Australia Telescope operates are listed in
	<xref linkend="table_sensitivity"></xref> see also section
	<xref linkend="Available-Frequency-Range"></xref>.
      </para>
      <para>
	Each range of frequencies is referred to as a
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>band</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>band</primary><secondary>letter codes</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>millimetre</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>centimetre</secondary></indexterm>
	<firstterm>band</firstterm>.  Bands are referred to by the wavelength of the approximate centre
	of the band or (especially at higher frequencies) by the frequency (and
	sometimes by the letter-codes shown over the columns of <xref linkend="table_sensitivity"></xref>.
	There are presently five feedhorns mounted on each antenna (four on
	antenna 6): a large (2m high) feed-horn that operates in the
	16cm band, and a somewhat smaller (50cm high) 4cm band
	feedhorn and three (several cm high) feedhorns mounted on the same dewar
	for the 15mm, 7mm and 3mm wavelengths.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>feedhorns</primary></indexterm>
	The feedhorns and the receivers are mounted on a rotating turret. The
	rotating turret design ensures that all feedhorns, when brought on-axis,
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>turret</primary></indexterm>
	are aligned with the
	optic axis of the antenna, allowing a wide field of view and
	dual-polarisation observations. The turrets are rotated automatically
	in accordance with the frequencies selected by the observing file.
	Rotating the turret orients the desired feed-horn and also ensures
	that the subsequent electronics suit the frequency at which you are
	observing.
	Changing the observing band to or
	from 7mm requires first rotating the turret to the 15mm position, and
	then translating the whole mm dewar to bring the 7mm feed on axis. The
	latter stage takes 2~3 minutes, and so changes to or from 7mm are
	much slower than any other band change.
      </para>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>receiver</primary></indexterm>
	Both the 16cm and 4cm band feedhorns are fitted with wide-bandwidth
	receivers that covers the horn's entire usable frequency range. All receivers run
	continuously and use cooled HEMT (high electron mobility transistor) and FET (field effect transistor)
	amplifiers that provide wide bandwidths and total system temperatures
	between 20K to 65K, depending on frequency.
      </para>
      <para>
	The signals collected by the feedhorns are fed to the receiver systems
	for amplification and conversion to standard intermediate
	frequencies. During observations each antenna provides four
	independent intermediate frequency (IF) outputs (two frequency bands,
	two polarisations). These channels allow simultaneous observations of
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>frequency</primary><secondary>intermediate</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary></indexterm>
	both polarisations at the two available frequencies in either
	dual-receiver system. The frequencies can be anywhere in the range
	covered by the selected feed-horn except at 15, 7 and 3mm where the two
	frequencies must be less than 6 GHz apart, and not straddle the
	7mm sideband inversion (see <xref linkend="strategy-frequency-switching"></xref>).
      </para>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>local oscillator</primary></indexterm>
	In order to convert the received radio signals to lower frequencies,
	the radio signals are mixed with a &#x201C;local oscillator&quot; signal. Four local oscillator signals provide
	four IF outputs to enable the dual-frequency, dual-polarisation
	operation. You can also switch frequencies at the end of each
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>frequency</primary><secondary>switching</secondary></indexterm>
	integration cycle (typically ten seconds). To change to a pair of
	frequencies covered by a different feed-horn requires a rotation of
	the turret and takes about twenty seconds. However, to avoid excessive
	wear of the turrets, a limit of four rotations per hour is imposed. Thus
	time sharing between a number of frequencies is limited only by signal
	to noise ratio, wear and tear on the equipment, your imagination, and
	the off-line software.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Signal-Path">
      <info>
	<title>Signal Path</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	The following sections describe the path of the signal from the initial
	reflection off the antenna surface, through to the data recorded onto
	export media, in more detail than the introduction above.
	Some radio-astronomy jargon is also explained, as is some important
	mathematics. The details of this section are not required by observers, but are
	included for completeness. A knowledge of the system
	is however essential if you want to design an experiment that uses the
	array in a new or unconventional way. Familiarity with the names and
	functions of some critical components can also be helpful if you need
	to diagnose faults. Many system components are housed in modules, and
	repairs can be made quickly by local staff replacing a module once a correct
	diagnosis has been made.
	<figure id="cabbpaths">
	  <title>Overview of signal paths into <acronym>CABB</acronym> (courtesy Brett Hiscock).</title>
          <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="figures/CABB2.jpg" format="JPG"></imagedata>
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</figure>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Sensitivity-and-System-Temperature">
      <info>
	<title>Sensitivity and System Temperature</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>system temperature</primary></indexterm>
	Radio waves (approximately within a range of 300 MHz to 120 GHz) are
	accurately reflected from the primary surface of the main parabolic
	dish and are re-reflected off a secondary reflector into a feed-horn.
	At the base of the feed-horn is a directional, coupling waveguide. In
	this coupler (the <firstterm>noise coupler</firstterm>) is a
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>noise</primary><secondary>coupler</secondary></indexterm>
	diode that injects a noise signal of known amplitude. This noise
	signal is used to calibrate the system temperature (<xref linkend="system_temperature"></xref>)
	and gain of the receiving system.
      </para>

      <para>
	For radiation emitted by a randomly polarised source, the
	power received by a radio telescope is given by:
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{P}_{\mathrm{received}} = \frac{1}{2}\mathrm{A}\mathrm{S} \Delta\nu,
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
	where A is the effective area of the antenna, S is the spectral power flux
	density and
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\Delta\nu</textobject></inlineequation>
	is the range of frequencies observed
	(the effective bandwidth). The factor of
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>bandwidth</primary></indexterm>
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\frac{1}{2}</textobject></inlineequation>
	occurs because a detector can only respond to one
	polarisation component of the randomly polarised wave. The
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary></indexterm>
	<acronym>ATCA</acronym> overcomes this limitation by providing separate detectors and electronics for two
	orthogonal polarisations, thus allowing all the power in the wave to
	be detected.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>band</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATCA</primary><secondary>baselines</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATCA</primary><secondary>configurations</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATCA</primary><secondary>field of view</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATCA</primary><secondary>frequencies</secondary></indexterm>
	<table frame="all" id="table_sensitivity" shortentry="1">
	  <title>Observing Parameters for the 6km Compact Array.</title>
	  <titleabbrev><acronym>ATCA</acronym> Observing Parameters</titleabbrev>
	  <!-- <?dbfo keep-together="always" ?> -->
	  <tgroup cols="6" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	    <colspec colname="band"/>
	    <colspec colname="ls" colwidth="0.6*"/>
	    <colspec colname="cx" colwidth="0.6*"/>
	    <colspec colname="k" colwidth="0.6*"/>
	    <colspec colname="q" colwidth="0.6*"/>
	    <colspec colname="w" colwidth="0.6*"/>
	    <thead>
	      <row>
		<entry>Band Name</entry>
		<entry>16cm</entry>
		<entry>4cm</entry>
		<entry>15mm</entry>
		<entry>7mm</entry>
		<entry>3mm</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Band Code</entry>
		<entry>L / S</entry>
		<entry>C / X</entry>
		<entry>K</entry>
		<entry>Q</entry>
		<entry>W</entry>
	      </row>
	    </thead>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry>Frequency Range (GHz)</entry>
		<entry>1.1 - 3.1</entry>
		<entry>3.9 - 11.0</entry>
		<entry>16 - 25</entry>
		<entry>30 - 50</entry>
		<entry>83 - 105</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Fractional frequency range</entry>
		<entry>95%</entry>
		<entry>95%</entry>
		<entry>44%</entry>
		<entry>50%</entry>
		<entry>24%</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Number of antennas</entry>
		<entry>6</entry>
		<entry>6</entry>
		<entry>6</entry>
		<entry>6</entry>
		<entry>5</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Number of baselines</entry>
		<entry>15</entry>
		<entry>15</entry>
		<entry>15</entry>
		<entry>15</entry>
		<entry>10</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>
		  Primary beam
		  <footnote>
		    <para>
		      Field of view (full width at half power).
		    </para>
		  </footnote>
		</entry>
		<entry>42&#x2032; - 15&#x2032;</entry>
		<entry>12&#x2032; - 4&#x2032;</entry>
		<entry>2&#x2032;</entry>
		<entry>70&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>30&#x2033;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>
		  System temperature (K)
		  <footnote>
		    <para>
		      The system temperature at high elevation under
		      reasonable weather conditions. These values,
		      particularly at high frequency, are weather-dependent.
		    </para>
		  </footnote>
		</entry>
		<entry>45</entry>
		<entry>36</entry>
		<entry>60</entry>
		<entry>112</entry>
		<entry>724</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>
		  System sensitivity (Jy)
		  <footnote>
		    <para>
		      The signal which doubles the system temperature.
		    </para>
		  </footnote>
		</entry>
		<entry>55</entry>
		<entry>43</entry>
		<entry>72</entry>
		<entry>136</entry>
		<entry>1051</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>
		  Strongest confusing source (mJy)
		  <footnote>
		    <para>
		      Within FWHM primary beam &#x2014; see A.H. Bridle, in
		      Perley R.A., Schwab F.A. &amp; Bridle A.H. (1989)
		      &#x201C;Synthesis Imaging in Radio Astronomy&#x201D; Astron. Soc.
		      Pacific Conf. Set., 6, p.471.
		    </para>
		  </footnote>
		</entry>
		<entry>140 - 24</entry>
		<entry>2.3 - 0.4</entry>
		<entry>&#x2014;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2014;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2014;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Array assumed below</entry>
		<entry>6 km</entry>
		<entry>6 km</entry>
		<entry>6 km</entry>
		<entry>6 km</entry>
		<entry>H214</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>
		  Synthesized beam
		  <footnote>
		    <para>
		      HPBW in R.A. for the 6 km array for all bands except 3mm,
		      for which the H214 array is assumed. No taper applied. In
		      Declination, for the 6 km array (and other pure east-west
		      arrays), the HPBW is larger by cosec(Dec). Longer arrays
		      (up to 3 km) are possible at 3mm but only with self-calibration
		      and under favourable weather conditions.
		    </para>
		  </footnote>
		</entry>
		<entry>9&#x2033; - 3&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>3&#x2033; - 1&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>0.5&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>0.2&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>2&#x2033;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Bandwidth assumed below (GHz)</entry>
		<entry>2</entry>
		<entry>2</entry>
		<entry>2</entry>
		<entry>2</entry>
		<entry>2</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Centre frequency assumed below (GHz)</entry>
		<entry>2.1</entry>
		<entry>7.0</entry>
		<entry>17.0</entry>
		<entry>40.0</entry>
		<entry>95.0</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>
		  Flux sensitivity (mJy/beam) (10 min)
		  <footnote>
		    <para>
		      Theoretical rms noise; one frequency; dual orthogonal polarisation;
		      natural weighting. The effect of confusing sources can substantially
		      degrade this number. This is the 1&#x03C3; Gaussian-noise level.
		    </para>
		  </footnote>
		</entry>
		<entry>0.04</entry>
		<entry>0.03</entry>
		<entry>0.05</entry>
		<entry>0.09</entry>
		<entry>0.70</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>
		  Brightness sensitivity (K) (10 min)
		  <footnote>
		    <para>
		      For the array listed in the same column: see following table for
		      shorter arrays. This is the 1&#x03C3; Gaussian-noise level.
		    </para>
		  </footnote>
		</entry>
		<entry>0.1</entry>
		<entry>0.1</entry>
		<entry>0.16</entry>
		<entry>0.29</entry>
		<entry>0.02</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Flux sensitivity (&#x03BC;Jy/beam) (12 hr)</entry>
		<entry>4</entry>
		<entry>3</entry>
		<entry>5</entry>
		<entry>33</entry>
		<entry>83</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Brightness sensitivity (K) (12 hr)</entry>
		<entry>0.02</entry>
		<entry>0.01</entry>
		<entry>0.02</entry>
		<entry>0.01</entry>
		<entry>0.002</entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</table>
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>sensitivity</primary></indexterm>
	The <firstterm>sensitivity</firstterm> of a radio telescope is the minimum signal power that
	can be distinguished from the random fluctuations at the output of the
	receiving system which are caused by noise inherent in the system. The
	sensitivity is usually defined as the spectral power flux density
	of a source that would produce the same
	signal power as the noise power. It is
	measured in <firstterm>Jansky</firstterm> (<abbrev>Jy</abbrev>), with 
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">1 \mathrm{Jy} = 10^{-26} \mathrm{\,W\,m}^{-2} \mathrm{\,Hz}^{-1}.
	</textobject></inlineequation>
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>noise</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>power</primary><secondary>definition</secondary></indexterm>
	The <firstterm>noise power</firstterm> consists of two main components: the noise power due
	to the receiving amplifier and other electrical system components, and
	the noise due to ground radiation, thermal emission from the
	atmosphere (which varies with elevation, cloud cover, etc.), background
	radio emission from our Galaxy and other sources detected by the
	antenna. These noise powers are usually referred to as <firstterm>equivalent
	temperatures</firstterm>, although at no
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>temperature</primary><secondary>equivalent</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>temperature</primary><secondary>system</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>system temperature</primary></indexterm>
	point is a physical temperature measured. The &#x201C;temperature&#x201D; due to
	the noise power is called the <firstterm>system temperature</firstterm>,
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{T}_{\mathrm{sys}}</textobject></inlineequation>,
	and is related to the noise power by:
	<equation id="system_temperature">
	  <title>System Temperature</title>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{T}_{\mathrm{sys}} = \frac{\mathrm{P}_{\mathrm{noise}}}{k\Delta\nu},
	  </textobject>
	</equation>
	where 
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{P}_{\mathrm{noise}}</textobject></inlineequation>
	is the noise power and
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">k</textobject></inlineequation>
	is Boltzmann's constant.  As both the source and noise signals are random
	in nature, measurements of the power levels made at time intervals
	separated by 
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">(2 \Delta\nu)^{-1}</textobject></inlineequation>
	can be considered independent
	(e.g., Thompson, Moran &amp; Swenson 1986, 2001).  If the signal level is
	averaged for
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">t</textobject></inlineequation>
	seconds then 
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">2 \Delta\nu t</textobject></inlineequation>
	samples have been measured.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>signal</primary><secondary>to noise ratio</secondary></indexterm>
	The signal to noise ratio is the ratio of the power in the output that
	is due to the radio source being observed to that caused by the noise,
	and is given by:
        <informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \frac{\mathrm{S}}{\mathrm{N}} = \frac{\mathrm{T}_{\mathrm{ant}}}{\mathrm{T}_{\mathrm{sys}}} \times \sqrt{\mathrm{number\; of\; independent\; samples}}.
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
        In this expression,
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{T}_{\mathrm{ant}}</textobject></inlineequation>
	is the <firstterm>antenna temperature</firstterm>, the
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>antenna</primary><secondary>temperature</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>temperature</primary><secondary>antenna</secondary></indexterm>
	equivalent temperature of the radio source being observed. Note that
	&#x201C;antenna temperature&quot; is sometimes also taken to mean the
	contribution to the noise power from radio noise detected by the
	antenna, as described above. For typical values for bandwidth (2 GHz)
	and integration time (12 hours), it is possible to detect a
	signal for which the power level is less than
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">10^{-6}</textobject></inlineequation>
	times the noise level.
      </para>
      <!-- %CHANGE THIS -->
      <!-- %\latex{Table \ref{ch3_t_btsens}}\html{A table} (on page 24) lists \htmlref{sensitivity -->
      <!-- %values}{ch3_t_btsens} -->
      <!-- %for the ATCA at various wavelengths. -->
      <!-- %Christiansen and H@"ogbom (1985) has a chapter on sensitivity. -->
    </section>
      
    <section id="Online-Calibration">
      <info>
	<title>Online Calibration</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATCA</primary><secondary>calibration</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibration</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>software</primary><secondary>online</secondary></indexterm>
	The noise source in the noise coupler injects a signal that is about 5%
	of the level of the system temperature at a rate of 30 Hz. This noise
	signal is synchronously demodulated and the following relationship
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>noise</primary><secondary>diode</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>synchronous demodulator</primary></indexterm>
	holds:
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
	    \mathrm{T}_{\mathrm{sys}} = \mathrm{T}_{\mathrm{cal}} \times \frac{\mathrm{P}_{\mathrm{on}}}{\mathrm{P}_{\mathrm{on}} - \mathrm{P}_{\mathrm{off}}}.
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
	Here,
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{T}_{\mathrm{cal}}</textobject></inlineequation>
	is the equivalent temperature of the noise
	source,
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{P}_{\mathrm{on}}</textobject></inlineequation>
	is the power received while the noise diode is
	on, and
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{P}_{\mathrm{off}}</textobject></inlineequation>
	is the power received while the noise diode is
	off.  
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{T}_{\mathrm{sys}}</textobject></inlineequation>
	is measured accurately once by placing a thermal
	radiator of known temperature (a microwave absorber at 300K, giving
	300K
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">+ \mathrm{T}_{\mathrm{sys}}</textobject></inlineequation>)
	directly above the feeds. The power received
	with this load in place is then compared with the power output with
	the antenna just looking at the sky (
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\sim \mathrm{T}_{\mathrm{sys}} + 3\mathrm{\,K}</textobject></inlineequation>).
	This measurement is used to establish the level of
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{T}_{\mathrm{cal}}</textobject></inlineequation>,
	which is assumed not to vary with time. The measurement of system and antenna
	temperature is described in a 
	<ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/observers/memos/d95b94%7E1.pdf">technical memo by 
	Sinclair and Gough (1991)</ulink>.

      </para>
      <para>
	The noise coupler is mounted on another coupler
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>feedhorns</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>noise</primary><secondary>coupler</secondary></indexterm>
	that provides a vacuum seal between the noise coupler and the subsequent
	receiver system, which is housed in an evacuated, cryogenic
	cylinder. An air gap
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>receiver</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>cryogenics</primary><secondary>cylinder</secondary></indexterm>
	thermally isolates the cylinder, the contents of which are cooled by a
	helium pump to 20K. The second coupler is mounted on the polariser.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary><secondary>polariser</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary></indexterm>
	The dual function of the polariser is to select the two linear
	polarisations and the desired band, so it is also known as a
	<firstterm>band splitter</firstterm>. The
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>band</primary><secondary>splitter</secondary></indexterm>
	polariser consists of four strips of metal inside a conical waveguide
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>waveguide</primary><secondary>conical</secondary></indexterm>
	that &#x201C;guide&#x201D; two orthogonal linear polarisations into probes at the
	narrow end of the polariser. The way in which the metal strips select
	the linear polarisations can be thought of as analogous to the effect
	of a ridged waveguide, which constrains a particular mode to propagate
	along the region between the ridge and the roof of the waveguide. The
	probes are simply short (with respect to the wavelength) lengths of
	the cores of the coaxial cables that take the signal into the first
	amplifiers. Thus the polariser converts a wave into a voltage: the
	impedance of the circuit is effectively the same as a waveguide
	impedance, so it works like a well-matched load. The polariser's
	official title is quad-ridged
	<firstterm>orthomode transducer</firstterm>, or <acronym>OMT</acronym>.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>orthomode transducer</primary><secondary>quad-ridged</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>orthomode transducer</primary></indexterm>
	Separate electronics exist for both orthogonal linear polarisations,
	which are measured simultaneously. The position angle of the polariser
	is fixed with respect to the antenna. As the antennas have
	altitude-azimuth mounts, the position angle of the linear probes
	rotate on the sky during the course of an observation (imagine a
	circumpolar line on the sky orbiting around a stationary antenna).
	Measurement of both polarisations is therefore required for polarised
	sources. The two linear polarisations can be combined to give an
	accurate total
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>Stokes parameters</primary><secondary>observed</secondary></indexterm>
	intensity: the Stokes I parameter. Without
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>Stokes parameters</primary></indexterm>
	additional calibration, the other Stokes parameters
	(the linear polarisation measures Q, and U, and the
	circularly polarised component V) can
	be in error by about 2% of the value of I. Measurements of the
	phase difference of the two linear polarisations (referred to as the X and
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary><secondary>X and Y</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary><secondary>A and B</secondary></indexterm>
	Y (or A and B) polarisations) at the receiver by on-line hardware may
	need further off-line calibration.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	For an unpolarised source, observing both orthogonal polarisations
	offers a
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\sqrt{2}</textobject></inlineequation>
	improvement in signal to noise ratio for an I
	image over an image generated from only one polarisation.
      </para>

      <!-- For the 6/3cm band, the two polarised outputs from the polariser go -->
      <!-- into @dfn{diplexers} which filter off the 6cm band and 3cm band -->
      <!-- signals. This stage is not necessary for any of the other bands. -->
      <!-- Separate IF chains exist for each of the subsequent four -->
      <!-- signals. -->
      <!-- Coaxial cable takes t -->
      <!-- The signal is taken from the feedhorn/diplexer into -->
      <para>
	The signal is taken from the feedhorn into
	<!-- @cindex diplexer -->
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>amplifier</primary><secondary>low noise</secondary></indexterm>
	a low noise, broadband amplifier.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The receivers each use two low-noise
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>LNA</primary><see>amplifier</see></indexterm>
	amplifiers (<acronym>LNA</acronym>s) to amplify the signal by 30&#x2013;40 dB.
	All six antennas are fitted with wideband, continuously running,
	receivers.  Cooled
	indium-phosphide 
	high electron mobility transistors
	(<acronym>InP HEMT</acronym>s) 
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>transistor</primary><secondary>high electron mobility</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>amplifier</primary><secondary>HEMT</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>transistor</primary><secondary>indium phosphide</secondary></indexterm>
	are used at 16cm and 4cm, 
	and indium-phosphide monolithic microwave integrated circuit (<acronym>InP MMIC</acronym>) devices
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>amplifier</primary><secondary>MMIC</secondary></indexterm>
	are used at 15mm, 7mm and 3mm.  Only the &#x201C;inner&quot;
	five antennas (i.e., excluding CA06) have 3mm receivers.
	The accessible
	frequency range is given in <xref linkend="table_sensitivity"></xref>, and
	the average system temperatures are given in <xref linkend="table_brightness_temperature"></xref>
	and in <xref linkend="Available-Frequency-Range"></xref>.  Note that
	frequencies outside these nominal limits may be accessible.
      </para>

      <para>
	The next step is the conversion to the frequency range that is used by
	<!-- the CABB digitisers. The 3cm -->the <acronym>CABB</acronym> digitisers. The 4cm
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>CABB</primary><secondary>digitisers</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>frequency</primary><secondary>conversion</secondary></indexterm>
	<!-- and 6cm -->signals require no conversion, whereas the mm signals require
	a down-conversion stage, and the 16cm signals require
	up-conversion to the 4 to 12 GHz band.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>local oscillator</primary></indexterm>
	The local oscillator signals have a relatively narrow tuning range,
	lying in the regions between the radio frequency bands (this reduces
	the likelihood of self-generated interference).  The conversion system
	is flexible, allowing the input signals to be within the same band
	(e.g., both in the 4cm centred band), or one from each of the two
	bands simultaneously received by the wide-band feed-horn.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="CABB-Correlator">
      <info>
	<title><acronym>CABB</acronym> Correlator</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	The final output from the conversion system is sent to the <firstterm>samplers</firstterm>
	for digitisation. The <acronym>CABB</acronym> (Compact Array Broadband Backend) samplers were developed in-house and are capable
	of 4 gigasamples per second (GS/s), with 10 bit sampling (more information is
	available in the
	<ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/news/newsletter/feb07/CABB_upgrade.htm">
	  February 2007 <acronym>ATNF</acronym> newsletter</ulink>
	  and in 
	<ulink url="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2011MNRAS.416..832W">Wilson et al. (2011, MNRAS, 416, 832)</ulink>).
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The samplers, which are also referred to as the
	<acronym>CABB</acronym> digitisers, do two things. First
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>CABB</primary><secondary>digitisers</secondary></indexterm>
	the analog (continuously variable in time and amplitude) signal is
	sampled into a discrete-time sequence of values. This process does not
	degrade the signal as it is sampled at the <firstterm>Nyquist rate</firstterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>Nyquist rate</primary></indexterm>
	(twice the inverse frequency of the bandwidth of the analog signal).
	Subsequently, each of the discrete-time, continuously variable values
	are converted to one of a finite set of values: this is called
	<firstterm>quantising</firstterm>.
	<!-- Traditionally, in order to keep the data rate at a manageable level, -->
	<!-- the quantisation is fairly coarse: in the case of one-bit sampling -->
	<!-- only the sign of the signal is retained. Two-bit sampling detects -->
	<!-- which of four states the signal is in when sampled, and so on. -->
	<!-- Quantisation naturally results in degradation of signal to noise ratio -->
	<!-- (or, put another way, quantisation noise is added to the signal). -->
	<!-- However the -->
	<!-- sensitivity lost when quantised signals are correlated is -->
	<!-- remarkably little: one-bit sampling recovers 64% of the information -->
	<!-- @cindex samplers, 1-bit -->
	<!-- @cindex samplers, 2-bit -->
	<!-- contained in the signal (Van Vleck and Middleton 1966, but see, e.g., -->
	<!-- Thompson, Moran & Swenson 1986, pp. 210-230). -->
	<!-- Two-bit sampling recovers 88%. --><acronym>CABB</acronym> uses 9-bit sampling (internally, as stated above, 10-bit sampling is used, with 9 bits transferred to the correlator), with approximately 6-bits
	used in sampling the regular data range, and the additional bits providing
	extra robustness in the case of interference
	<acronym>RFI</acronym> (radio-frequency interference).
	The digitised signals from the sampler are sent from each antenna to
	the correlator along optic fibres at a rate of 160 gigabits per
	second for each antenna. Optical fibres run from the samplers in each
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>optical fibre</primary></indexterm>
	antenna to the correlator, which is housed in the
	screened room (to prevent RFI generated by the correlator electronics from
	affecting the observations) of the central control
	building. Synchronising code is added to the data stream at the start
	of each integration cycle to allow each bit to be correctly identified
	at the correlator irrespective of temporal changes in the length of
	the fibre.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>correlator</primary><see>CABB</see></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>correlator</primary></indexterm>
	The <firstterm>correlator</firstterm> effectively multiplies simultaneous signals from
	two samplers: the more similar the signal from both antennas,
	the large the degree of correlation.  A plane wavefront approaching the
	<acronym>ATCA</acronym> will, in general, arrive at different antennas at different
	times. The signals from the antennas therefore need to be <firstterm>delayed</firstterm>
	before being presented to the correlator so as to simulate a wavefront
	arriving at each antenna simultaneously.  This was previously
	achieved by separate
	<firstterm>delay units</firstterm>, but is now included in the <acronym>CABB</acronym> boards.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>CABB</primary><secondary>delay units</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>delay</primary><secondary>calibration</secondary><see>calibration</see></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>delay</secondary></indexterm>
	The <firstterm>delay calibration</firstterm> undertaken at the start of an observation
	removes other delays caused by return path length
	differences, instrumental delay variations and the like, so that
	wavefront samples are presented to the correlator synchronously.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The <acronym>CABB</acronym> filterbank/correlator is divided across a number of Digital Signal Processing (DSP)
	boards. The DSP boards use Virtex-4
	Xilinx Field Programmable Gated Arrays (FPGAs) to provide a flexible, programmable
	hardware correlator.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>CABB</primary><secondary>blocks</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>CABB</primary><secondary>boards</secondary></indexterm>
	The output from the correlator is averaged for the period of one
	<firstterm>integration cycle</firstterm>, and sent to the correlator control computer caccc
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>integration</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>integration</primary><secondary>cycle</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>integration</primary><secondary>averaging</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>caccc</primary></indexterm>
	where it is written to hard disk.
	Integration cycles can be set by the observer, between 2 and 30 seconds,
	although the default cycle time of 10 seconds is generally recommended for
	all observers. (For mosaic-mode observations, 6-seconds is the practical
minimum cycle time.)
      </para>
      
      <para>
	More information on the correlator can be found at the
	<ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/CABB.html"><acronym>CABB</acronym> webpage</ulink>.
	This page is updated frequently, and the current state of correlator development can always
	be found there.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	The <acronym>CABB</acronym> correlator provides a number of observing
	modes:
	<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Two always-available 2048 MHz continuum IF bands (although an analogue bandpass filter
	    may reduce the usable bandwidth by 32 MHz). These can currently be divided into 2048 x 1MHz channels or 32 x 64MHz channels, 
	    with up to 16 &#x201C;zoom&#x201D; bands able to be placed for higher spectral resolution.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Up to 6 GHz separation of simultaneous IF centre frequencies (depending on receiver restrictions)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>9 bit sampling accuracy</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Square, independent channels (ie. no leakage between channels)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>All polarisation parameters for all products (including auto-correlations)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Up to 16 zoom bands per IF to provide finer spectral resolution</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>A pulsar binning mode</para>
          </listitem>
<!--          <listitem>
            <para>Integration times as fast as 1 second</para>
          </listitem>
-->
        </itemizedlist>
        This design ensures that the user will always get high continuum sensitivity from the
	wide-bandwidth IFs, while providing very high spectral resolution for line studies at
	the same time.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="Choosing-an-Observing-Frequency">
    <info>
      <title>Choosing an Observing Frequency</title>
    </info>
    <section id="Available-Frequency-Range">
      <info>
        <title>Available Frequency Range</title>
      </info>
      <figure id="cmsystemps21">
        <title>
	  Average Compact Array system temperatures for 
	  each observing band at high elevation under reasonable observing conditions. These are based 
	  on hot-cold load measurements, and include the atmosphere at the time of observation, thus 
	  representing the total system temperature. These measurements were made by J. Stevens 
	  with the <acronym>CABB</acronym> system, except for the 3mm measurements which were 
	  made by T. Wong in September 2004.
	</title>
	<titleabbrev>Average <acronym>ATCA</acronym> system temperatures in each observing band.</titleabbrev>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="figures/usersguide_sefds_tsys_combined_l.jpg" format="JPG">
	    </imagedata>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
	You can also switch automatically to other wavelengths within
	tens of seconds (with the exception of the 7mm band as described
	previously). Similarly the 16cm receiver has a single
	feedhorn and observations with this package will cover the entire
	1.1 - 3.1 GHz range simultaneously.
	Observations at two simultaneous frequencies are possible in the 15mm
	band or the 7mm, or the 3mm bands.  With <acronym>CABB</acronym>, the centre frequencies
	of the two <acronym>IF</acronym>s need to lie within 6 GHz of each other, and 
	even this might be too much separation depending on the exact frequencies chosen.
	For <acronym>CABB</acronym>, the nominal standard frequencies for continuum observations
	are 
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>2100 MHz in the 16cm band,</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>5500 MHz and 9000 MHz in the 4cm band,</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>16700 MHz and 21200 MHz in the 15mm band,</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>33000 MHz and 35000 MHz in the 7mm LSB band,</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>43000 MHz and 45000 MHz in the 7mm USB band,</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>93000 MHz and 95000 MHz in the 3mm band.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	These frequency designations follow the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> custom
	of stating the central frequency of the chosen observing frequency
	range. (For archival data from the pre-CABB era
	the standard frequencies were
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>1384 MHz and 2368 MHz in the 20/13cm band,</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>4800 MHz and 8640 MHz in the 6/3cm band,</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>18496 MHz and 19520 MHz in the 12mm band,</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>34496 MHz and 34524 MHz in the 7mm LSB band,</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>44096 MHz and 44224 MHz in the 7mm USB band,</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>93504 MHz and 95552 MHz in the 3mm band.</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	The 15mm recommended <acronym>CABB</acronym> central frequencies have recently been changed
	from 17000 and 19000 GHz, due to the presence of RFI from a geostationary satellite
	(see <xref linkend="interference_mm"></xref> for details).
      </para>
      <!-- See also -->
      <!-- @url{http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/recfreq.html}. -->

      <para>
	Switching between the 15/3mm bands, the 4cm band, and the 16cm
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>frequency</primary><secondary>switching</secondary></indexterm>
	band involves a change in feed horns by means of a turret
	rotation. This is done automatically under computer control and takes
	about 20 seconds. Turret rotation should be limited to once every 15
	minutes unless a compelling scientific case is made for more frequent
	rotations. The additional overhead in changing to or from 7mm has been
	described earlier in this document.
      </para>

      <para>
	Observing-band centre frequencies may be set to the nearest MHz only and no
	on-line Doppler tracking is done.
      </para>

      <para>
	Observations of weak H 90&#x03B1; recombination lines <emphasis>may be</emphasis>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>feedhorns</primary><secondary>trapped mode</secondary></indexterm>
	affected by a trapped mode in the 6/3cm horn at 8857 &#x00B1; 18 MHz. This trapped mode
	may enhance the power received this recombination line at their rest-frequency.
	There are also notches reported in the passband due to trapped modes in the receiver
	waveguides at 4550 &#x00B1; 10 MHz, 5328 &#x00B1; 10 MHz and
	8780 &#x00B1; 10 MHz which may need to be flagged during data reduction.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Interference">
      <info>
        <title>Interference</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	Both terrestrial and satellite emitters cause radio frequency interference (RFI)
	to <acronym>ATCA</acronym> observations, with the lower frequency bands being more
	adversely affected than the higher frequency bands. This section describes the RFI
	that is known in each of the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> bands, and also covers interference
	caused by the Sun.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>RFI</primary><see>interference</see></indexterm>
      </para>

      <section id="interference_16cm">
	<info>
	  <title>16cm band RFI</title>
	</info>
	<para>
	  The interference is
	  worse at lower frequencies with the main offenders being microwave
	  links, microwave TV, microwave ovens, navigation satellites and
	  self-generated interference.  There can also be significant
	  interference at 1381 MHz from the GPS L3 beacon on occasions.  These
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>satellite</primary><secondary>GPS</secondary></indexterm>
	  channels may have to be removed from the data.
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary><secondary>survey</secondary>
	  <tertiary>16cm</tertiary></indexterm>
	  <xref linkend="rfi_survey_annotated"></xref> shows what the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> sees
	  in its 16cm band (centred at the recommended continuum central frequency of 2100 MHz)
	  when fringe-rotation is disabled (achieved by setting the phase centre to be the South
	  celestial pole). The black and red lines show the log of the amplitude as observed by
	  a survey in 2011 and 2015 respectively, and from this we can see that the RFI environment
	  does change slightly over time. No self-generated interference is visible in this plot.
	  The Australian Communications and Media Authority (<acronym>ACMA</acronym>) band licenses
	  are shown on the plot as coloured frequency regions. The strongest sources of RFI are
	  mobile phone towers, satellites and TV transmitters, all of which are relatively stable
	  in time.
	</para>

	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_survey_annotated">
	    <title>The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> 16cm RFI environment. Two surveys are shown, one from 2011 and the other
	    from 2015. The licenses applicable to each frequency range are shown as coloured
	    regions, labelled with a similar colour at the top of the plot.</title>
	    <titleabbrev><acronym>ATCA</acronym> 16cm RFI environment.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/rfisurvey_comparison_broadranges.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary><secondary>RFI monitor</secondary></indexterm>
	  An RFI monitoring antenna sits atop the central control building at the observatory. It monitors
	  the frequency range 700 - 3000 MHz once every 20 seconds, with 2 MHz frequency resolution,
	  and presents its data in near-real time
	  <ulink url="https://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/rfi/monitor/rfi_monitor.html#atca">on a web page</ulink>.
	  Three different plots are presented on the page: a &#x201C;latest spectra&#x201D; plot
	  (<xref linkend="rfi_monitor_spectra"></xref>), a waterfall plot showing the last hour of
	  data (<xref linkend="rfi_monitor_waterfall"></xref>), and a plot that may help in determining
	  the direction from which RFI is being observed (<xref linkend="rfi_monitor_polar"></xref>). The
	  latest spectra plot always shows the earliest spectrum obtained by the monitor in the displayed time range, along with
	  a &#x201C;maximum hold&#x201D; value for each channel over the last hour and the time-averaged power
	  for each channel. The waterfall plot
	  is useful for seeing emission switch on or off over the last hour. All data from the RFI monitor
	  is archived, and if you want to get the output of the monitor for a particular time range since
	  its installation in November 2014, please visit the
	  <ulink url="https://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/rfi/monitor/rfi_monitor_archive_query.html">
	    archive query page</ulink>.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_monitor_spectra">
	    <title>An example of the &#x201C;latest spectra&#x201D; plot available from the
	    <acronym>ATCA</acronym> RFI weathermap page.</title>
	    <titleabbrev>&#x201C;Latest spectra&#x201D; plot example from the RFI weathermap page.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/rfimonitor_spectrum_latest.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_monitor_waterfall">
	    <title>An example of the &#x201C;latest waterfall&#x201D; plot available from the
	    <acronym>ATCA</acronym> RFI weathermap page.</title>
	    <titleabbrev>&#x201C;Latest waterfall&#x201D; plot example from the RFI weathermap page.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/rfimonitor_rfiwaterfall_latest.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_monitor_polar">
	    <title>An example of the &#x201C;latest skyplot&#x201D; plot available from the
	    <acronym>ATCA</acronym> RFI weathermap page.</title>
	    <titleabbrev>&#x201C;Latest skyplot&#x201D; plot example from the RFI weathermap page.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/rfimonitor_skyplot_latest.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary><secondary>mid-week RFI</secondary></indexterm>
	  In addition to the &#x201C;normal&#x201D; RFI in the 16cm band, as shown in
	  <xref linkend="rfi_survey_annotated"></xref>, you may also see something dubbed
	  &#x201C;mid-week RFI&#x201D;. This RFI has frequency peaks around 1265 and 1300-1310 MHz,
	  and can have extremely high amplitudes. The RFI monitor can be used to see when mid-week RFI
	  is present, as shown in <xref linkend="rfi_monitor_midweek"></xref>. Because of the strength
	  of this RFI, it can often drive the front-end system of the 16cm receivers, or the CABB digitisers,
	  into saturation; if this occurs, the data becomes unusable. We do now sometimes receive advanced
	  warning on when this RFI may be present, and if this will affect observations, the investigators
	  will be notified so they can plan how to deal with it.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_monitor_midweek">
	    <title>A waterfall plot from the RFI monitor, showing what &#x201C;mid-week RFI&#x201D;
	    can look like (in the brighter region).</title>
	    <titleabbrev>RFI weathermap waterfall plot showing &#x201C;mid-week RFI&#x201D;.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/rfimonitor_midweek.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>

	<para>
	  Only the 16cm band is affected by mid-week RFI, so if mid-week RFI is forecast during your
	  observations, you may wish to avoid using the 16cm band during those times, wherever possible.
	  If this is not possible, you may ask for a schedule swap, but this may not always be a
	  possibility. Our observations have also shown that mid-week RFI is present only for a small
	  fraction of the default CABB 10 second cycle time, but is so strong that it ruins the entire
	  integration. You may therefore be able to cope with mid-week RFI by running with a shorter cycle
	  time (say 1 or 2 seconds) and flagging those cycles in which the RFI is present; this will result
	  in a much higher data rate of course, and is only really suitable for continuum experiments that
	  do not need mosaicking.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section id="interference_4cm">
	<info>
	  <title>4cm band RFI</title>
	</info>
	<para>
	  The RFI present in the 4cm band is direction dependent, and can be quite variable over time.
	  Using a similar survey technique to the 16cm band, where the fringe-rotation is disabled, we can
	  determine the static levels of RFI. We also use the antennas to determine how directional the
	  RFI signals are, by doing the survey twice; once while the antennas are pointing at the
	  South Celestial Pole (<acronym>SCP</acronym>, <xref linkend="rfi_survey_4cm_scp"></xref>),
	  and again while pointing at the celestial equator (<xref linkend="rfi_survey_4cm_equ"></xref>).
	  We expect that signals coming from satellites will be stronger towards the celestial equator.
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary><secondary>4cm band</secondary></indexterm>
	</para>

	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_survey_4cm_scp">
	    <title>The 4cm band, as observed during an RFI survey from 2016-09-07, while the antennas
	    were pointing at the South Celestial Pole (<acronym>SCP</acronym>). The colour bands show
	    frequency ranges that represent either the <acronym>CABB</acronym> recommended continuum
	    bands, or the ACMA licence applicable.</title>
	    <titleabbrev>RFI in the 4cm band, towards the SCP.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/rfisurvey_4cm_scp.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>

      	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_survey_4cm_equ">
	    <title>The 4cm band, as observed during an RFI survey from 2016-09-07, while the antennas
	    were pointing at the celestial equator at transit. The colour bands show
	    frequency ranges that represent either the <acronym>CABB</acronym> recommended continuum
	    bands, or the ACMA licence applicable.</title>
	    <titleabbrev>RFI in the 4cm band, towards the celestial equator.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/rfisurvey_4cm_equ.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>

      <para>
	Indeed, we see that in the pink- and orange-highlighted regions of those two figures, the signal intensity
	is higher while pointing at the equator. That is, in the frequency bands licenced for
	satellite communications to Earth, the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> will see a lot more interfering
	signal while observing near to the equator. The frequencies of these highlighted regions are given
	in <xref linkend="table_rfi_4cm_satellites"></xref>.
      </para>

      <para>
	<table frame="all" id="table_rfi_4cm_satellites" shortentry="1">
	  <title>Frequency ranges of satellite emission bands observed with a 4cm RFI survey. The ranges given
	  are delimited by ACMA allocations, so several entries may be given even if they represent one contiguous
	  frequency range.</title>
	  <titleabbrev>Frequency ranges of satellite emission bands observed with a 4cm RFI survey.</titleabbrev>
	  <tgroup cols="3" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	    <colspec colname="purpose"/>
	    <colspec colname="lowfreq"/>
	    <colspec colname="highfreq"/>
	    <thead>
	      <row>
		<entry morerows="1" valign="middle">Purpose</entry>
		<entry namest="lowfreq" nameend="highfreq">Frequencies</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Low [GHz]</entry>
		<entry>High [GHz]</entry>
	      </row>
	    </thead>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry morerows="6" valign="middle">Communications to Earth</entry>
		<entry>3.6</entry>
		<entry>4.2</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>5.925</entry>
		<entry>6.7</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>7.2525</entry>
		<entry>7.3775</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>7.375</entry>
		<entry>7.45</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>7.45</entry>
		<entry>7.55</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>7.55</entry>
		<entry>7.75</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>10.7</entry>
		<entry>11.7</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>Broadcast to Earth</entry>
		<entry>11.7</entry>
		<entry>12.2</entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</table>
      </para>

      <para>
	The other frequency ranges shown on <xref linkend="rfi_survey_4cm_scp"></xref> and
	<xref linkend="rfi_survey_4cm_equ"></xref> encompass RFI that is not likely to be from
	satellites, but as can be seen, the intensity of this RFI is not high and should be easily
	excisable during data reduction.
      </para>
      
      </section>

      <section id="interference_mm">
	<info>
	  <title>mm band RFI</title>
	</info>
	<para>
	  There appears to be no significant interference within the 7mm and 3mm bands.
	  A recent RFI survey in the 15mm band showed that interference from the Australian
	  National Broadband Network (NBN) satellite &#x201C;Sky Muster&#x201D; is now clearly
	  visible when pointing toward the equator. Similar to the 4cm RFI survey technique,
	  <xref linkend="rfi_survey_15mm_equ"></xref>, <xref linkend="rfi_survey_15mm_scp"></xref> and
	  <xref linkend="rfi_survey_15mm_zen"></xref> show that the signal received by the antennas
	  from this satellite (soon to be two satellites) is very dependent on the pointing
	  direction.
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary><secondary>15mm band</secondary></indexterm>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary><secondary>Sky Muster satellite</secondary></indexterm>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Sky Muster</primary><see>interference</see></indexterm>
	</para>

      	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_survey_15mm_equ">
	    <title>The 15mm band, as observed during an RFI survey from 2016-08-01, while the antennas
	    were pointing at the celestial equator at transit.</title>
	    <titleabbrev>RFI in the 15mm band, towards the celestial equator.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/rfisurvey_15mm_equ.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>

	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_survey_15mm_scp">
	    <title>The 15mm band, as observed during an RFI survey from 2016-08-01, while the antennas
	    were pointing at the South Celestial Pole (<acronym>SCP</acronym>) at transit.</title>
	    <titleabbrev>RFI in the 15mm band, towards the SCP.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/rfisurvey_15mm_scp.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>

      	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_survey_15mm_zen">
	    <title>The 15mm band, as observed during an RFI survey from 2016-08-01, while the antennas
	    were pointing east at an elevation of 85&#176;.</title>
	    <titleabbrev>RFI in the 15mm band, towards azimuth 90&#176; and elevation 85&#176;.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/rfisurvey_15mm_zen.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>

	<para>
	  The &#x201C;Sky Muster&#x201D; satellite emits in
	  <ulink url="http://www.nbnco.com.au/content/dam/nbnco2/documents/network-design-rules.pdf">
	    three broad downlink frequency ranges</ulink>.
	  These ranges are 17.7 - 18.2 GHz (<xref linkend="rfi_survey_15mm_skymuster_range1"></xref>),
	  18.8 - 19.3 GHz (<xref linkend="rfi_survey_15mm_skymuster_range2"></xref>)
	  and 19.7 - 20.2 GHz (<xref linkend="rfi_survey_15mm_skymuster_range3"></xref>).
	</para>

      	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_survey_15mm_skymuster_range1">
	    <title>A subset of the 15mm band, as observed during an RFI survey from 2016-08-01, while the antennas
	    were pointing at the celestial equator. This frequency subset covers the &#x201C;Sky Muster&#x201D;
	    downlink range 17.7 - 18.2 GHz.</title>
	    <titleabbrev>RFI in the 15mm band from the low Sky Muster downlink range.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/skymuster_range1.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>

      	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_survey_15mm_skymuster_range2">
	    <title>A subset of the 15mm band, as observed during an RFI survey from 2016-08-01, while the antennas
	    were pointing at the celestial equator. This frequency subset covers the &#x201C;Sky Muster&#x201D;
	    downlink range 18.8 - 19.3 GHz.</title>
	    <titleabbrev>RFI in the 15mm band from the middle Sky Muster downlink range.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/skymuster_range2.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>
	
      	<para>
	  <figure id="rfi_survey_15mm_skymuster_range3">
	    <title>A subset of the 15mm band, as observed during an RFI survey from 2016-08-01, while the antennas
	    were pointing at the celestial equator. This frequency subset covers the &#x201C;Sky Muster&#x201D;
	    downlink range 19.7 - 20.2 GHz.</title>
	    <titleabbrev>RFI in the 15mm band from the high Sky Muster downlink range.</titleabbrev>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="figures/skymuster_range3.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</para>

	<para>
	  This geostationary satellite is at an azimuth of 341.5&#176; and elevation of 53.1&#176;, as
	  seen from the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>. This corresponds to a declination of +6&#176; 35&#x2032;
	  and hour angle of +1h 14m (west of transit). This position is approximately 18.9&#176; away from
	  pointing position of the antennas during the RFI survey, so the intensity of the interference can
	  be expected to be much higher than shown in <xref linkend="rfi_survey_15mm_equ"></xref> for pointings
	  closer to the satellite.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The recommended <acronym>CABB</acronym> continuum central frequencies for the 15mm band were 17 and 19 GHz,
	  but these may now contain a significant amount of RFI from &#x201C;Sky Muster&#x201D;, depending on
	  where your source is. If you are worried about this interference and wish to avoid it, we recommend
	  a new set of continuum central frequencies of 16.7 and 21.2 GHz. These recommended frequency bands
	  are not contiguous, but do avoid all the &#x201C;Sky Muster&#x201D; downlink emissions and in fact are
	  slightly more (between 3 and 10%) sensitive than the 17/19 GHz bands. If you need to use the 17/19 GHz
	  bands now in order to facilitate comparisons to data obtained in the past, you will likely need to
	  do extensive flagging during data reduction; the reduced bandwidth lost to flagging will also mean that
	  your continuum sensitivity suffers.
	</para>
	
      </section>

      <section id="interference_solar">
	<info>
	  <title>Solar Interference</title>
	</info>
	<para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>interference</primary><secondary>Solar</secondary></indexterm>
	  To avoid Solar interference, a rule-of-thumb is to observe at a time
	  of year when your source is further than about 40&#x00B0; from
	  the Sun, where possible. It is recommended to specify in your proposal
	  dates that are not suitable for observations if the Sun angle is too
	  small.  Low-frequency observations, particularly in spectral-line
	  mode, should be made at greater Solar separations. You are advised to observe
	  at night in cases where good quality 21cm HI data is essential
	  on the shortest (30m) baseline.  For spectral-line observations,
	  software exists in <application>Miriad</application> to model and subtract out solar
	  interference. Some information about solar activity can be obtained
	  from the <ulink url="http://www.ips.gov.au/">Ionospheric Prediction Service</ulink>.
	</para>
      </section>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="Choosing-Angular-and-Frequency-Resolution">
    <info>
      <title>Choosing Angular and Frequency Resolution</title>
    </info>
    <section id="Image-Complexity">
      <info>
        <title>Image Complexity, Angular Resolution and Observing Time</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	A synthesis imaging telescope such as the Compact Array provides a
	great deal of flexibility when deciding how to image an object. In
	addition to the well-known trade-off between observing time and
	sensitivity, we have trade-offs with maximum resolution and with the
	sampling interval in the visibility plane.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>resolution</primary><secondary>angular</secondary></indexterm>
	The choice of angular resolution is fairly straightforward. Increased
	angular resolution (resulting from longer baselines) leaves the
	point-source sensitivity constant, but decreases brightness
	sensitivity in proportion to the beam area (see <xref linkend="table_brightness_temperature"></xref>).
      </para>

      <para>
	The choice of (u,v)-plane coverage is more difficult. The
	amount of independent information needed to specify the image should
	not exceed the number of independent (u,v)-plane samples. But
	unfortunately neither of these &#x201C;independents&#x201D; is easily defined. At
	one extreme, consider making a high resolution image of a complex
	source filling the entire primary beam.  In this case full
	(u,v)-coverage is obtained by using all baselines between 30m
	and 6000m in increments of 15m. Although this was theoretically
	possible (it takes 25 separate array configurations), it was never
	attempted and, since the decommissioning of the second 6km station,
	is no longer actually possible!
      </para>

      <para>
	If on the other hand the image is smaller than the primary beam then
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>sampling</primary><secondary>Nyquist</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>sampling</primary><secondary>uv</secondary></indexterm>
	the Nyquist sampling interval is larger and the number of
	(u,v)-samples required is reduced. The observing time can then
	be reduced either by decreasing the number of configurations or the
	amount of hour angle coverage, depending on the array configuration.
	For east-west arrays, reducing the total number of configurations is
	the more practical option. If the source is large but partly empty it
	can be considered to have a size corresponding to its area.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	For ordinary observations Table 1.4 gives the maximum sizes of structures that
	can be reliably imaged for typical sets of observing configurations.
	This is only a rough guide since the actual coverage needed depends on
	details of the 2-dimensional brightness distribution, on the actual
	distribution of baselines, and on the type of deconvolution.
	Additionally, other techniques such as <link linkend="Mosaicing">mosaicing</link>
	and <link linkend="Multi-frequency-Synthesis">multi-frequency synthesis</link>,
	can be extremely effective at improving (u,v)-coverage.
      </para>

      <para>
	A further consideration is the minimum spacing available. This is
	never less than 30 m and for a given configuration can be much larger.
	This acts as a high-pass filter removing all Fourier components less
	than the minimum spacing.  If this is a serious problem, short
	baseline information (e.g., from a single dish) can be added
	separately during processing.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Array-Configurations-and-Baselines">
      <info>
        <title>Array Configurations and Baselines</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	Antenna 6 sits permanently on station W392. Maximum baselines to this
	antenna (the last 5 columns) are shown for all configurations in
	<xref linkend="ATCA-Array-Configurations"></xref>, but
	form part of a designed array only for configurations 6.0A to 6.0D.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>ATCA</primary><secondary>configurations</secondary></indexterm>
	The antennas can be moved to, and set up on, a limited number of fixed
	stations. Because of this and other physical restraints, the shortest
	spacing available is 30 m, the longest is 6 km, and the minimum
	grating increment is 15 m.  
<!-- Predetermined east-west configurations are
	offered, each with approximately uniform spacings, and thus with good
	single-day (u,v)-coverage. -->
From 2006 October, the standard set
	of configurations has been:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>1  hybrid configuration with a nominal maximum baseline of  75 m (H75)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>1  hybrid configuration with a nominal maximum baseline of 168 m (H168)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>1  hybrid configuration with a nominal maximum baseline of 214 m (H214)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>2  east-west configurations with a maximum baseline of about  375 m</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>4  east-west configurations with a maximum baseline of about  750 m</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>4  east-west configurations with a maximum baseline of about 1500 m</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>4  east-west configurations with a maximum baseline of about 6000 m.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	Snapshot observations using the Northern spur in hybrid configurations
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>spur</primary><secondary>Northern</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>snapshot</secondary></indexterm>
	will generate a two-dimensional sampling of the (u,v)-plane. The
	Northern spur was installed so that good coverage of the
	(u,v)-plane was achievable for observations which are limited to
	hour-angles near transit. Observations at mm wavelengths should be
	limited to higher elevations to avoid large atmospheric
	opacities. Hybrid arrays are also useful for observations of northern
	sources which are similarly restricted in hour-angle range.
      </para>

      <para>
	The 6 km antenna may also be added to any of the shorter
	configurations, but in these cases the distribution of array spacings
	is bi-modal.
      </para>

      <para>
	The predetermined set of configurations offered for forthcoming
	observing terms will assist in planning multi-configuration proposals.
	Details of previous configurations and those being offered in coming
	semesters can be found
	<ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/configs.html">on our website</ulink>,
	or see <xref linkend="upcoming_configurations"></xref>.
      </para>

      <para>
	Note that proposals requiring two or more configurations will usually
	be allotted two or more widely separated times; therefore, expect to
	make two or more observing visits, or conduct the second observation
	using remote observing. If you are not allotted all the configurations
	requested, you should re-apply in the next term, as the proposal will
	not be automatically reconsidered.
      </para>

      <para>
	The overall philosophy is that, in each semester, there will be a 6km,
	1.5km, and 750m configuration, and for these baselines, the full set
	of 4 configurations will generally be covered in three semesters.
	Each semester will also contain at least one 375m configuration.
	Analysis of user preferences for the past few years show some
	configurations to be more generally useful (e.g., providing better
	single-configuration (u,v)-coverage), and it is desirable to
	offer these more frequently.  Millimetre observing conditions are
	optimal in the (southern hemisphere) winter, so arrays of 214m or
	smaller will be offered mainly in the April semester.
      </para>

      <para>
	<table frame="all" id="upcoming_configurations">
	  <title>Array configurations that will be offered in future semesters.</title>
	  <tgroup cols="6" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	    <colspec colname="array"/>
	    <colspec colname="sem1"/>
	    <colspec colname="sem2"/>
	    <colspec colname="sem3"/>
	    <colspec colname="sem4"/>
	    <colspec colname="sem5"/>
	    <thead>
	      <row>
		<entry morerows="1" valign="middle">Array</entry>
		<entry namest="sem1" nameend="sem5" align="center">Semester</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>2016OCTS</entry>
		<entry>2017APRS</entry>
		<entry>2017OCTS</entry>
		<entry>2018APRS</entry>
		<entry>2018OCTS</entry>
	      </row>
	    </thead>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry>6A</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>6B</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>6C</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>6D</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>1.5A</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>1.5B</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>1.5C</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>1.5D</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>750A</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>750B</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>750C</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>750D</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>EW367</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>EW352</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>H214</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>H168</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>H75</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry>&#x2022;</entry>
		<entry></entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</table>
      </para>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>configurations</primary><secondary>non-standard</secondary></indexterm>
	Besides the predetermined configurations, you can request any standard
	or non-standard configuration in any term.  When writing your
	application, your scientific justification should include a very
	convincing argument of why you need to use a special array
	configuration, rather than one of those offered for the term.  If you
	realise the need for such a &#x201C;wildcard&#x201D; request for a significant
	amount of observing time (e.g., more than 5 x 12h), you can enhance
	the probability of it being scheduled if you contact <acronym>ATNF</acronym> well in
	advance of the deadline (preferably even before the call for proposals
	announcement).  The wildcard can then be advertised as a potential
	additional configuration for the term, which may then lead to other
	proposers requesting it, and making its scheduling viable.
      </para>

      <para>
	For those who wish to improve their (u,v)-coverage by
	re-observing on different days with different antenna configurations,
	specific sets of configurations combines well, e.g., 6A, 6C, 1.5B and
	1.5D &#x2014; for more details see <xref linkend="ATCA-Array-Configurations"></xref>.
      </para>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>VRI</primary></indexterm>
	An interactive tool, the 
	<ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/astronomy/vri.html"><firstterm>Virtual Radio Interferometer</firstterm></ulink> (<acronym>VRI</acronym>),
	  is available to assist users in exploring the
	  (u,v)-coverage of standard
	  (and non-standard) configurations.
      </para>

      <para>
	It is strongly recommended that the proposer gives a clear indication of
	the maximum extent of their sources. You should also specify the
	maximum and minimum baselines, and the number of configurations (days)
	needed.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Bandwidths-and-correlator">
      <info>
        <title>Bandwidths and correlator</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>CABB</primary><secondary>installation</secondary></indexterm>
	The <acronym>CABB</acronym> now provides a variety of
	frequency resolutions. The available
	resolution options are more commonly denoted by the <acronym>CABB</acronym> configuration that
	is used to provide them. When development of <acronym>CABB</acronym> is complete,
	four correlator configurations will be offered:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">Currently available modes</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
		  <emphasis role="bold">CFB 1M-0.5k</emphasis>: 2048 channels per 2048 MHz continuum IF (1 MHz coarse resolution),
		  and 2048 channels per 1 MHz zoom band (0.5 kHz fine resolution).
		</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
		  <emphasis role="bold">CFB 64M-32k</emphasis>: 32 channels per 2048 MHz continuum IF (64 MHz coarse resolution),
and 2048 channels per 64 MHz zoom band (32 kHz fine resolution).
		</para>
                <para>
		  There is also a &#x201C;hybrid&quot; mode available which provides one continuum 2048 &#x00D7; 1 MHz
		  IF (with no zoom bands), and a second continuum 32 &#x00D7; 64 MHz IF (with up to sixteen 64 MHz zoom bands).
		</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">Modes available in the future</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
		  <emphasis role="bold">CFB 16M-8k</emphasis>: 128 channels per 2048 MHz continuum IF (16 MHz coarse resolution),
		  and 2048 channels per 16 MHz zoom band (8 kHz fine resolution).
		</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
		  <emphasis role="bold">CFB 4M-2k</emphasis>: 512 channels per 2048 MHz continuum IF (4 MHz coarse resolution),
		  and 2048 channels per 4 MHz zoom band (2 kHz fine resolution).
		</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      <para>
	It should be noted that the correlator routinely computes double the number of channels
	as is recorded. This second set of channels is offset from the available set by half the
	channel width, and are there to provide flexibility in choosing the zoom band frequency,
	as well as to ensure that it will always be possible to avoid observing a spectral line at the
	edge of a channel. It is also possible to combine a number of overlapping zoom bands that are separated
	by half a continuum channel into a seamless single zoom band.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="centimetre-observations">
    <info>
      <title>Centimetre Observations (16&#x2013;4 cm bands)</title>
    </info>
    <para>
      The next two sections describe some necessary considerations for both
      centimetre and millimetre observations at the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>. This section on centimetre
      observations is also relevant for millimetre observers and should be read by
      everyone planning to propose for the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>. The millimetre section describes
      some additional requirements specific to millimetre observations.
    </para>
    <para>
      <table frame="all" id="table_brightness_temperature" shortentry="1">
	<titleabbrev>Brightness Temperature Sensitivity Table</titleabbrev>
	<title>
	  Continuum brightness temperature sensitivity (12 hr integration) for
	  bandwidth specified in <xref linkend="table_sensitivity"></xref>, for
	  various arrays.
	</title>
	<tgroup cols="7" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	  <colspec colname="band"/>
	  <colspec colname="a6km"/>
	  <colspec colname="a1.5km"/>
	  <colspec colname="a750m"/>
	  <colspec colname="ew352"/>
	  <colspec colname="h214"/>
	  <colspec colname="h75"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry morerows="1" valign="middle">Band</entry>
	      <entry namest="a6km" nameend="h75" align="center">
		Array
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>6km</entry>
	      <entry>1.5km</entry>
	      <entry>750m</entry>
	      <entry>EW352</entry>
	      <entry>H214</entry>
	      <entry>H75</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>16cm</entry>
	      <entry>0.02 K</entry>
	      <entry>2.1 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.53 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.1 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.1 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.02 mK</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>4cm</entry>
	      <entry>0.01 K</entry>
	      <entry>1.6 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.4 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.07 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.11 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.01 mK</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>15mm</entry>
	      <entry>0.02 K</entry>
	      <entry>2.6 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.65 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.12 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.18 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.02 mK</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>7mm</entry>
	      <entry>0.03 K</entry>
	      <entry>4.8 mK</entry>
	      <entry>1.2 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.22 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.33 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.04 mK</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>3mm</entry>
	      <entry>&#x2014;</entry>
	      <entry>&#x2014;</entry>
	      <entry>&#x2014;</entry>
	      <entry>1.4 mK</entry>
	      <entry>2.1 mK</entry>
	      <entry>0.24 mK</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
    </para>
    
    <section id="Calibration">
      <info>
	<title>Calibration</title>
      </info>
      
      <para>
	It is crucial to obtain good calibration data during your observations, and you must consider
	how much of an overhead calibration will represent before you propose an experiment. A detailed
	description of the calibration required is given in <xref linkend="observations-calibration"></xref>.
      </para>

      <!-- 
      <para>
	There are four classes of data calibration: flux, bandpass, polarization and
	gain.  The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> instrumental bandpass, polarization response and gain
	amplitude are all relatively stable and flux, bandpass and polarization
	calibration can be done just once during an observation. At centimetre
	wavelengths these three calibrations can be performed with an observation of
	B1934-638. This is often called the <firstterm>primary</firstterm> flux calibrator.
	Atmosphere-induced phase and amplitude gains are more variable and brief
	observations of suitable calibrator sources (<firstterm>gain</firstterm> calibrators) are
	usually interleaved with observations of the target source.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>primary flux</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>bandpass</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>gain</secondary></indexterm>
	In addition, observations are made to calibrate aspects of the instrument's
	performance: antenna pointing and instrumental delay. Pointing calibration is
	normally only necessary at short wavelengths 7mm and 3mm, and involves periodic
	observations of a nearby point source.  Differences in signal arrival times at
	the correlator arise from the geometric delay, which can be calculated, and
	instrumental delays, which must be measured. Instrumental delays vary slowly
	and are measured with a single observation of a strong point source at the
	beginning of an observing session.
      </para>
      -->

      <!--
      <section id="Flux-Calibration">
	<info>
          <title>Flux Calibration</title>
	</info>
        <para>
	  All observations must be ultimately related to a compact source in the
	  southern sky with a known, constant flux density. For
	  frequencies below 30 GHz, PKS B1934-638 is used; this source
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>primary flux</secondary></indexterm>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>1934-648</secondary></indexterm>
	  should be observed at least once a day. Its flux density (following a
	  revision of the flux density scale in August 1994) is 12.6, 5.0
	  and 2.7 Jy at 2100, 5500 and 9000 MHz, respectively
	  (<ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/observers/memos/d96783~.pdf">Reynolds 1994</ulink>) and 1.2 and 1.0 Jy
	  at 17000 and 19000 MHz respectively
	  (<ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/calibrators/data/1934-638/1934_12mm.pdf">Sault 2003</ulink>).
	  The flux densities are incorporated in the on-line calibration
	  routine in <command>caobs</command>, and in the miriad calibration software.  For frequencies
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Miriad</primary></indexterm>
	  above 30 GHz, observations of a planet (Uranus is recommended, Mars
	  may be an alternative in the most compact arrays) will be required
	  for primary amplitude calibration (in suitably compact
	  configurations). In the 7mm band, PKS B1934-638 can also be used.
	  Suitable software exists in Miriad for using
	  planetary calibration data.
	</para>
      </section>
      -->

      <!--
      <section id="Gain-Calibration">
	<info>
          <title>Gain Calibration</title>
	</info>
        <para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>gain</secondary></indexterm>
	  The calibrators database gives information on potential sources that may be
	  used to measure the interferometer amplitude/phase calibration. 
	  The on-line system
	  temperature calibration takes out the temporal changes in the electronics gain
	  but does not correct for elevation dependence of either antenna (optical) gain
	  or atmospheric opacity.
	</para>

        <para>
	  A series of brief gain calibrator observations
	  are important to correct for these effects. The gain calibrator should
	  be close to the target source.  Observers concerned
	  with accurate positions will also need to choose a gain
	  calibrator whose J2000 position is accurately known.  It is preferable
	  to make
	  <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\sim2</textobject></inlineequation>
	  min calibrator observations once every
	  <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\sim30</textobject></inlineequation>
	  min. Less-frequent calibration is possible at 16cm and
	  more frequent calibration may be required at 4cm. At 15mm and shorter
	  wavelengths, it is preferable to calibrate as frequently as possible
	  (consistent with not spending too much time off source), unless the
	  array is very compact.
	</para>
	
        <para>
	  In summer, or during the day, phase stability can be poor. Phase
	  stability can be monitored for bright compact sources with <command>vis</command>, or
	  with the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> seeing monitor.
	  <ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/observers/docs/7mm/seeing.pdf">The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> Seeing Monitor page</ulink>
	  describes the system as initially installed. In 2008 a new satellite beacon was adopted, resulting in a
	  change in the frequency from 30GHz to 21GHz.
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>seeing monitor</primary></indexterm>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>satellite</primary><secondary>beacon</secondary></indexterm>
	</para>
	-->

      <para>
	The amount of calibration required will also depend on when the experiment is scheduled.
	Observations requiring maximum phase stability (e.g., at wavelengths less than 6cm) should
	be made in winter, or at night.
      </para>
      
	<!--
        <para>
	  The most up-to-date calibrator list is available by position or
	  flux-limited online search from
	  <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/calibrators/">the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> calibrator database page</ulink>.
	</para>

      </section> -->

	<!--
	<section id="Bandpass-Calibration">
	<info>
          <title>Bandpass Calibration</title>
	</info>
        <para>
	  A spectral-line observation will normally require a bandpass
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>bandpass</secondary></indexterm>
	  calibrator. At low frequencies, the primary calibrator PKS
	  B1934-638 is usually enough, but at wavelengths of 3cm and
	  shorter a source such as 0537-441, 1253-055, or
	  1921-293 (usually &gt;5Jy) may be needed.  The Compact Array
	  bandpasses are stable, and so a single bandpass calibration is
	  normally sufficient, unless you need high dynamic range.
	</para>
      </section> -->
    </section>

    <section id="Sensitivity-Calculations">
      <info>
        <title>Sensitivity Calculations</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	The general expressions for the flux and brightness sensitivities are given
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>sensitivity</primary><secondary>formulae</secondary></indexterm>
	in the document
	<ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/AT-01.17-025.pdf">AT/01.17/025</ulink>,
	and these general expressions have been used in
	<xref linkend="table_sensitivity"></xref>.
	The observer has control of the integration time (
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">t</textobject></inlineequation>),
	bandwidth (<emphasis>B</emphasis>), observing wavelength (
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\lambda</textobject></inlineequation>), number of
	baselines (<emphasis>N</emphasis>) and synthesized beam
	size (
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\theta</textobject></inlineequation>) only, and with these variables and
	the system sensitivity (
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{S}_{\mathrm{sys}}</textobject></inlineequation>),
	the expressions reduce approximately to:
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
            \mathrm{rms\; Flux\; Sensitivity}  = \Delta\mathrm{S} = 7.55\times10^{-5}  \mathrm{S}_{\mathrm{sys}}(\mathrm{N} t \mathrm{B})^{-1/2} \mathrm{Jy},
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
	and
	<informalequation>
	  <textobject role="tex">
            \mathrm{rms\; Brightness\; Sensitivity}  = \Delta\mathrm{T}  =  1.36\times10^{3} \Delta\mathrm{S}
	    \lambda^{2}/(\theta_\alpha\theta_\delta) \mathrm{K},
	  </textobject>
	</informalequation>
        where
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\mathrm{S}_{\mathrm{sys}}</textobject></inlineequation>
	is in Jy,
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">t</textobject></inlineequation>
	in min, <emphasis>B</emphasis> in MHz,
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\lambda</textobject></inlineequation>
	in cm, and
	<inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\theta</textobject></inlineequation>
	is in arcsec. For the full 6 km array, <emphasis>N</emphasis>=15.
	There is a convenient
	<ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/myatca/interactive_senscalc.html"><acronym>ATCA</acronym> sensitivity calculator</ulink>
	  which takes into account system temperature, observing frequency,
	  array, correlator configuration and (u,v)-weighting.  
	  (A pre-CABB version of the calculator is also available on the ATCA web page
	  for use when considering the utility of archival ATCA data.)
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="millimetre-observations">
    <info>
      <title>Millimetre-wave observations (15mm&#x2013;3mm)</title>
    </info>
    <para>
      Technical details of the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> mm systems are presented in
      <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/EuMW2004Gough.pdf">MMICS for the AT mm-wave receiver system</ulink>
      by Gough et al. (Proc. 12th European Gallium Arsenide and other Compound Semiconductors 
      Application Symposium, 2004, pp.359-362) and
      <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/EuMC2008Moorey.pdf">Cryogenically Cooled mm-wave Front 
      Ends for the Australia Telescope</ulink>
      by Moorey et al. (Proc. European Microwave Conference, 2008, pp.155-158). This section builds on many of the
      concepts described in the previous section on centimetre wavelength observations,
      which should be read before reading this section.
    </para>

    <section id="15mm-Observations">
      <info>
	<title>15mm Observations</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	All six antennas of the Compact Array are equipped with 15mm receivers
	covering the frequency range 16&#x2013;25 GHz.  The 15mm system shares a
	common dewar with the 7mm and 3mm receivers, and the separate feed horns
	at the top of the dewar are moved to the Cassegrain focus of the
	Compact Array antennas using the rotator positioning system. Because
	the 15, 7 and 3 mm receivers have separate feed horns, observations
	cannot be simultaneous between the 15, 7 and 3 mm bands.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="7mm-Observations">
      <info>
	<title>7mm Observations</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> can observe within the frequency range 30&#x2013;50GHz.  Feeds and
	receivers were installed into the existing mm-wave receiver packages on
	all 6 antennas in 2007, with the 7mm upgrade jointly funded by the
	<acronym>ATNF</acronym> and NASA's Deep Space Network to enable the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> to participate
	in occasional spacecraft tracking.
      </para>

      <para>
	The wide 7mm band presents difficulties in signal down-conversion,
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>down-conversion</primary><secondary>7mm</secondary></indexterm>
	as the aliased signal from the first down conversion stage can also
	be within the 7mm band. Although image rejection filters are used,
	variations in receiver gain across the band, combined with the
	frequency-dependent performance of the filters themselves, can result
	in appreciable signal levels being added to the observing band.
	Generally, this aliased signal does not cross-correlate and is present
	as a contribution to the noise level. However, in some circumstances,
	notably as the delay rate drops to zero (e.g., around source transit on
	north-south baselines), the aliased component can cross-correlate and
	be visible as &#x201C;beating&quot; on some baselines. This data must be flagged
	during the data processing.
      </para>

<!--      <para>
	A swap-program may, if possible, be scheduled for 7mm projects &#x2014;
	see the following section for details.
      </para>
-->
    </section>

    <section id="observations-3mm">
      <info>
        <title>3mm Observations</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	The inner five <acronym>ATCA</acronym> telescopes (i.e., excluding CA06) are outfitted
	with a 3mm receiver and can observe in the range 83 to 105 GHz.
	A noise diode has been added to the 3mm system on CA02 (only) to aid
	with 3mm polarisation calibration.  Aliasing effects similar to those
	described at 7mm can also arise in the 3mm band.
      </para>

      <para>
	A limited form of flexible scheduling is operational for observations
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>schedule</primary><secondary>flexible</secondary></indexterm>
	at millimetre wavelengths. Consult the document 
	<ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/flexsched.html"><wordasword>Flexible Scheduling
	at ATCA</wordasword></ulink> for details.
      </para>

      <para>
	A
	<ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/observers/docs/3mm/quickstart.html">quickstart guide for 3mm observing</ulink>
	is also available.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Procedure-for-mm-observations">
      <info>
        <title>Procedure for mm observations</title>
      </info>
      <!-- \label{s:mm_obsproc} -->
      <para>
	Observations in the mm band are run from a schedule file in the same way as
	cm-band observations. However, due to the effects of atmosphere stability, mm
	observations require bandpass and phase-calibration checks at a much more
	frequent rate.
      </para>

      <para>
	Note that as <acronym>ATCA</acronym> does not Doppler track, it is important to have a
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>Doppler tracking</primary></indexterm>
	good estimation of the magnitude of the Doppler shift for the line of
	interest. This is particularly so for the higher frequencies available to the
	3mm system. The sky frequency can be calculated using an
	<ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/obstools/velo.html">online calculator</ulink>.
      </para>

      <para>
	A simple phase reference observation takes about an hour to run,
	including calibration. The following procedure is typical:
      </para>

      <para>
	Pointing calibration
	&#x2192; Paddle calibration
	&#x2192; Bandpass/Phase calibrator
	&#x2192; Target source
	&#x2192; Paddle calibration
	&#x2192; Bandpass/Phase calibration
	&#x2192; Target observation.
      </para>

      <para>
	The
	<ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/sched/cabb/"><acronym>CABB</acronym> web scheduler</ulink>
	can be used to construct the observing schedule.
      </para>

      <section id="Warnings-for-mm-observations">
	<info>
          <title>Warnings for mm observations</title>
	</info>
        <para>
	  Elevation angles close to
	  the array horizon should be avoided because of the increased opacity
	  and poorer atmospheric stability. Therefore, observations of objects
	  with a declination further north of -50&#x00B0; are best
	  made using hybrid configurations (i.e., one using the N-S spur) in order
	  to achieve sufficient (u,v)-coverage.
	</para>

        <para>
	  Observations using very compact telescope configurations should be
	  made with caution, as telescope shadowing can be a significant
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>shadowing</primary></indexterm>
	  problem, especially for sources at declinations which do not achieve
	  elevations high above the horizon. See
	  <xref linkend="Shadowing-Diagrams"></xref>
	  for details.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <!-- <section id="Calibration3">
      <info>
        <title>Calibration</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	The first stage of calibration in any observation is delay calibration, which is
described in detail in chapter 3. 
      </para>

      <section id="Flux-calibration">
	<info>
          <title>Flux calibration</title>
	</info>
        <para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>primary flux</secondary></indexterm>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>planets</primary></indexterm>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>planets</primary><secondary>Uranus</secondary></indexterm>
	  At wavelengths shorter than a few centimetres, extra-galactic sources are generally
	  too variable to be useful as flux density calibrators. So at these
	  wavelengths, the blackbody emission from the planets are often used as flux
	  standards. The two most commonly used planets for the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> at 3mm are Uranus and Mars. Jupiter is too large for use as an <acronym>ATCA</acronym> flux density calibrator.
	  Neptune could be used as a flux density calibrator, however, it is currently
	  quite close to Uranus and only half as bright, and so does not offer anything
	  over Uranus.
	</para>

        <para>
	  Uranus is the preferred flux density calibrator for the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>. Mars is less
	  suitable for a number of reasons: some models of Mars' average brightness
	  temperature suggest variations in the temperature of up to 10% as a result of
	  Mars' diurnal rotation, its distance from the Sun and the viewing geometry of
	  Earth-based observers. Definitive measurements and confirmation of these
	  models are poorly studied in the literature. Depending on its distance and the
	  array configuration, structure on Mars is also readily detected with the
	  <acronym>ATCA</acronym>: Mars has hot equatorial and cold polar regions.
	</para>

        <para>
	  Details of planet rise and set times can be determined using
	  <ulink url="http://www.parkes.atnf.csiro.au/cgi-bin/utilities/planets.cgi">an online calculator tool</ulink>.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section id="Bandpass-calibration">
	<info>
          <title>Bandpass calibration</title>
	</info>
        <para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>bandpass</secondary></indexterm>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>delay</secondary></indexterm>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>pointing</secondary></indexterm>
	  Bright extragalactic continuum sources
	  (such as 0537-441, 1253-055, or 1921-293)
	  are useful for bandpass and delay
	  calibration as well as pointing.  A 15 minute integration will usually
	  provide an adequate bandpass, except at the narrowest bandwidths where extra
	  time should be allowed.  Refer to the
	  <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/calibrators"><acronym>ATNF</acronym> calibrator catalogue</ulink>
	  and use the form to select bright sources (by specifying a lower limit
	  to the flux density) near your target source &#x2013; but be sure to avoid
	  Cen A (1322-427) at cm wavelengths and other sources with
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>defect</secondary></indexterm>
	  large &#x201C;defects&quot; (see
	  catalogue webpages for details) at your frequency in your array, and
	  resolved planets.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section id="Gain-calibration">
	<info>
          <title>Gain calibration</title>
	</info>
        <para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>gain</secondary></indexterm>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>phase</secondary></indexterm>
	  To find the nearest gain calibrator to your source, use the position and
	  flux-limited calibrator online search engine from the
	  <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/calibrators"><acronym>ATNF</acronym> calibrator catalogue</ulink>.
	  The list of calibrators interrogated by this engine includes OVRO and BIMA
	  sources, which will be useful for observations of sources north of
	  -30&#x00B0;. The CABB scheduler provides a direct interface to the calibrator database.
	</para>

        <para>
	  The spatial and time separation of source and phase calibrator
	  measurements has a strong dependence on telescope configuration and
	  the atmospheric conditions. The
	  <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/calibrators/calcycle.html"><acronym>ATNF</acronym> online calibrator cycle calculator</ulink>
	  can be used to estimate of the rate of gain calibrator measurements for a
	  number of different phase decorrelation percentages.
	</para>

        <para>
	  Daytime observations, or observations with long baselines should require
	  much more frequent gain calibration measurements than those made during
	  nighttime observations and with compact configurations.
	</para>

      </section>

      <section id="Pointing-calibration">
	<info>
          <title>Pointing calibration</title>
	</info>
        <para>
	  Regular pointing checks (every hour or so) are essential because of the
	  small size of the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> primary beam at mm wavelengths. Pointing corrections are
	  valid within an area with a diameter of around 15-20 degrees, centred
	  on the azimuth/elevation of the pointing scan.
	</para>

        <para>
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>pointing</secondary></indexterm>
	  To refine your pointing during your observation, it is best to choose
	  a pointing calibrator near your target source (within 10&#x00B0;
	  if possible), not only because the pointing changes with position, but
	  also because you will want to observe it throughout your run.
	  Generally, any quasar with a flux density of 100 mJy or more will suffice.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section id="Paddle-calibration">
	<info>
          <title>Paddle (vane) calibration</title>
	</info>
        <para>
	  At millimetre wavelengths, the atmosphere can no longer be approximated as
	  perfectly transparent. It degrades overall sensitivity in two ways: the
	  atmosphere emits radiation, and so raises the system temperature, and the
	  atmosphere attenuates the astronomical signal. For <acronym>ATCA</acronym> at 3mm wavelength,
	  the effect of the atmospheric opacity is corrected for via a measurement of
	  the effective system temperature - the the so-called &#x201C;above atmosphere&#x201D; system
	  temperature. More details are available in the MIRIAD User Guide.
	</para>

        <para>
	  The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> uses the paddle, or vane, calibration method
	  in its 3mm system to determine an above-atmosphere system temperature. This
	  involves placing an ambient load (paddle) in front of the receiver horn.
	  This is a standard procedure at 3mm wavelengths for placing the
	  amplitudes on a brightness temperature scale.  You will need to include
	  periodic paddle measurements in your schedule file &#x2014; about every
	  10&#x2013;20 minutes.  The entire paddle scan takes about 2 minutes.
	  <indexterm role="cp"><primary>paddle</primary></indexterm>
	</para>
      </section> 
    </section> -->
  </section>


  <section id="Additional-Observing-Notes-and-Techniques">
    <info>
      <title>Additional Observing Notes and Techniques</title>
    </info>
    <section id="Short-Observations">
      <info>
        <title>Short Observations</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>short</secondary></indexterm>
	You may not wish to make detailed high resolution images but instead,
	for example, survey a large number of compact or simple sources. Under
	these circumstances, if the sources are strong enough, short
	observations will suffice (<xref linkend="table_image_structure"></xref>).  In scheduling
	these, slew time becomes an important consideration; these may be
	calculated see <xref linkend="Mosaicing"></xref>, or
	with the use of the CABB scheduler. A single short observation in an
	E-W array will give a 1-dimensional (u,v)-coverage; two or more
	short observations will give some 2-dimensional information.  In such
	short observations consequent higher sidelobe levels will exacerbate
	problems caused by confusing sources in the primary beam. Because the
	Compact Array has poor (u,v)-coverage, in contrast to its good
	sensitivity, this confusion makes it difficult to reach the receiver
	noise limit when observing weak sources or searching for detections,
	particularly at lower frequencies. Current experience suggests that at
	6cm at least 8 short observations well distributed in hour angle are
	needed to reduce confusion to the noise level.  At 16cm, short
	observations are unlikely to ever reach the noise limit.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	<table frame="all" id="table_image_structure">
	  <title>Largest well-imaged structure at 6cm wavelength.</title>
	  <tgroup cols="4" align="center" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
	    <colspec colname="time"/>
	    <colspec colname="a6km"/>
	    <colspec colname="a1.5km"/>
	    <colspec colname="a750m"/>
	    <thead>
	      <row>
		<entry>Observing Time</entry>
		<entry>6 or 3 km</entry>
		<entry>1.5 km</entry>
		<entry>750 m</entry>
	      </row>
	    </thead>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry>25 days</entry>
		<entry>
		  6&#x2032;
		  <footnote>
		    <para>
		      For other wavelengths, scale sizes by
		      <inlineequation><textobject role="tex">\lambda</textobject></inlineequation> / 6 cm.
		    </para>
		  </footnote>
		</entry>
		<entry>&#x2014;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2014;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>12 days</entry>
		<entry>4.5&#x2032;</entry>
		<entry>6&#x2032;</entry>
		<entry>&#x2014;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>4 days</entry>
		<entry>160&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>4&#x2032;</entry>
		<entry>8&#x2032;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>2 days</entry>
		<entry>115&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>160&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>5&#x2032;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>1 day</entry>
		<entry>80&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>115&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>230&#x2033;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>
		  6 x 1-10 min
		  <footnote>
		    <para>
		      Well distributed in hour angle.
		    </para>
		  </footnote>
		</entry>
		<entry>30&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>50&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>100&#x2033;</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>
		  1-10 min
		  <footnote>
		    <para>
		      One-dimensional information only.
		    </para>
		  </footnote>
		</entry>
		<entry>20&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>40&#x2033;</entry>
		<entry>80&#x2033;</entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</table>
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id="Polarimetry">
      <info>
        <title>Polarimetry</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary></indexterm>
	Two orthogonal linear polarisations are measured simultaneously. The
	position angle of the polarisation splitter is stationary with respect
	to the alt-az&#x2013;mounted antennas and so rotates on the sky. A suite of
	tasks in <application>Miriad</application> is available for polarimetric calibration of Compact
	Array data.  No specific calibrators, other than the usual flux and
	gain calibrators, are needed for polarisation calibration. An
	observation of B1934-638 is essential when only making short
	observations.  Small drifts with time can be corrected for using the
	on-line measurements of the <emphasis>XY</emphasis> phase differences to an accuracy
	of 0.5 degrees at all bands.  Best polarimetric calibration results
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>polarisation</secondary></indexterm>
	when the gain calibrator is observed at a good sampling of
	different parallactic angles.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>Miriad</primary></indexterm>
	<application>Miriad</application> is routinely used to calibrate data in all bands, with
	consistent results being achieved over several months in the cm bands.
	The on-axis instrumental polarisation is typically below 2-3%.  After
	calibrating for instrumental polarisation, we are currently able to
	reduce on-axis instrumental effects to 0.1%, and better with some
	care. Procedures for 3mm polarisation observations are still being
	established.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary><secondary>off-axis</secondary></indexterm>
	The off-axis polarisation increases roughly as the square of the
	distance from the pointing centre at least up to the half-power point.
	At 16, 6 and 3cm, the instrumental polarisation is about 3%,
	1.6% and 3% of the <emphasis>apparent</emphasis> total intensity at the half
	power point, respectively. At 16 and 6cm this error is almost purely
	linearly polarised (there is no circularly polarised component),
	whereas at 3cm the circularly polarised component is somewhat
	less than 1% at the half-power point.
	<!-- Fig @ref{f:pol} shows the -->
	<!-- off-axis linearly polarised response at 20 and 13 cm. -->
	Because the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> antennas have an alt-az mount, the off-axis response
	varies with parallactic angle, and will be smeared out by a factor of
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>parallactic angle</primary></indexterm>
	a few by a long synthesis. This smearing is a function of
	declination. The <application>Miriad</application> task <command>offpol</command> can be used to simulate off-axis
	polarimetric response of a long synthesis observation.  Mosaicing
	smears out the off-axis response still further, by as much as an order
	of magnitude.
      </para>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polarisation</primary><secondary>instrumental</secondary></indexterm>
	At 16cm, instrumental polarisation is largely independent of frequency,
	due to a recent upgrade of the receivers and OMTs. The leakages are now
	flat to better than 2% across the entire usable band. More detail on the
	polarisation properties of the <acronym>ATCA</acronym> 16cm receivers can be found in the
	receiver commissioning report. 
	<!-- make link to that report here -->
	Leakages of more than 10% occur at 4550 &#x00B1; 10,
	5328 &#x00B1; 10 MHz and 8780 &#x00B1; 10 MHz. Data near these
	frequencies may need to be flagged.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Mosaicing">
      <info>
	<title>Mosaicing</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>mosaic</primary></indexterm>
	Objects which are of similar size or larger than the primary beam will need
	to be <firstterm>mosaiced</firstterm>. In such cases, the recommended spacing of pointing
	centres is half of the primary beamwidth. The Compact Array antennas
	and control system allow for rapid switching between pointing centres
	&#x2014; as frequently as once per integration cycle. This enables a source
	to be rapidly mosaiced without necessarily losing
	(u,v)-coverage.  In mosaicing mode, data is not recorded when
	antennas are driving between fields. The antenna acceleration limit is
	800 deg/min/min, and the slew limit is 38 deg/min in azimuth and 19
	deg/min in elevation. Mosaicing mode may also be useful for observing
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>limits</primary><secondary>slewing</secondary></indexterm>
	large numbers of nearby sources, as the observing overheads are
	reduced.
      </para>

      <para>
	There is also a facility for &#x201C;on-the-fly&quot; mosaicing, whereby the
	antennas are continuously driven. This type of mosaicing may be
	especially useful for large-area mosaics at low frequencies, where
	the drive times between mosaic pointings are significant.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	<xref linkend="scheduling-mosaics"></xref> explains how to set up mosaic files.
	The
	<ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/computing/software/miriad/userguide/userhtml.html"><application>Miriad</application> User Guide</ulink>
	describes how to reduce a mosaic data set.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Multi-frequency-Synthesis">
      <info>
        <title>Multi-frequency Synthesis</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>synthesis</primary><secondary>multi-frequency</secondary></indexterm>
	As (u,v)-distance is proportional to frequency as well as
	baseline length, different (u,v)-spacings can be obtained not
	only by varying the antenna configuration, but also by varying the
	frequency.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>sampling</primary><secondary>uv</secondary></indexterm>
	Additional (u,v)-coverage can be obtained in the mm bands by
	observing at multiple frequencies.  Observing at two frequencies has
	the added advantage of increasing sensitivity, as they can be observed
	simultaneously.  Observing more than two frequencies requires time
	sharing. While this will not improve the sensitivity further, it can
	significantly improve the (u,v)-coverage. However, there is a
	trade off between gaps in the tangential and radial directions in the
	(u,v)-plane.  Typically two or three pairs of frequencies,
	observing each setting for 10 minutes, is a good compromise.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>synthesis</primary><secondary>bandwidth</secondary></indexterm>
	When you use both bandwidth synthesis and two or three configurations,
	and require (u,v)-coverage to 6km, the best choice of
	configurations is not two or three 6km arrays, but a combination of
	6km with 1.5km and 750m arrays (all arrays using the 6km antenna).
	<!-- A -->
	<!-- program (@sc{mfplan}) is available in @sc{miriad} to help select configurations -->
	<!-- and determine optimum observing frequencies. -->
	The flux density of most sources will often vary significantly between different
	frequencies and, furthermore, this variation itself (i.e., the
	spectral index) will vary across the source. This complicates the task
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>spectral index</primary></indexterm>
	of combining data from the different frequencies when you want
	high-dynamic-range images. However software is available in <application>Miriad</application> to
	account for the spectral variations in the imaging, deconvolution and
	self-calibration steps. These algorithms solve for, or use, both a
	basic flux-density image and a spectral-index image. For typical
	spectral indices, they are appropriate for frequency ratios less than
	about 1.25.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Reference-Pointing">
      <info>
        <title>Reference Pointing</title>
      </info>
      <!-- \label{s:pointing} -->
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>pointing</primary><secondary>reference</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>pointing</primary><secondary>solution</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>reconfiguration</primary></indexterm>
	After each antenna reconfiguration a pointing solution is determined.
	Generally, rms errors of around 5 arcsec are achieved at this time.
	These solutions degrade with thermal (and other) effects. By the time
	observations are undertaken, rms errors of about 10 arcsec (or more) are likely.
	There is a significant offset (of up to 30 arcsecs) between the mm and the cm receivers.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>calibrator</primary><secondary>pointing</secondary></indexterm>
	A reference pointing mode is available which is recommended for mm observations.
	In this mode, a 1 Jy
	calibrator, about 5&#x00B0; to 10&#x00B0; away from the
	target will hold the pointing to 10 arcsec rms.  A bright (say 5 Jy)
	calibrator at 2&#x00B0; to 3&#x00B0; from the target will
	reduce the errors to about 5 arcsec rms. A reference pointing scan
	generally takes 3-4 minutes to complete. See the
	<ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/pointing">Reference Pointing Guide</ulink>
	for details.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="High_Time_Resolution_Pulsars_Planets_and_VLBI">
    <info>
      <title>High Time Resolution, Pulsars, Planets and VLBI</title>
    </info>
    <section id="High-Time-Resolution-and-Pulsar-Observing">
      <info>
        <title>High Time Resolution and Pulsar Observing</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	In pulsar binning mode, the correlator cycle time (normally 10 seconds) is divided
	into an integer number of pulsar periods. Each pulsar period is further divided into
	N equal time intervals called bins. The integration in the correlator is done
	separately for each bin, such that at the end of the cycle, N quantities are
	produced, each of which represents the integrated value at a particular pulsar phase.
The minimum time bin is around 110 micro-seconds, allowing, for example, 32 phase bins for a 3.5 milli-second pulsar.	
	The correlator will also record both the full 2 GHz continuum bands in addition
	to the pulsar binning data, analagous to how the zoom modes are recorded.
      </para>

      <para>
For high time resolution observations, a time resolution of order 10 milliseconds is possible, though with a reduced number of channels across each 2 GHz band (achieved by averaging over 1 MHz channels). 
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Solar-System-Objects">
      <info>
        <title>Solar System Objects</title>
      </info>
      <!-- \label{s:solar} -->
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>Solar System</secondary></indexterm>
	The Compact Array can track sources with non-sidereal rates, such as
	planets or comets. In this case delay tracking is adjusted
	continuously to account for source proper motion. However the pointing
	tracks a fixed celestial position during a scan. Thus scans must be
	short enough that there is not significant proper motion across the
	primary beam in the course of a scan. This is rarely a problem.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>ephemerides</primary></indexterm>
	JPL ephemerides of the planets are built into the observing program,
	and a simple mechanism exists to import current JPL ephemerides of
	other solar system objects (e.g. new comets).
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Tied-Array-Mode">
      <info>
        <title>Tied Array Mode</title>
      </info>
      <!-- \label{s:cat} -->
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>array</primary><secondary>tied</secondary></indexterm>
	A tied array capability is available.  It provides tying of the array
	at one or two frequencies and, for <acronym>CABB</acronym>, initially at a bandwidth of 64 MHz.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>catie</primary></indexterm>
	The tied array adder is controlled via a process called <literal>catie</literal> which
	runs within cacor. This allows the choice of which antennas are
	included and whether the adder produces linear or circular
	polarisation outputs. The array is phased up in the usual way, and an
	option to allow the insertion of a 90&#x00B0; phase offset
	between the A and B linear polarisations at each antenna &#x2013; thereby
	forming circular polarisation at the tied-array output &#x2013; is available.
      </para>

      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>DAS</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>VLBI</primary></indexterm>
	The tied-array adder can be fed into the LBA (<firstterm>Long Baseline Array</firstterm>)
	DAS which provides outputs for the
	VLBI disk-based recorders at bandwidths between 62.5 kHz and 64 MHz.
	Simultaneous Compact Array and tied array operation is possible, although
	currently this is limited to 64 MHz in both IFs, or 64 MHz in one IF and
	the full 2 GHz (which is not formed into a tied array) in the other.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="Other-Things-to-Consider">
    <info>
      <title>Other Things to Consider</title>
    </info>
    <section id="Confusion">
      <info>
        <title>Confusion</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>confusion</primary></indexterm>
	The presence of field sources in the primary antenna beam can limit
	continuum image quality. These sources produce unwanted sidelobes in
	the images and can lead to dynamic range and aliasing problems. The
	brightest source expected on average in the half-power primary antenna
	beam (away from the Galactic plane) is listed in <xref linkend="table_sensitivity"></xref>.
	Note that confusion becomes much worse as you go
	to lower frequencies, and that this can be particularly serious for
	snapshot observations (See <xref linkend="Short-Observations"></xref>).  The
	<ulink url="http://www.astrop.physics.usyd.edu.au/sumsscat">SUMSS catalogue and database</ulink>,
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>catalogue</primary><secondary>SUMSS</secondary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>catalogue</primary><secondary>MGPS</secondary></indexterm>
	and the
	<ulink url="http://www.physics.usyd.edu.au/sifa/Main/MGPS2">Molonglo Galactic Plane Survey (MGPS-2) catalogue and database</ulink>
	are useful references to search for potential confusing sources in the
	16cm band, where the effects of confusion are greatest.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Weather">
      <info>
        <title>Weather</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>weather effects</secondary></indexterm>
	At short wavelengths and/or long baselines, atmospheric refraction can cause
	serious phase errors. The problem becomes progressively less serious at
	longer wavelengths and shorter baselines. Atmospheric conditions are most
	favourable during winter and at night. A seeing monitor at Narrabri
	continuously monitors the phase stability at a frequency of 21 GHz and
	over a baseline of 200 m.  See
	<ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/observers/docs/7mm/seeing.pdf">The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> Seeing Monitor</ulink>
	for details (though note this paper describes the initial system;
	    in 2008 a new satellite beacon was adopted, resulting in a
	    change in the frequency from 30GHz to 21GHz).
      </para>
      
      <para>
          High winds, storms and extreme heat can damage the antennas.  See <xref linkend="Wind"></xref> to <xref linkend="Heat"></xref> for further details on automated stowing procedures.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="Artefacts">
      <info>
        <title>Artefacts</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	As with other synthesis instruments, system errors such as DC offsets and
	sampler harmonics can lead to artefacts at the centre of the field.
	These artefacts have not yet been observed to affect the data from the
	<acronym>CABB</acronym> correlator, but if such an error would severely degrade your science
	goals (e.g. in a detection experiment), it is preferable to displace the
	source positions a few (synthesized) beamwidths from the field centre.
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>DC offset</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>samplers</primary><see>CABB digitisers</see></indexterm>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>CABB</primary><secondary>digitisers</secondary></indexterm>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section  id="Submitting-a-proposal">
    <info>
      <title>Submitting a proposal</title>
    </info>
    <para>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>proposal</primary><secondary>submitting</secondary></indexterm>
    </para>

    <para>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>proposal</primary><secondary>deadline</secondary></indexterm>
      The Compact Array usually operates under a semester system with two
      application deadlines each year: around June 15 for observations from October
      1 to March 31; and around December 15 for observations from April 1 to
      September 30.
      During each semester array maintenance, upgrades and array
      reconfigurations (moving the antennas to different stations)
      are scheduled in addition to astronomical observations.
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>maintenance</primary></indexterm>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>reconfiguration</primary></indexterm>
      Target of Opportunity (<acronym>ToO</acronym>)
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>target of opportunity</primary></indexterm>
      requests for observations of extremely important transient or
      non-predicted events can be made at any time. To learn how to apply for
      <acronym>ToO</acronym> observing time, visit
      <ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/observers/apply/too_apply.html">our webpage</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Based on previous experience, observing at 3mm usually ends by October
      15, restarting in late April. Detection experiments at 7mm and 15mm
      usually end by October 31, restarting in early March.  Observations of
      bright compact sources, for which self-calibration is possible, may be
      made throughout the year.  Observations at times other than those
      indicated above require an explicit justification in the proposal.
    </para>

    <para>
      Check <ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/observers/apply/avail.html">our web page</ulink>
      for information about the current status of the <acronym>ATNF</acronym> facilities.
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>observations</primary><secondary>millimetre</secondary></indexterm>
      Before submitting proposals to observe particular objects, you should
      check that the observation you are proposing has not already been made.
      Previous Compact Array proposals and observations
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>proposal</primary><secondary>archive</secondary></indexterm>
      can be found in the <ulink url="http://atoa.atnf.csiro.au/"><acronym>ATOA</acronym></ulink>
      (Australia Telescope Online Archive).
      After the proprietary period has expired, the data files from previous
      observations may be downloaded from <acronym>ATOA</acronym>.
<!--
      An archive of older proposals (submitted between 1990 Quarter2 and the
      2005 OCTS observing semester) is held in the
      <ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/observers/search_proj.html">Projects Database</ulink>.
-->
    </para>

    <para>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>OPAL</primary></indexterm>
      All <acronym>ATNF</acronym> Telescope Applications must be submitted using
      <ulink url="http://opal.atnf.csiro.au/"><acronym>OPAL</acronym></ulink>.
    </para>

    <section id="A-Friend">
      <info>
        <title>A &#x201C;Friend&#x201D;</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>friend</primary></indexterm>
	All observing projects are now allocated a &#x201C;friend&#x201D; who can help
	when preparing for observations, and with later data analysis. Friends will only help
	observers who visit the Marsfield <firstterm>Science Operations Centre</firstterm> (<acronym>SOC</acronym>)
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>Science Operations Centre</primary></indexterm> to do their
	observations. Friends are allocated based on their expertise. For those projects with
	<acronym>ATNF</acronym> co-investigators, one of the co-investigators will be assigned as
	the friend.
      </para>

      <para>
	A <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/support/da_support.html">duty astronomer</ulink>
	(<acronym>DA</acronym>)
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>duty astronomer</primary></indexterm>
	is provided at the <acronym>SOC</acronym> who will help in the initial set up of the telescope
	and with any problems which arise in the course of the
	observations. In addition, they may also be able to help with schedule preparation and
	initial data analysis, although requesting the help of your &#x201C;friend&#x201D; is a better option for
	observers that require this help, as they will be involved much earlier than
	the <acronym>DA</acronym>.
	The duty astronomer has no obligation to participate in the observing, however, and should
	not be asked to do so.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="Successful-Proposals">
    <info>
      <title>Successful Proposals and Observing</title>
    </info>
    <para>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>Time Allocation Committee</primary></indexterm>
      After the Time Assignment Committee (<acronym>TAC</acronym>) has met, you will be notified when
      the <acronym>TAC</acronym> grades and feedback on your proposal are available. These are available
      to all members of the proposal team through <acronym>OPAL</acronym>.
      All proposers are notified when the schedule for the next semester is released, and these schedules
      will appear 
      <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/schedules/">on the web</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Generally, at least one member of the observing team must be present
      at the <acronym>SOC</acronym> to do the observations. The visiting observer should be
      well-versed with the needs of their observing program before arriving,
      particularly if they did not write the observing proposal or schedule
      files. If they need assistance from the friend or <acronym>DA</acronym> to prepare
      their schedules, they should arrive well before the start of their observations; at
      least two weekdays.
    </para>

    <para>
      Occupational Health and Safety regulations require that
      observers are not to observe for more than 16 hours, so
      <emphasis role="bold">for long observations you will need more than one observer</emphasis>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Plan your trip to the <acronym>SOC</acronym> with the help of the <acronym>ATNF</acronym>
      <ulink url="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/observers/visit">Visitor's Information</ulink>.
      You will need to book transport,
      accommodation and computer resources in Marsfield before arrival.
    </para>

    <para>
      Note that multi-configuration observations are likely to occur weeks
      or even months apart, so you may need to plan either one long visit
      or several short trips.
      Overseas observers will require a valid visa and
      passport for entry into Australia.
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>visa</primary></indexterm>
    </para>

    <para>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>schedule</primary><secondary>file</secondary></indexterm>
      The Compact Array is controlled from user generated schedule files.
      Schedule files are prepared with
      the <ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/sched"><acronym>CABB</acronym> web scheduler</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Schedules contain source names, positions, frequencies,
      bandwidths, and any other information that
      <command>caobs</command> needs for observations.
    </para>
    <!-- You can prepare your initial schedule as a simple text file, which @sc{atcasched} -->
    <!-- can convert into the form required by the Compact Array's observing -->
    <!-- program. This method (described in @ref{How to Prepare a Schedule File}) -->
    <!-- %CHANGE THIS -->
    <!-- %\hyperref{the Before Observing -->
    <!-- %section}{Chapter }{}{ch3}) -->
    <!-- is recommended for long or complicated schedules. -->
    <para>
      <indexterm role="cp"><primary>coord</primary></indexterm>
      A useful tool to determine the altitude, azimuth,
      and rising and setting times of astronomical objects, which may help
      with preparation of your schedule files, is coord.
      Currently, this is most easily accessed via the
      <ulink url="http://www.parkes.atnf.csiro.au/cgi-bin/utilities/coord.cgi">Parkes website</ulink>.
      When using this tool be sure to change the site to
      Australia Telescope Compact Array, and change the elevation limit to
      12 degrees for cm observing at the <acronym>ATCA</acronym>.
    </para>
    
    <section id="The-Duty-Astronomer">
      <info>
        <title>The Duty Astronomer</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	<indexterm role="cp"><primary>duty astronomer</primary></indexterm>
	A Duty Astronomer will be present at the <acronym>SOC</acronym> to help local observers get
	their observations started, and to help with any problems that arise during the
	observations. Our web site has the 
	<ulink url="http://www.narrabri.atnf.csiro.au/observing/support">list of duty astronomers</ulink>
	for the upcoming semester, as well as for previous semesters.
	The Duty Astronomer has <emphasis role="bold">no obligation</emphasis> to participate in the
	observing.
      </para>

      <para>
	For help before and after your observations, see <xref linkend="A-Friend"></xref>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="NAPA-overrides">
      <info>
	<title>NAPAs, ToOs and over-riding observations</title>
      </info>
      <para>
	The <acronym>ATCA</acronym> is responsive to requests for observations of targets of
	opportunity. There are two paths to such observations: through a <acronym>NAPA</acronym>
	(non-apriori assignable) project, or through a <acronym>ToO</acronym>
	(target of opportunity) request.
      </para>
      <para>
	A <acronym>NAPA</acronym> project is one whose science goals have been set down in a
	proposal that the <acronym>TAC</acronym> has evaluated in the normal way. Such projects
	can be triggered any time during the semester, whenever the investigator wants to
	proceed. The project will have requested a specific amount of time for the semester,
	but this is not binding.
      </para>
      <para>
	A <acronym>ToO</acronym> request can also be made at any time during the semester.
	Unlike <acronym>NAPA</acronym> projects though, a <acronym>ToO</acronym> will not generally
	be allowed to over-ride a scheduled observation.
      </para>
      <section>
	<info>
	  <title>Requesting an observation</title>
	</info>
	<para>
	  The first step to either trigger a <acronym>NAPA</acronym> project, or request a
	  <acronym>ToO</acronym> observation, is to email either the alerts exploder
	  (<email>alert@atnf.csiro.au</email>) or the scheduler directly
	  (<email>Jamie.Stevens@csiro.au</email>); the former is preferable since there is a greater
	  chance of someone seeing the request quickly.
	</para>
	<para>
	  For a <acronym>NAPA</acronym> trigger, you should include in your email the
	  <acronym>NAPA</acronym>'s project code, and some details about the source(s) you
	  are triggering on, including at least right ascensions and declinations. For a
	  <acronym>ToO</acronym> request, you should also include a short scientific justification
	  for why you want to observe.
	</para>
	<para>
	  If you are requesting a slot of Director's time (also known as green time), then you should
	  also put in a request via the Portal's booking system. If you require an over-ride of
	  scheduled time (only available for <acronym>NAPA</acronym> projects), then please state your
	  preferred observation time in your email.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Since the beginning of the 2017OCT semester, it has been possible for almost any <acronym>NAPA</acronym>
	  project to over-ride almost any scheduled project. Any exceptions to this will be made clear
	  in the release notes for the semester, and will be communicated privately to the investigators of
	  <acronym>NAPA</acronym> projects who cannot avail themselves of over-rides.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The observatory will try to make contact with <acronym>NAPA</acronym> requesters as quickly
	  as possible after a trigger has been issued, but sometimes it might not be possible to
	  reach observatory staff (eg. overnight, at weekends, etc.). If the investigators think it necessary,
	  <acronym>NAPA</acronym> projects may over-ride scheduled observations without further consultation with
	  observatory staff. We recommend that in such a case, the investigator wishing to over-ride
	  communicate with the current observer in charge to effect the change to the <acronym>NAPA</acronym>.
	  It should be noted though that if the <acronym>NAPA</acronym> project has already used up the
	  time that it requested for the semester, it is no longer entitled to over-ride scheduled time and
	  must use Director's time instead.
	</para>
	<para>
	  In the case that a <acronym>NAPA</acronym> investigator wants to start observing, and the telescope
	  is idle, the current time is unallocated, and there is no observer in charge, they may proceed without
	  any further consultation. This is true for any <acronym>NAPA</acronym> project, even those which may
	  not have achieved the grade required to over-ride scheduled time. The investigator must though notify
	  any observers who may want to start their scheduled observations. Even if the time is unallocated,
	  the telescope is idle, and there is no observer in charge, a <acronym>ToO</acronym> observation should
	  not assume control of the telescope without permission from observatory staff, since it may be that
	  their science request conflicts with another scheduled project.
	</para>
	<para>
	  For <acronym>NAPA</acronym> projects which require very prompt response to a trigger, we recommend
	  the use of the rapid response mode (<xref linkend="rapid-response-mode"></xref>). Use of this mode is limited in the same
	  way as for a normal <acronym>NAPA</acronym>, but an email request does not need to be sent prior to the
	  trigger, and the observing system will manage the transition to the <acronym>NAPA</acronym> observations
	  automatically. The investigators of each project that is over-ridden by a rapid response trigger will
	  be notified by email of the displacement, at the time of the trigger.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Otherwise, observatory staff will try to find a time that maximises the science output of the <acronym>NAPA</acronym>
	  or <acronym>ToO</acronym> request, and minimises the disruption
	  to scheduled time. In any event, all affected investigators will be notified by email as soon as possible
	  after the decision is made.
	</para>
	<para>
	  If multiple requests are received to look at the same target, then staff will need to decide how
	  to allocate the time. In general, <acronym>NAPA</acronym> projects will be prioritised over
	  <acronym>ToO</acronym> requests, because the <acronym>TAC</acronym> has already evaluated the
	  science cases for the <acronym>NAPA</acronym>s. This will hold even if the <acronym>NAPA</acronym>
	  project has exhausted its time allocation for the semester. If multiple <acronym>NAPA</acronym>
	  requests are made for the same target, then both the <acronym>TAC</acronym> ranking score and the
	  order in which the requests were received will be considered.
	</para>
	<para>
	  It is possible for one <acronym>NAPA</acronym> to be over-ridden by another <acronym>NAPA</acronym>,
	  if the observatory staff think it appropriate to do so. In such a case, it would be inappropriate for
	  a <acronym>NAPA</acronym> investigator to take control of the telescope without first consulting with
	  observatory staff.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Rapid response observations are a special case: the automatic system does not need staff
	  interaction to work, and so if a rapid response request arrives while another <acronym>NAPA</acronym>
	  project is being observed, the rapid response over-ride will take priority. Once a rapid response
	  over-ride is being observed, it must be allowed to run for its allocated duration, and the automatic
	  system will reissue the over-ride should the observation be interrupted. Observatory staff do though have
	  the power to stop a rapid response over-ride observation if necessary.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
